Abbreviated Texts on Appointments

AN 5.272 A Meal Assigner Bhattuddesakasutta

“Mendicants, someone with five qualities should not be appointed as meal assigner. What five? They make decisions prejudiced by favoritism, hostility, stupidity, and cowardice. And they don’t know if a meal has been assigned or not. Someone with these five qualities should not be appointed as meal assigner.

Someone with five qualities should be appointed as meal assigner. What five? They don’t make decisions prejudiced by favoritism, hostility, stupidity, and cowardice. And they know if a meal has been assigned or not. Someone with these five qualities should be appointed as meal assigner.

Someone with five qualities who has been appointed as meal assigner should not be called upon … should be called upon … should be known as a fool … should be known as astute … they keep themselves broken and damaged … they keep themselves unbroken and undamaged … is placed in hell as if delivered there … is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What five? They don’t make decisions prejudiced by favoritism, hostility, stupidity, and cowardice. And they know if a meal has been assigned or not. A meal assigner with these five qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 5.273–285 A Lodgings Allotter Senāsanapaññāpakasuttādi

“Mendicants, someone with five qualities should not be appointed as lodgings allotter … they don’t know if a lodging has been allotted or not … Someone with five qualities should be appointed as lodgings allotter … they know if a lodging has been allotted or not …

A person should not be appointed as lodgings allocator … they don’t know if a lodging has been allocated or not … A person should be appointed as lodgings allocator … they know if a lodging has been allocated or not …

A person should not be appointed as storeperson … they don’t know if stores are protected or not … A person should be appointed as storeperson … they know if stores are protected or not …

… robe receiver …

… robe distributor …

… porridge distributor …

… fruit distributor …

… cake distributor …

… dispenser of minor accessories …

… allocator of bathing cloths …

… bowl allocator …

… supervisor of monastery staff …

… supervisor of novices …

What five? They don’t make decisions prejudiced by favoritism, hostility, stupidity, and cowardice. And they know if a novice has been supervised or not. A supervisor of novices with these five qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

The Chapter on Perceptions

AN 5.61 Perceptions (1st) Paṭhamasaññāsutta

“Mendicants, these five perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination. What five? The perceptions of ugliness, death, drawbacks, repulsiveness of food, and dissatisfaction with the whole world. These five perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination.”

AN 5.62 Perceptions (2nd) Dutiyasaññāsutta

“Mendicants, these five perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination. What five? The perceptions of impermanence, not-self, death, repulsiveness of food, and dissatisfaction with the whole world. These five perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination.”

AN 5.63 Growth (1st) Paṭhamavaḍḍhisutta

“Mendicants, a male noble disciple who grows in five ways grows nobly, taking on what is essential and excellent in this life. What five? He grows in faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. A male noble disciple who grows in these five ways grows nobly, taking on what is essential and excellent in this life.

He who grows in faith and ethics,
wisdom, and both generosity and learning—
a good man such as he sees clearly,
and takes on what is essential for himself in this life.”

AN 5.64 Growth (2nd) Dutiyavaḍḍhisutta

“Mendicants, a female noble disciple who grows in five ways grows nobly, taking on what is essential and excellent in this life. What five? She grows in faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. A female noble disciple who grows in these five ways grows nobly, taking on what is essential and excellent in this life.

She who grows in faith and ethics,
wisdom, and both generosity and learning—
a virtuous laywoman such as she
takes on what is essential for herself in this life.”

AN 5.65 Discussion Sākacchasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with five qualities is fit to hold a discussion with their spiritual companions. What five?

A mendicant is personally accomplished in ethics, and answers questions that come up when discussing accomplishment in ethics.

They’re personally accomplished in immersion, and they answer questions that come up when discussing accomplishment in immersion.

They’re personally accomplished in wisdom, and they answer questions that come up when discussing accomplishment in wisdom.

They’re personally accomplished in freedom, and they answer questions that come up when discussing accomplishment in freedom.

They’re personally accomplished in the knowledge and vision of freedom, and they answer questions that come up when discussing accomplishment in the knowledge and vision of freedom.

A mendicant with these five qualities is fit to hold a discussion with their spiritual companions.”

AN 5.66 Sharing Life Sājīvasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with five qualities is fit to share their life with their spiritual companions. What five?

A mendicant is personally accomplished in ethics, and answers questions posed when discussing accomplishment in ethics.

They’re personally accomplished in immersion, and they answer questions posed when discussing accomplishment in immersion.

They’re personally accomplished in wisdom, and they answer questions posed when discussing accomplishment in wisdom.

They’re personally accomplished in freedom, and they answer questions posed when discussing accomplishment in freedom.

They’re personally accomplished in the knowledge and vision of freedom, and they answer questions posed when discussing accomplishment in the knowledge and vision of freedom.

A mendicant with these five qualities is fit to share their life with their spiritual companions.”

AN 5.67 Bases of Psychic Power (1st) Paṭhamaiddhipādasutta

“Mendicants, any monk or nun who develops and cultivates five qualities can expect one of two results: enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return.

What five?

A mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort …

A mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy, and active effort …

A mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to mental development, and active effort …

A mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to inquiry, and active effort.

And the fifth is sheer vigor.

Any monk or nun who develops and cultivates these five qualities can expect one of two results: enlightenment in this very life, or if there’s residue left behind, non-return.”

AN 5.68 Bases of Psychic Power (2nd) Dutiyaiddhipādasutta

“Mendicants, before my awakening—when I was still not awake but intent on awakening—I developed and cultivated five things. What five?

The basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort … the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy, and active effort … the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to mental development, and active effort … the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to inquiry, and active effort. And the fifth is sheer vigor.

When I had developed and cultivated these five things, with vigor as fifth, I extended the mind to realize by insight each and every thing that can be realized by insight; and I was capable of realizing those things, since each and every one was within range.

If I wished: ‘May I multiply myself and become one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity.’ I was capable of realizing it, since each and every one is within range.

If I wished: … ‘May I realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with my own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.’ I was capable of realizing it, since each and every one is within range.”

AN 5.69 Disillusionment Nibbidāsutta

“Mendicants, these five things, when developed and cultivated, lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.

What five? A mendicant meditates observing the ugliness of the body, perceives the repulsiveness of food, perceives dissatisfaction with the whole world, observes the impermanence of all conditions, and has well established the perception of their own death.

These five things, when developed and cultivated, lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment.”

AN 5.70 The Ending of Defilements Āsavakkhayasutta

“Mendicants, these five things, when developed and cultivated, lead to the ending of defilements. What five? A mendicant meditates observing the ugliness of the body, perceives the repulsiveness of food, perceives dissatisfaction with the whole world, observes the impermanence of all conditions, and has well established the perception of their own death. These five things, when developed and cultivated, lead to the ending of defilements.”

Abbreviated Texts on Training Rules

AN 5.286 A Monk Bhikkhusutta

“Mendicants, a monk with five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What five? He kills living creatures, steals, has sex, lies, and consumes intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. A monk with these five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

A monk with five qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What five? He doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, have sex, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. A monk with these five qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 5.287–292 A Nun Bhikkhunīsuttādi

“A nun … trainee nun … novice monk … novice nun … layman … laywoman … with five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What five? They kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, and consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. With these five qualities they’re placed in hell as if delivered there.

A nun … trainee nun … novice monk … novice nun … layman … laywoman … with five qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What five? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. With these five qualities they’re placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 5.293 An Ājīvaka Ājīvakasutta

“Mendicants, an Ājīvaka ascetic with five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What five? They kill living creatures, steal, have sex, lie, and consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. An Ājīvaka ascetic with these five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.”

AN 5.294–302 A Jain Ascetic, Etc. Nigaṇṭhasuttādi

“A Jain ascetic … disciple of the shavelings … a matted-hair ascetic … a wanderer … a follower of Māgaṇḍiya … a trident-bearing ascetic … a follower of the unobstructed … a follower of Gotama … a performer of rituals for the gods … with five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What five? They kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, and consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. With these five qualities they’re placed in hell as if delivered there.”

The Chapter with Sumanā

AN 5.31 With Sumanā Sumanasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Then Princess Sumanā, escorted by five hundred chariots and five hundred royal maidens, went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, suppose there were two disciples equal in faith, ethics, and wisdom. One is a giver, one is not. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. When they have become gods, would there be any distinction or difference between them?”

“There would be, Sumanā,” said the Buddha.

“As a god, the one who was a giver surpasses the other in five respects: heavenly lifespan, beauty, happiness, glory, and sovereignty. As a god, the one who was a giver surpasses the other in these five respects.”

“But sir, if they pass away from there and come back to this place as human beings, would there still be any distinction or difference between them?”

“There would be, Sumanā,” said the Buddha.

“As a human being, the one who was a giver surpasses the other in five respects: human lifespan, beauty, happiness, glory, and sovereignty. As a human being, the one who was a giver surpasses the other in these five respects.”

“But sir, if they both go forth from the lay life to homelessness, would there still be any distinction or difference between them?”

“There would be, Sumanā,” said the Buddha.

“As a renunciate, the one who was a giver surpasses the other in five respects. They usually use only what they’ve been invited to accept—robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick—rarely using them without invitation. When living with other spiritual practitioners, they usually find themselves treated agreeably by them by way of body, speech, and mind, and rarely disagreeably. And they are usually presented with agreeable things by them, rarely with disagreeable ones. As a renunciate, the one who was a giver surpasses the other in these five respects.”

“But sir, if they both attain perfection, as perfected ones would there still be any distinction or difference between them?”

“In that case, I say there is no difference between the freedom of one and the freedom of the other.”

“It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! This is quite enough to justify giving gifts and making merit. For merit is helpful for those who have become gods, human beings, and renunciates.”

“That’s so true, Sumanā. It’s quite enough to justify giving gifts and making merit. For merit is helpful for those who have become gods, human beings, and renunciates.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“The moon so immaculate,
journeying across the dimension of space;
outshines with its radiance
all the world’s stars.

So too, a faithful individual,
perfect in ethics,
outshines with their generosity
all the world’s stingy people.

The thundering rain cloud,
its hundred peaks wreathed in lightning,
pours down over the rich earth,
soaking the uplands and valleys.

Even so, an astute person accomplished in vision,
a disciple of the fully awakened Buddha,
surpasses a stingy person
in five respects:

long life and fame,
beauty and happiness.
Lavished with riches,
they depart to rejoice in heaven.”

AN 5.32 With Cundī Cundīsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground. Then Princess Cundī, escorted by five hundred chariots and five hundred royal maidens, went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, my brother, Prince Cunda, says this: ‘Take a woman or man who goes for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. Only then do they get reborn in a good place, not a bad place, when their body breaks up, after death.’ And so I ask the Buddha: Sir, what kind of teacher should you have confidence in so as to be reborn in a good place, not a bad place, when the body breaks up, after death? Sir, what kind of teaching should you have confidence in so as to be reborn in a good place, not a bad place, when the body breaks up, after death? Sir, what kind of Saṅgha should you have confidence in so as to be reborn in a good place, not a bad place, when the body breaks up, after death? Sir, what kind of ethics should you fulfill so as to be reborn in a good place, not a bad place, when the body breaks up, after death?”

“Cundī, the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha, is said to be the best of all sentient beings—be they footless, with two feet, four feet, or many feet; with form or formless; with perception or without perception or with neither perception nor non-perception. Those who have confidence in the Buddha have confidence in the best. Having confidence in the best, the result is the best.

The noble eightfold path is said to be the best of all conditioned things. Those who have confidence in the noble eightfold path have confidence in the best. Having confidence in the best, the result is the best.

Fading away is said to be the best of all things whether conditioned or unconditioned. That is, the quelling of vanity, the removing of thirst, the uprooting of clinging, the breaking of the round, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment. Those who have confidence in the teaching of fading away have confidence in the best. Having confidence in the best, the result is the best.

The Saṅgha of the Realized One’s disciples is said to be the best of all communities and groups. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. Those who have confidence in the Saṅgha have confidence in the best. Having confidence in the best, the result is the best.

The ethical conduct loved by the noble ones is said to be the best of all ethics. It is intact, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. Those who fulfill the ethics loved by the noble ones fulfill the best. Fulfilling the best, the result is the best.

For those who, knowing the best teaching,
base their confidence on the best—
confident in the best Awakened One,
supremely worthy of a religious donation;

confident in the best teaching,
the bliss of fading and stilling;
confident in the best Saṅgha,
the supreme field of merit—

giving gifts to the best,
the best of merit grows:
the best lifespan, beauty,
fame, reputation, happiness, and strength.

An intelligent person gives to the best,
settled on the best teaching.
When they become a god or human,
they rejoice at reaching the best.”

AN 5.33 With Uggaha Uggahasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Bhaddiya in Jātiyā Wood.

Then Uggaha, Meṇḍaka’s grandson, went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, would the Buddha, together with three other monks, please accept tomorrow’s meal from me?” The Buddha consented with silence. Then, knowing that the Buddha had consented, Uggaha rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

Then when the night had passed, the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to Uggaha’s home, where he sat down on the seat spread out. Then Uggaha served and satisfied the Buddha with his own hands with delicious fresh and cooked foods.

When the Buddha had eaten and washed his hand and bowl, Uggaha sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, these girls of mine will be going to their husbands’ families. May the Buddha please advise and instruct them. It will be for their lasting welfare and happiness.”

Then the Buddha said to those girls:

“So, girls, you should train like this: ‘Our parents will give us to a husband wanting what’s best, out of kindness and sympathy. We will get up before him and go to bed after him, and be obliging, behaving nicely and speaking politely.’ That’s how you should train.

So, girls, you should train like this: ‘Those our husband respects—mother and father, ascetics and brahmins—we will honor, respect, revere, and venerate, and serve with a seat and a drink when they come as guests.’ That’s how you should train.

So, girls, you should train like this: ‘We will be deft and tireless in doing domestic duties for our husband, such as knitting and sewing. We will have an understanding of how to go about things in order to complete and organize the work.’ That’s how you should train.

So, girls, you should train like this: ‘We will know what work our husband’s domestic bondservants, servants, and workers have completed, and what they’ve left incomplete. We will know who is sick, and who is fit or unwell. We will distribute to each a fair portion of fresh and cooked foods.’ That’s how you should train.

So, girls, you should train like this: ‘We will ensure that any income our husbands earn is guarded and protected, whether money, grain, silver, or gold. We will not overspend, steal, waste, or lose it.’ That’s how you should train. When they possess these five qualities, ladies—when their body breaks up, after death—are reborn in company with the Gods of the Agreeable Host.

She’d never look down on her husband,
who’s always eager to work hard,
always looking after her,
and bringing whatever she wants.

And a good woman never scolds her husband
with jealous words.
Being astute, she reveres
those respected by her husband.

She gets up early, works tirelessly,
and manages the domestic help.
She’s agreeable to her husband,
and preserves his wealth.

A lady who fulfills these duties
according to her husband’s desire,
is reborn among the gods
called ‘Agreeable’.”

AN 5.34 With General Sīha Sīhasenāpatisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof.

Then General Sīha went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and asked him, “Sir, can you point out a fruit of giving that’s apparent in the present life?”

“I can, Sīha,” said the Buddha.

“A giver, a donor is dear and beloved to many people. This is a fruit of giving that’s apparent in the present life.

Furthermore, good and true persons associate with a giver. This is another fruit of giving that’s apparent in the present life.

Furthermore, a giver gains a good reputation. This is another fruit of giving that’s apparent in the present life.

Furthermore, a giver enters any kind of assembly bold and self-assured, whether it’s an assembly of aristocrats, brahmins, householders, or ascetics. This is another fruit of giving that’s apparent in the present life.

Furthermore, when a giver’s body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. This is a fruit of giving to do with lives to come.”

When he said this, General Sīha said to the Buddha, “When it comes to those four fruits of giving that are apparent in the present life, I don’t rely on faith in the Buddha, for I know them too. I’m a giver, a donor, and am dear and beloved to many people. I’m a giver, and good and true persons associate with me. I’m a giver, and I have this good reputation: ‘General Sīha gives, serves, and attends on the Saṅgha.’ I’m a giver, and I enter any kind of assembly bold and self-assured, whether it’s an assembly of aristocrats, brahmins, householders, or ascetics. When it comes to these four fruits of giving that are apparent in the present life, I don’t rely on faith in the Buddha, for I know them too. But when the Buddha says: ‘When a giver’s body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’ I don’t know this, so I have to rely on faith in the Buddha.”

“That’s so true, Sīha! That’s so true! When a giver’s body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

Giving, you’re loved and befriended by many people.
You get a good reputation, and your fame grows.
A generous man enters an assembly
bold and self-assured.

So an astute person, seeking happiness, would give gifts,
having driven out the stain of stinginess.
They live long in the Third Heaven,
enjoying the company of the gods.

Having taken the opportunity to do good, when they pass from here
they wander self-radiant in the Garden of Delight.
There they delight, rejoice, and enjoy themselves,
provided with the five kinds of sensual stimulation.
Having practiced the word of the unattached, the unaffected,
disciples of the Holy One rejoice in heaven.”

AN 5.35 The Benefits of Giving Dānānisaṁsasutta

“Mendicants, there are five benefits of giving. What five? A giver, a donor is dear and beloved by many people. Good and true persons associate with them. They get a good reputation. They don’t neglect a layperson’s duties. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. These are the five benefits of giving.

Giving, one is loved,
and follows the way of the good.
The good, disciplined spiritual practitioners
always associate with you.

They teach you the Dhamma
that casts aside all suffering.
Having understood this teaching,
the undefiled one is fully extinguished.”

AN 5.36 Timely Gifts Kāladānasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five timely gifts. What five? A gift to a visitor. A gift to someone setting out on a journey. A gift to someone who is sick. A gift at a time of famine. Presenting the freshly harvested grains and fruits first to those who are ethical. These are the five timely gifts.

The wise give at the right time,
being bountiful and rid of stinginess.
A religious donation at the right time
to the noble ones, upright and unaffected,

given with a clear and confident mind,
is indeed abundant.
Those who rejoice at that,
or do other services,
don’t miss out on the offering;
they too have a share in the merit.

So you should give without holding back,
where a gift is very fruitful.
The good deeds of sentient beings
support them in the next world.”

AN 5.37 Food Bhojanasutta

“Mendicants, when a giver gives food, they give the recipients five things. What five? Long life, beauty, happiness, strength, and eloquence.

Giving long life, they have long life as a god or human.

Giving beauty, they have beauty as a god or human.

Giving happiness, they have happiness as a god or human.

Giving strength, they have strength as a god or human.

Giving eloquence, they are eloquent as a god or human.

When a giver gives food, they give the recipients five things.

Being attentive, one is a giver of life, strength,
beauty, and eloquence.
An intelligent giver of happiness
gains happiness in return.

Giving life, strength, beauty,
happiness, and eloquence,
they’re long-lived and famous
wherever they’re reborn.”

AN 5.38 Faith Saddhasutta

“Mendicants, a faithful gentleman gets five benefits. What five? The true persons in the world show sympathy first to the faithful, not so much to the unfaithful. They first approach the faithful, not so much the unfaithful. They first receive alms from the faithful, not so much the unfaithful. They first teach Dhamma to the faithful, not so much the unfaithful. When their body breaks up, after death, the faithful are reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. A faithful gentleman gets these five benefits.

Suppose there was a great banyan tree at a level crossroads. It would become a refuge for birds from all around. In the same way, a faithful gentleman becomes a refuge for many people—monks, nuns, laywomen, and laymen.

With its branches, leaves, and fruit,
a great tree with its strong trunk,
firmly-rooted and fruit-bearing,
supports many birds.

It’s a lovely place,
frequented by the sky-soarers.
Those that need shade go in the shade,
those that need fruit enjoy the fruit.

So too, a faithful individual
is perfect in ethics,
placid in manner and amenable,
gentle, courteous, and tender.

Those free of greed, freed of hate,
free of delusion, undefiled,
fields of merit for the world,
associate with such a person.

They teach them the Dhamma,
that casts aside all suffering.
Having understood this teaching,
the undefiled one is fully extinguished.”

AN 5.39 A Child Puttasutta

“Mendicants, parents see five reasons to wish for the birth of a child in the family. What five? Since we looked after them, they’ll look after us. They’ll do their duty for us. The family customs will last. They’ll take care of the inheritance. Or else when we have passed away they’ll give an offering on our behalf. Parents see these five reasons to wish for the birth of a child in the family.

Seeing five reasons,
astute people wish for a child.
Since we looked after them, they’ll look after us.
They’ll do their duty for us.

The family customs will last.
They’ll take care of the inheritance.
Or else when we have passed away
they’ll give an offering on our behalf.

Seeing these five reasons
astute people wish for a child.
And so true persons,
grateful and thankful,

look after their parents,
remembering past deeds.
They do for their parents,
as their parents did for them in the past.

Following their advice, looking after those who raised them,
the family customs are not lost.
Faithful, accomplished in ethics,
such a child is praiseworthy.”

AN 5.40 Great Sal Trees Mahāsālaputtasutta

“Mendicants, great sal trees grow in five ways supported by the Himalayas, the king of mountains. What five? The branches, leaves, and foliage; the bark; the shoots; the softwood; and the hardwood. Great sal trees grow in these five ways supported by the Himalayas, the king of mountains.

In the same way, a family grows in five ways supported by a family head with faith. What five? Faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. A family grows in these five ways supported by a family head with faith.

Supported by the rocky mountain
in the wilds, the formidable forest,
the tree grows
to become lord of the forest.

So too, when the family head
is ethical and faithful,
supported by them, they grow:
children, partners, and kin,
colleagues, relatives,
and those dependent for their livelihood.

Seeing the ethical conduct of the virtuous,
the generosity and good deeds,
those who see clearly
do likewise.

Having practiced the teaching here,
the path that goes to a good place,
they delight in the heavenly realm,
enjoying all the pleasures they desire.”

The Third Fifty

The Chapter on Living Comfortably

AN 5.101 Assurance Sārajjasutta

“Mendicants, these five qualities make a trainee self-assured. What five? It’s when a mendicant is faithful, ethical, learned, energetic, and wise.

A person of faith doesn’t have the insecurities of someone who lacks faith. So this quality makes a trainee self-assured.

An ethical person doesn’t have the insecurities of someone who is unethical. So this quality makes a trainee self-assured.

A learned person doesn’t have the insecurities of a person of little learning. So this quality makes a trainee self-assured.

An energetic person doesn’t have the insecurities of a lazy person. So this quality makes a trainee self-assured.

A wise person doesn’t have the insecurities of someone who is witless. So this quality makes a trainee self-assured.

These are the five qualities that make a trainee self-assured.”

AN 5.102 Suspected Ussaṅkitasutta

“Mendicants, even if a monk is of impeccable character, he might be suspected and distrusted as a ‘bad monk’ for five reasons.

What five? It’s when a monk resorts to prostitutes, widows, voluptuous girls, eunuchs, or nuns for alms.

Even if a monk is of impeccable character, he might be suspected and distrusted as a ‘bad monk’ for these five reasons.”

AN 5.103 A Master Thief Mahācorasutta

“Mendicants, a master thief with five factors breaks into houses, plunders wealth, steals from isolated buildings, and commits highway robbery. What five? A master thief relies on rough ground, on thick cover, and on the powerful; they pay bribes, and they act alone.

And how does a master thief rely on rough ground? It’s when a master thief relies on inaccessible riverlands or rugged mountains. That’s how a master thief relies on rough ground.

And how does a master thief rely on thick cover? It’s when a master thief relies on thick grass, thick trees, a blind spot, or a large forest grove. That’s how a master thief relies on thick cover.

And how does a master thief rely on the powerful? It’s when a master thief relies on rulers or their chief ministers. They think: ‘If anyone accuses me of anything, these rulers or their chief ministers will speak in my defense in the case.’ And that’s exactly what happens. That’s how a master thief relies on the powerful.

And how does a master thief pay bribes? It’s when a master thief is rich, affluent, and wealthy. They think: ‘If anyone accuses me of anything, I’ll settle it with a bribe.’ And that’s exactly what happens. That’s how a master thief pays bribes.

And how does a master thief act alone? It’s when a master thief carries out robbery all alone. Why is that? So that their secret plans are not leaked to others. That’s how a master thief acts alone.

A master thief with these five factors breaks into houses, plunders wealth, steals from isolated buildings, and commits highway robbery.

In the same way, when a bad mendicant has five qualities, they keep themselves broken and damaged. They deserve to be blamed and criticized by sensible people, and they brim with much wickedness. What five? A bad mendicant relies on rough ground, on thick cover, and on the powerful; they pay bribes, and they act alone.

And how does a bad mendicant rely on rough ground? It’s when a bad mendicant has unethical conduct by way of body, speech, and mind. That’s how a bad mendicant relies on rough ground.

And how does a bad mendicant rely on thick cover? It’s when a bad mendicant has wrong view, he’s attached to an extremist view. That’s how a bad mendicant relies on thick cover.

And how does a bad mendicant rely on the powerful? It’s when a bad mendicant relies on rulers or their chief ministers. They think: ‘If anyone accuses me of anything, these rulers or their chief ministers will speak in my defense in the case.’ And that’s exactly what happens. That’s how a bad mendicant relies on the powerful.

And how does a bad mendicant pay bribes? It’s when a bad mendicant receives robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. They think: ‘If anyone accuses me of anything, I’ll settle it with a bribe.’ And that’s exactly what happens. That’s how a bad mendicant pays bribes.

And how does a bad mendicant act alone? It’s when a bad mendicant dwells alone in the borderlands. They visit families there to acquire material things. That’s how a bad mendicant acts alone.

When a bad mendicant possesses these five qualities, they keep themselves broken and damaged. They deserve to be blamed and criticized by sensible people, and they brim with much wickedness.”

AN 5.104 A Delicate Ascetic of Ascetics Samaṇasukhumālasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with five qualities is a delicate ascetic of ascetics.

What five?

It’s when a mendicant usually uses only what they’ve been invited to accept—robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick—rarely using them without invitation.

When living with other spiritual practitioners, they usually find themselves treated agreeably by them by way of body, speech, and mind, and rarely disagreeably. And they are usually presented with agreeable things by them, rarely with disagreeable ones.

They’re healthy, so the various unpleasant feelings—stemming from disorders of bile, phlegm, wind, or their conjunction; or caused by change in weather, by not taking care of themselves, by exertion, or as the result of past deeds—usually don’t come up.

They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty.

And they realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

A mendicant with these five qualities is a delicate ascetic of ascetics.

And if anyone should be rightly called a delicate ascetic of ascetics, it’s me. For I usually use only what I’ve been invited to accept. When living with other mendicants, I am usually treated agreeably by them. And I usually present them with agreeable things. I’m healthy. I get the four absorptions when I want, without trouble or difficulty. And I’ve realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom … in this very life … So if anyone should be rightly called a delicate ascetic of ascetics, it’s me.”

AN 5.105 Living Comfortably Phāsuvihārasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five ways of living comfortably. What five?

It’s when a mendicant consistently treats their spiritual companions with kindness by way of body, speech, and mind, both in public and in private.

They live according to the precepts shared with their spiritual companions, both in public and in private. Those precepts are intact, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion.

They live according to the view shared with their spiritual companions, both in public and in private. That view is noble and emancipating, and delivers one who applies it to the complete ending of suffering.

These are the five ways of living comfortably.”

AN 5.106 With Ānanda Ānandasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery.

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, how could a mendicant live comfortably while staying in a monastic community?”

“It’s when a mendicant is accomplished in their own ethical conduct, but they don’t urge others to be ethical. That’s how a mendicant could live comfortably while staying in a monastic community.”

“But sir, could there be another way for a mendicant to live comfortably while staying in a monastic community?”

“There could, Ānanda. It’s when a mendicant is accomplished in their own ethical conduct, but they don’t urge others to be ethical. And they watch themselves, but don’t watch others. That’s how a mendicant could live comfortably while staying in a monastic community.”

“But sir, could there be another way for a mendicant to live comfortably while staying in a monastic community?”

“There could, Ānanda. It’s when a mendicant is accomplished in their own ethical conduct, but they don’t urge others to be ethical. And they watch themselves, but don’t watch others. And they’re not well-known, but aren’t bothered by that. That’s how a mendicant could live comfortably while staying in a monastic community.”

“But sir, could there be another way for a mendicant to live comfortably while staying in a monastic community?”

“There could, Ānanda. It’s when a mendicant is accomplished in their own ethical conduct, but they don’t urge others to be ethical. And they watch themselves, but don’t watch others. And they’re not well-known, but aren’t bothered by that. And they get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty. That’s how a mendicant could live comfortably while staying in a monastic community.”

“But sir, might there be another way for a mendicant to live comfortably while staying in a monastic community?”

“There could, Ānanda. It’s when a mendicant is accomplished in their own ethical conduct, but they don’t urge others to be ethical. And they watch themselves, but don’t watch others. And they’re not well-known, but aren’t bothered by that. And they get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty. And they realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. That’s how a mendicant could live comfortably while staying in a monastic community.

And I say that there is no better or finer way of living comfortably than this.”

AN 5.107 Ethics Sīlasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with five qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.

What five? It’s when a mendicant is accomplished in ethics, immersion, wisdom, freedom, and the knowledge and vision of freedom.

A mendicant with these five qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 5.108 An adept Asekhasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with five qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.

What five? It’s when they have the entire spectrum of the adept’s ethics, immersion, wisdom, freedom, and knowledge and vision of freedom. A mendicant with these five qualities … is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 5.109 All Four Quarters Cātuddisasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with five qualities is at ease in any quarter. What five?

It’s when mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken.

They’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically.

They’re content with any kind of robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick.

They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty.

They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

A mendicant with these five qualities is at ease in any quarter.”

AN 5.110 Wilderness Araññasutta

“Mendicants, when a mendicant has five qualities they’re ready to frequent remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. What five?

It’s when a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken.

They’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s totally full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, reciting them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically.

They live with energy roused up. They’re strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities.

They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty.

They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

When a mendicant possesses these five qualities they’re ready to frequent remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest.”

The Chapter on Senior Mendicants

AN 5.81 Desirable Rajanīyasutta

“Mendicants, a senior mendicant with five qualities is disliked and disagreeable to their spiritual companions, not respected or admired. What five? They desire the desirable, they hate the hateful, they’re deluded by the delusory, they’re annoyed by the annoying, and they’re intoxicated by the intoxicating. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is disliked and disagreeable by their spiritual companions, not respected or admired.

A senior mendicant with five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired. What five? They don’t desire the desirable, they don’t hate the hateful, they’re not deluded by the delusory, they’re not annoyed by the annoying, and they’re not intoxicated by the intoxicating. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired.”

AN 5.82 Free of Greed Vītarāgasutta

“Mendicants, a senior mendicant with five qualities is disliked and disagreeable to their spiritual companions, not respected or admired. What five? They’re not free of greed, hate, and delusion; they are offensive and contemptuous. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is disliked and disagreeable to their spiritual companions, not respected or admired.

A senior mendicant with five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired. What five? They’re free of greed, hate, and delusion; they’re not offensive and contemptuous. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired.”

AN 5.83 Deceiver Kuhakasutta

“Mendicants, a senior mendicant with five qualities is disliked and disagreeable to their spiritual companions, not respected or admired. What five? They use deceit, flattery, hinting, and belittling, and they use material things to chase after other material things. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is disliked and disagreeable to their spiritual companions, not respected or admired.

A senior mendicant with five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired. What five? They don’t use deceit, flattery, hinting, or belittling, and they don’t use material things to chase after other material things. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired.”

AN 5.84 Faithless Assaddhasutta

“Mendicants, a senior mendicant with five qualities is disliked and disagreeable to their spiritual companions, not respected or admired. What five? They’re faithless, shameless, imprudent, lazy, and witless. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is disliked and disagreeable to their spiritual companions, not respected or admired.

A senior mendicant with five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired. What five? They’re faithful, conscientious, prudent, energetic, and wise. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired.”

AN 5.85 Cannot Endure Akkhamasutta

“Mendicants, a senior mendicant with five qualities is disliked and disagreeable to their spiritual companions, not respected or admired. What five? They can’t endure sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is disliked and disagreeable to their spiritual companions, not respected or admired.

A senior mendicant with five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired. What five? They can endure sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired.”

AN 5.86 Attaining the Methods of Textual Analysis Paṭisambhidāpattasutta

“A senior mendicant with five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired. What five? They have attained the textual analysis of meaning, text, definition, and eloquence. And they are deft and tireless in a diverse spectrum of duties for their spiritual companions, understanding how to go about things in order to complete and organize the work. A senior mendicant with these five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired.”

AN 5.87 Ethical Sīlavantasutta

“A senior mendicant with five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired. What five?

They’re ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken.

They’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically.

They’re a good speaker who enunciates well, with a polished, clear, and articulate voice that expresses the meaning.

They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty.

They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

A senior mendicant with these five qualities is dear and beloved to their spiritual companions, respected and admired.”

AN 5.88 Senior Mendicants Therasutta

“Mendicants, a senior mendicant who has five qualities is acting for the detriment and unhappiness of the people, against the people, for the harm, detriment, and suffering of of gods and humans.

What five?

They are long standing and have long gone forth.

They’re well-known, famous, with a large following that includes both laypeople and renunciates.

They receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick.

They’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically.

But they have wrong view and distorted perspective. They draw many people away from the true teaching and establish them in false teachings.

People follow their example, thinking that the senior mendicant is long standing and has long gone forth. Or that they’re well-known, famous, with a large following that includes both laypeople and renunciates. Or that they receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. Or that they’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. A senior mendicant who possesses these five qualities is acting for the detriment and unhappiness of the people, against the people, for the harm, detriment, and suffering of gods and humans.

A senior mendicant who has five qualities is acting for the welfare and happiness of the people, for the people, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.

What five?

They are long standing and have long gone forth.

They’re well-known, famous, with a large following, including both laypeople and renunciates.

They receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick.

They’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically.

And they have right view and an undistorted perspective. They draw many people away from false teachings and establish them in the true teaching.

People follow their example, thinking that the senior mendicant is long standing and has long gone forth. Or that they’re well-known, famous, with a large following that includes both laypeople and renunciates. Or that they receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. Or that they’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. A senior mendicant who possesses these five qualities is acting for the welfare and happiness of the people, for the people, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.”

AN 5.89 A Trainee (1st) Paṭhamasekhasutta

“These five things lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee. What five? They relish work, talk, sleep, and company. And they don’t review the extent of their mind’s freedom. These five things lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

These five things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee. What five? They don’t relish work, talk, sleep, and company. And they review the extent of their mind’s freedom. These five things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.”

AN 5.90 A Trainee (2nd) Dutiyasekhasutta

“These five things lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee. What five?

Firstly, a mendicant trainee has many duties and responsibilities, and is competent in many tasks. They neglect retreat, and are not committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the first thing that leads to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant trainee spends too much time doing trivial work. They neglect retreat, and are not committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the second thing that leads to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant trainee mixes closely with laypeople and renunciates, socializing inappropriately like a layperson. They neglect retreat, and are not committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the third thing that leads to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant trainee enters the town at the wrong time, and returns too late in the day. They neglect retreat, and are not committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the fourth thing that leads to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant trainee doesn’t get to take part in talk about self-effacement that helps open the heart, when they want, without trouble or difficulty. That is, talk about fewness of wishes, contentment, seclusion, aloofness, arousing energy, ethics, immersion, wisdom, freedom, and the knowledge and vision of freedom. They neglect retreat, and are not committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the fifth thing that leads to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

These five things lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

These five things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee. What five?

Firstly, a mendicant trainee doesn’t have many duties and responsibilities, even though they are competent in many tasks. They don’t neglect retreat, and are committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the first thing that doesn’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant trainee doesn’t waste their day doing trivial work. They don’t neglect retreat, and are committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the second thing that doesn’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant trainee doesn’t mix closely with laypeople and renunciates, socializing inappropriately like a layperson. They don’t neglect retreat, and are committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the third thing that doesn’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant trainee doesn’t enter the village too early or return too late in the day. They don’t neglect retreat, and are committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the fourth thing that doesn’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

Furthermore, a mendicant trainee gets to take part in talk about self-effacement that helps open the heart, when they want, without trouble or difficulty. That is, talk about fewness of wishes, contentment, seclusion, aloofness, arousing energy, ethics, immersion, wisdom, freedom, and the knowledge and vision of freedom. They don’t neglect retreat, and are committed to internal serenity of heart. This is the fifth thing that doesn’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

These five things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.”

The Chapter at Tikaṇḍakī

AN 5.141 Scorn Avajānātisutta

“Mendicants, these five individuals are found in the world. What five? One gives then scorns, one lives together then scorns, one is gullible for gossip, one is impulsive, and one is dull and stupid.

And how does an individual give then scorn? It’s when an individual gives an individual robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. They think: ‘I give; this one receives.’ They give to them, then they scorn them. That’s how an individual gives then scorns.

And how does an individual live together then scorn? It’s when an individual lives with someone else for two or three years. They live together with them, then they scorn them. That’s how an individual lives together then scorns.

And how is an individual gullible for gossip? It’s when they’re very quick to believe what a certain individual says in praise or criticism of another. That’s how an individual is gullible for gossip.

And how is an individual impulsive? It’s when a certain individual is fickle in faith, devotion, fondness, and confidence. That’s how an individual is impulsive.

And how is an individual dull and stupid? It’s when they don’t know the difference between qualities that are skillful and unskillful, blameworthy and blameless, inferior and superior, and those with a portion of dark or bright. That’s how an individual is dull and stupid.

These are the five individuals found in the world.”

AN 5.142 Transgression Ārabhatisutta

“Mendicants, these five individuals are found in the world. What five?

One individual transgresses and regrets it. And they don’t truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where those arisen bad, unskillful qualities cease without remainder.

One individual transgresses and doesn’t regret it. And they don’t understand …

One individual doesn’t transgress yet still feels regret. And they don’t understand …

One individual neither transgresses nor regrets. But they don’t understand …

One individual neither transgresses nor regrets. And they do understand where those arisen bad, unskillful qualities cease without remainder.

Take the case of the individual who transgresses and regrets it. And they don’t truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where those arisen bad, unskillful qualities cease without remainder. They should be told: ‘Venerable, the defilements born of transgression are found in you, and the defilements born of regret grow. You would do well to give up the defilements born of transgression and dispel the defilements born of regret, and then develop the mind and wisdom. In this way you’ll become just like the fifth individual.’

Take the case of the individual who transgresses and doesn’t regret it. And they don’t understand … They should be told: ‘Venerable, the defilements born of transgression are found in you, but the defilements born of regret don’t grow. You would do well to give up the defilements born of transgression, and then develop the mind and wisdom. In this way you’ll become just like the fifth individual.’

Take the case of the individual who doesn’t transgress yet feels regret. And they don’t understand … They should be told: ‘Venerable, the defilements born of transgression are not found in you, yet the defilements born of regret grow. You would do well to dispel the defilements born of regret, and then develop the mind and wisdom. In this way you’ll become just like the fifth individual.’

Take the case of the individual who neither transgresses nor regrets. But they don’t understand … They should be told: ‘Venerable, the defilements born of transgression are not found in you, and the defilements born of regret don’t grow. You would do well to develop the mind and wisdom. In this way you’ll become just like the fifth individual.’

And so, mendicants, when these four individuals are advised and instructed by comparison with the fifth individual, they gradually attain the ending of defilements.”

AN 5.143 At Sārandada Sārandadasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof.

Then the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Vesālī for alms.

Now at that time around five hundred Licchavis were sitting together at the Sārandada Shrine, and this discussion came up among them, “The appearance of five treasures is rare in the world. What five? The elephant-treasure, the horse-treasure, the jewel-treasure, the woman-treasure, and the householder-treasure. The appearance of these five treasures is rare in the world.”

Then those Licchavis sent a man out on to the road, saying, “My man, please tell us when you see the Buddha.”

That man saw the Buddha coming off in the distance. He went to the Licchavis and said, “Sirs, the Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha is coming. Please go at your convenience.”

Then those Licchavis went up to the Buddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him, “Please go to the Sārandada Shrine, out of sympathy.” The Buddha consented with silence.

Then the Buddha went up to the Sārandada Shrine. He sat down on the seat spread out and said to the Licchavis, “Licchavis, what were you sitting talking about just now? What conversation was left unfinished?”

“Well, sir, this discussion came up among us while we were sitting together: ‘The appearance of five treasures is rare in the world. …’”

“You Licchavis are so fixated on sensual pleasures, that’s the only discussion that came up! Licchavis, the appearance of five treasures is rare in the world. What five?

The appearance of a Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha.

A teacher of the teaching and training proclaimed by a Realized One.

An individual who understands the teaching and training proclaimed by a Realized One.

An individual who practices in line with the teaching.

An individual who is grateful and thankful.

The appearance of these five treasures is rare in the world.”

AN 5.144 At Tikaṇḍakī Tikaṇḍakīsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāketa in Tikaṇḍakī Wood. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, a mendicant would do well to meditate from time to time perceiving the following: the repulsive in the unrepulsive,
the unrepulsive in the repulsive,
the repulsive in both the unrepulsive and the repulsive, and
the unrepulsive in both the repulsive and the unrepulsive.
A mendicant would do well to meditate from time to time staying equanimous, mindful and aware, shunning both the repulsive and the unrepulsive.

For what reason should a mendicant meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive? ‘May greed not arise in me for things that arouse greed.’ A mendicant should meditate perceiving the repulsive in the unrepulsive for this reason.

For what reason should a mendicant meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in the repulsive? ‘May hate not arise in me for things that provoke hate.’ …

For what reason should a mendicant meditate perceiving the repulsive in both the unrepulsive and the repulsive? ‘May greed not arise in me for things that arouse greed. May hate not arise in me for things that provoke hate.’ …

For what reason should a mendicant meditate perceiving the unrepulsive in both the repulsive and the unrepulsive? ‘May hate not arise in me for things that provoke hate. May greed not arise in me for things that arouse greed.’ …

For what reason should a mendicant meditate staying equanimous, mindful and aware, shunning both the repulsive and the unrepulsive? ‘May no greed for things that arouse greed, hate for things that provoke hate, or delusion for things that promote delusion arise in me in any way at all.’ For this reason a mendicant should meditate staying equanimous, mindful and aware, shunning both the repulsive and the unrepulsive.”

AN 5.145 Hell Nirayasutta

“Mendicants, someone with five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What five? They kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, and consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. Someone with these five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

Someone with five qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What five? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. Someone with these five qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 5.146 A Friend Mittasutta

“Mendicants, you shouldn’t associate with a mendicant friend who has five qualities. What five? They start up work projects. They take up disciplinary issues. They conflict with leading mendicants. They like long and aimless wandering. They’re unable to educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire you from time to time with a Dhamma talk. Mendicants, you shouldn’t associate with a mendicant friend who possesses these five qualities.

You should associate with a mendicant friend who has five qualities. What five? They don’t start up work projects. They don’t take up disciplinary issues. They don’t conflict with leading mendicants. They don’t like long and aimless wandering. They’re able to educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire you from time to time with a Dhamma talk. You should associate with a mendicant friend who possesses these five qualities.”

AN 5.147 Gifts of an Untrue Person Asappurisadānasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five gifts of an untrue person. What five? They give carelessly. They give thoughtlessly. They don’t give with their own hand. They give the dregs. They give without consideration for consequences. These are the five gifts of an untrue person.

There are these five gifts of a true person. What five? They give carefully. They give thoughtfully. They give with their own hand. They don’t give the dregs. They give with consideration for consequences. These are the five gifts of a true person.”

AN 5.148 Gifts of a True Person Sappurisadānasutta

“There are these five gifts of a true person. What five? They give a gift out of faith. They give a gift carefully. They give a gift at the right time. They give a gift with no strings attached. They give a gift without damaging themselves or others.

Having given a gift out of faith, in whatever place the result of that gift manifests they become rich, affluent, and wealthy. And they’re attractive, good-looking, lovely, of surpassing beauty.

Having given a gift carefully, in whatever place the result of that gift manifests they become rich, affluent, and wealthy. And their children, wives, bondservants, servants, and workers want to listen. They actively listen and try to understand.

Having given a gift at the right time, in whatever place the result of that gift manifests they become rich, affluent, and wealthy. And when the time is right, their needs are amply satisfied.

Having given a gift with no strings attached, in whatever place the result of that gift manifests they become rich, affluent, and wealthy. And their mind tends to enjoy the five refined kinds of sensual stimulation.

Having given a gift without damaging themselves or others, in whatever place the result of that gift manifests they become rich, affluent, and wealthy. And no damage comes to their property from anywhere, whether fire, flood, rulers, bandits, or unloved heirs.

These are the five gifts of a true person.”

AN 5.149 Temporarily Free (1st) Paṭhamasamayavimuttasutta

“Mendicants, these five things lead to the decline of a mendicant who is temporarily free. What five? They relish work, talk, sleep, and company. And they don’t review the extent of their mind’s freedom. These five things lead to the decline of a mendicant who is temporarily free.

These five things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant who is temporarily free. What five? They don’t relish work, talk, sleep, and company. And they review the extent of their mind’s freedom. These five things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant who is temporarily free.”

AN 5.150 Temporarily Free (2nd) Dutiyasamayavimuttasutta

“Mendicants, these five things lead to the decline of a mendicant who is temporarily free. What five? They relish work, talk, and sleep. They don’t guard the sense doors and they eat too much. These five things lead to the decline of a mendicant who is temporarily free.

These five things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant who is temporarily free. What five? They don’t relish work, talk, and sleep. They guard the sense doors and they have moderation in eating. These five things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant who is temporarily free.”

The Chapter on a Lay Follower

AN 5.171 Timidity Sārajjasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“A lay follower with five qualities is overcome by timidity. What five? They kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, and consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. A lay follower with these five qualities is overcome by timidity.

A lay follower with five qualities is self-assured. What five? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. A lay follower with these five qualities is self-assured.”

AN 5.172 Assured Visāradasutta

“A lay follower living at home with five qualities is not self-assured. What five? They kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, and consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. A lay follower living at home with these five qualities is not self-assured.

A lay follower living at home with these five qualities is self-assured. What five? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. A lay follower living at home with these five qualities is self-assured.”

AN 5.173 Hell Nirayasutta

“Mendicants, a lay follower with five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there. What five? They kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, and consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. A lay follower with these five qualities is placed in hell as if delivered there.

A lay follower with five qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there. What five? They don’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. A lay follower with these five qualities is placed in heaven as if delivered there.”

AN 5.174 Threats Verasutta

Then the householder Anāthapiṇḍika went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Householder, unless these five fears and enmities are given up, one is said to be unethical, and is reborn in hell. What five? Killing living creatures, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, and intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. Unless these five fears and enmities are given up, one is said to be unethical, and is reborn in hell.

Once these five fears and enmities are given up, one is said to be ethical, and is reborn in a good place. What five? Killing living creatures, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, and intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. Once these five fears and enmities are given up, one is said to be ethical, and is reborn in a good place.

Anyone who kills living creatures brims with fear and enmity both in this life and in lives to come, and experiences mental pain and sadness. Anyone who refrains from killing living creatures does not brim with fear and enmity either in this life or in lives to come, and doesn’t experience mental pain and sadness. So that fear and enmity is quelled for anyone who refrains from killing living creatures.

Anyone who steals …

Anyone who commits sexual misconduct …

Anyone who lies …

Anyone who consumes beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants brims with fear and enmity both in this life and in lives to come, and experiences mental pain and sadness. Anyone who refrains from beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants does not brim with fear and enmity either in this life or in lives to come, and doesn’t experience mental pain and sadness. So that fear and enmity is quelled for anyone who refrains from beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants.

Someone in this world
who kills living creatures,
speaks falsely, steals,
commits adultery,
and indulges in drinking
beer and wine—

unless they give up these five threats,
they’re said to be unethical.
When their body breaks up, that witless person
is reborn in hell.

But someone in this world
who doesn’t kill living creatures,
speak falsely, steal,
commit adultery,
or indulge in drinking
beer and wine—

having given up these five threats,
they’re said to be ethical.
When their body breaks up, that wise person
is reborn in a good place.”

AN 5.175 Corpse-worker Caṇḍālasutta

“Mendicants, a lay follower with five qualities is a corpse-worker, a stain, and a reject among lay followers. What five? They’re faithless. They’re unethical. They follow boisterous, superstitious rites, believing in omens rather than deeds. They seek outside of the Buddhist community for those worthy of religious donations. And they make offerings there first. A lay follower with these five qualities is a corpse-worker, a stain, and a reject among lay followers.

A lay follower with five qualities is a gem, a pink lotus, and a white lotus among lay followers. What five? They’re faithful. They’re ethical. They don’t practice boisterous, superstitious rites, and believe in deeds rather than omens. They don’t seek outside of the Buddhist community for those worthy of religious donations. And they don’t make offerings there first. A lay follower with these five qualities is a gem, a pink lotus, and a white lotus among lay followers.”

AN 5.176 Rapture Pītisutta

Then the householder Anāthapiṇḍika, escorted by around five hundred lay followers, went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Householders, you have supplied the mendicant Saṅgha with robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. But you should not be content with just this much. So you should train like this: ‘How can we, from time to time, enter and dwell in the rapture of seclusion?’ That’s how you should train.”

When he said this, Venerable Sāriputta said to the Buddha, “It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! How well said this was by the Buddha: ‘Householders, you have supplied the mendicant Saṅgha with robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. But you should not be content with just this much. So you should train like this: “How can we, from time to time, enter and dwell in the rapture of seclusion?” That’s how you should train.’

At a time when a noble disciple enters and dwells in the rapture of seclusion, five things aren’t present in him. The pain and sadness connected with sensual pleasures. The pleasure and happiness connected with sensual pleasures. The pain and sadness connected with the unskillful. The pleasure and happiness connected with the unskillful. The pain and sadness connected with the skillful. At a time when a noble disciple enters and dwells in the rapture of seclusion, these five things aren’t present in him.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! At a time when a noble disciple enters and dwells in the rapture of seclusion, five things aren’t present in him. The pain and sadness connected with sensual pleasures. The pleasure and happiness connected with sensual pleasures. The pain and sadness connected with the unskillful. The pleasure and happiness connected with the unskillful. The pain and sadness connected with the skillful. At a time when a noble disciple enters and dwells in the rapture of seclusion, these five things aren’t present in him.”

AN 5.177 Trades Vaṇijjāsutta

“Mendicants, a lay follower should not engage in these five trades. What five? Trade in weapons, living creatures, meat, intoxicants, and poisons. A lay follower should not engage in these five trades.”

AN 5.178 Kings Rājāsutta

“What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of a person who has given up killing living creatures, and the kings have them arrested for that, and execute, imprison, or banish them, or do what the case requires?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing. Rather, the kings are informed of someone’s bad deed: ‘This person has murdered a man or a woman.’ The kings have them arrested for killing, and execute, imprison, or banish them, or do what the case requires. Have you ever seen or heard of such a case?”

“Sir, we have seen it and heard of it, and we will hear of it again.”

“What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of a person who has given up stealing, and the kings have them arrested for that …?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing. Rather, the kings are informed of someone’s bad deed: ‘This person took something from a village or wilderness, with the intention to commit theft.’ The kings have them arrested for stealing … Have you ever seen or heard of such a case?”

“Sir, we have seen it and heard of it, and we will hear of it again.”

“What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of a person who has given up sexual misconduct, and the kings have them arrested for that …?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing. Rather, the kings are informed of someone’s bad deed: ‘This person had relations with women or maidens under someone else’s protection.’ The kings have them arrested for that … Have you ever seen or heard of such a case?”

“Sir, we have seen it and heard of it, and we will hear of it again.”

“What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of a person who has given up lying, and the kings have them arrested for that …?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing. Rather, the kings are informed of someone’s bad deed: ‘This person has ruined a householder or householder’s child by lying.’ The kings have them arrested for that … Have you ever seen or heard of such a case?”

“Sir, we have seen it and heard of it, and we will hear of it again.”

“What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of a person who has given up intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor, and the kings have them arrested for that, and execute, imprison, or banish them, or do what the case requires?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing. Rather, the kings are informed of someone’s bad deed: ‘While under the influence of intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor, this person murdered a woman or a man. Or they stole something from a village or wilderness. Or they had relations with women or maidens under someone else’s protection. Or they ruined a householder or householder’s child by lying.’ The kings have them arrested for being under the influence of intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor, and execute, imprison, or banish them, or do what the case requires. Have you ever seen or heard of such a case?”

“Sir, we have seen it and heard of it, and we will hear of it again.”

AN 5.179 A Layperson Gihisutta

Then the householder Anāthapiṇḍika, escorted by around five hundred lay followers, went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. Then the Buddha said to Venerable Sāriputta:

“You should know this, Sāriputta, about those white-clothed laypeople whose actions are restrained in the five precepts, and who get four blissful meditations in this life belonging to the higher mind when they want, without trouble or difficulty. They may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’

And what are the five precepts in which their actions are restrained? It’s when a noble disciple doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. These are the five precepts in which their actions are restrained.

And what are the four blissful meditations in this life belonging to the higher mind that they get when they want, without trouble or difficulty?

It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ This is the first blissful meditation in this life belonging to the higher mind, which they achieve in order to purify the unpurified mind and cleanse the unclean mind.

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’ This is the second blissful meditation …

Furthermore, a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.’ This is the third blissful meditation …

Furthermore, a noble disciple’s ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. This is the fourth blissful meditation in this life belonging to the higher mind, which they achieve in order to purify the unpurified mind and cleanse the unclean mind. These are the four blissful meditations in this life belonging to the higher mind that they get when they want, without trouble or difficulty.

You should know this, Sāriputta, about those white-clothed laypeople whose actions are restrained in the five precepts, and who get four blissful meditations in this life belonging to the higher mind when they want, without trouble or difficulty. They may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’

Seeing the peril in the hells,
you should shun bad deeds.
Taking up the teaching of the noble ones,
an astute person should shun them.

You shouldn’t harm living beings,
so long as strength is found.
Nor should you knowingly speak falsehood,
or take what is not given.

Content with your own partners,
you should stay away from the partners of others.
A personage shouldn’t drink wine or toddy,
as they confuse the mind.

You should recollect the Buddha,
and reflect on the teaching.
You should develop a harmless mind of welfare,
which leads to the realms of gods.

When suitable gifts to give are available
to someone who seeks and needs merit,
a religious donation is abundant
if given first to the peaceful ones.

I will tell of the peaceful ones,
Sāriputta, listen to me.
Cows may be black or white,
red or tawny,

mottled or uniform,
or pigeon-colored.
But when one is born among them,
the bull that’s tamed—

a behemoth, powerful,
well-paced in pulling forward—
they yoke the load just to him,
regardless of his color.

So it is for humans,
wherever they may be born—
among aristocrats, brahmins, peasants,
menials, or corpse-workers and scavengers—

but when one is born among them,
tamed, true to their vows.
Firm in principle, accomplished in ethical conduct,
truthful, conscientious,

they’ve given up birth and death,
and have completed the spiritual journey.
With burden put down, detached,
they’ve completed the task and are free of defilements.

Gone beyond all things,
they’re quenched by not grasping.
In that flawless field,
a religious donation is abundant.

Fools who don’t understand—
unlearned simpletons—
give their gifts to those outside,
and don’t attend the peaceful ones.

But those who do attend the peaceful ones—
wise, esteemed as attentive—
and whose faith in the Holy One
has roots planted deep,

they go to the realm of the gods,
or are born here in a good family.
Gradually those astute ones
reach extinguishment.”

AN 5.180 About Gavesī Gavesīsutta

At one time the Buddha was wandering in the land of the Kosalans together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants. While traveling along a road the Buddha saw a large sal grove in a certain spot. He left the road, went to the sal grove, and plunged deep into it. And at a certain spot he smiled.

Then Venerable Ānanda thought, “What is the cause, what is the reason why the Buddha smiled? Realized Ones do not smile for no reason.”

So Venerable Ānanda said to the Buddha, “What is the cause, what is the reason why the Buddha smiled? Realized Ones do not smile for no reason.”

“Once upon a time, Ānanda, there was a city in this spot that was successful and prosperous, populous and full of people. And Kassapa, a blessed one, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha, lived supported by that city.

He had a lay follower named Gavesī who had not fulfilled all the precepts. And the five hundred lay followers who were taught and advised by Gavesī also had not fulfilled all the precepts. Then Gavesī thought: ‘I’m the helper, leader, and adviser of these five hundred lay followers, yet neither I nor they have fulfilled the precepts. We’re the same, I’m in no way better. So let me do better.’

Then Gavesī went to those five hundred lay followers and said to them: ‘From this day forth may the venerables remember me as one who has fulfilled the precepts.’ Then those five hundred lay followers thought: ‘Master Gavesī is our helper, leader, and adviser, and now he will fulfill the precepts. Why don’t we do the same?’ Then those five hundred lay followers went to Gavesī and said to him: ‘From this day forth may Master Gavesī remember these five hundred lay followers as having fulfilled the precepts.’

Then Gavesī thought: ‘I’m the helper, leader, and adviser of these five hundred lay followers, and both I and they have fulfilled the precepts. We’re the same, I’m in no way better. So let me do better.’

Then Gavesī went to those five hundred lay followers and said to them: ‘From this day forth may the venerables remember me as one who is chaste, set apart, refraining from the vulgar act of sex.’ Then those five hundred lay followers did the same. …

Then Gavesī thought: ‘These five hundred lay followers … are chaste, set apart, refraining from the vulgar act of sex. We’re the same, I’m in no way better. So let me do better.’

Then Gavesī went to those five hundred lay followers and said to them: ‘From this day forth may the venerables remember me as one who eats in one part of the day, abstaining from eating at night, and from food at the wrong time.’ Then those five hundred lay followers did the same. …

Then Gavesī thought: ‘These five hundred lay followers … eat in one part of the day, abstaining from eating at night, and food at the wrong time. We’re the same, I’m in no way better. So let me do better.’

Then the lay follower Gavesī went up to the blessed one Kassapa, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha and said to him: ‘Sir, may I receive the going forth, the ordination in the Buddha’s presence?’ And he received the going forth, the ordination in the Buddha’s presence. Not long after his ordination, the mendicant Gavesī, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: ‘Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.’ And the mendicant Gavesī became one of the perfected.

Then those five hundred lay followers thought: ‘Master Gavesī is our helper, leader, and adviser, He has shaved off his hair and beard, dressed in ocher robes, and gone forth from the lay life to homelessness. Why don’t we do the same?’ Then those five hundred lay followers went up to the blessed one Kassapa, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha and said to him: ‘Sir, may we receive the going forth and ordination in the Buddha’s presence?’ And they did receive the going forth and ordination in the Buddha’s presence.

Then the mendicant Gavesī thought: ‘I get the supreme bliss of freedom whenever I want, without trouble or difficulty. Oh, may these five hundred mendicants do the same!’ Then those five hundred mendicants, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. They lived having achieved with their own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

They understood: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’

And so, Ānanda, those five hundred mendicants headed by Gavesī, trying to go higher and higher, better and better, realized the supreme bliss of freedom. So you should train like this: ‘Trying to go higher and higher, better and better, we will realize the supreme bliss of freedom.’ That’s how you should train.”

The Chapter on a Warrior

AN 5.71 Freedom of Heart is the Fruit (1st) Paṭhamacetovimuttiphalasutta

“Mendicants, these five things, when developed and cultivated, have freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom as their fruit and benefit.

What five? A mendicant meditates observing the ugliness of the body, perceives the repulsiveness of food, perceives dissatisfaction with the whole world, observes the impermanence of all conditions, and has well established the perception of their own death. These five things, when developed and cultivated, have freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom as their fruit and benefit. When a mendicant has freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, such a mendicant is one who is called ‘one who has lifted the cross-bar’, ‘one who has filled in the moat’, ‘one who has pulled up the pillar’, ‘one who is unimpeded’, and also ‘a noble one with banner lowered and burden dropped, detached’.

And how has a mendicant lifted the cross-bar? It’s when a mendicant has given up ignorance, cut it off at the root, made it like a palm stump, obliterated it, so it’s unable to arise in the future. That’s how a mendicant has lifted the cross-bar.

And how has a mendicant filled in the moat? It’s when a mendicant has given up transmigrating through births in future lives, cut it off at the root, made it like a palm stump, obliterated it, so it’s unable to arise in the future. That’s how a mendicant has filled in the moat.

And how has a mendicant pulled up the pillar? It’s when a mendicant has given up craving, cut it off at the root, made it like a palm stump, obliterated it, so it’s unable to arise in the future. That’s how a mendicant has pulled up the pillar.

And how is a mendicant unimpeded? It’s when a mendicant has given up the five lower fetters, cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so they’re unable to arise in the future. That’s how a mendicant is unimpeded.

And how is a mendicant a noble one with with banner lowered and burden dropped, detached? It’s when a mendicant has given up the conceit ‘I am’, cut it off at the root, made it like a palm stump, obliterated it, so it’s unable to arise in the future. That’s how a mendicant is a noble one with banner lowered and burden dropped, detached.”

AN 5.72 Freedom of Heart is the Fruit (2nd) Dutiyacetovimuttiphalasutta

“Mendicants, these five things, when developed and cultivated, have freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom as their fruit and benefit. What five?

The perception of impermanence, the perception of suffering in impermanence, the perception of not-self in suffering, the perception of giving up, and the perception of fading away.

These five things, when developed and cultivated, have freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom as their fruit and benefit.

When a mendicant has freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, such a mendicant is one who is called ‘one who has lifted the cross-bar’, ‘one who has filled in the moat’, ‘one who has pulled up the pillar’, ‘one who is unimpeded’, and also ‘a noble one with banner lowered and burden dropped, detached’. …”

AN 5.73 One Who Lives by the Teaching (1st) Paṭhamadhammavihārīsutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of ‘one who lives by the teaching’. How is a mendicant who lives by the teaching defined?”

“Mendicant, take a mendicant who memorizes the teaching—statements, mixed prose & verse, discussions, verses, inspired exclamations, legends, stories of past lives, amazing stories, and elaborations. They spend too much time studying that teaching. They neglect retreat, and are not committed to internal serenity of heart. That mendicant is called one who studies a lot, not one who lives by the teaching.

Furthermore, a mendicant teaches Dhamma in detail to others as they learned and memorized it. They spend too much time advocating that teaching. They neglect retreat, and are not committed to internal serenity of heart. That mendicant is called one who advocates a lot, not one who lives by the teaching.

Furthermore, a mendicant rehearses the teaching in detail as they learned and memorized it. They spend too much time reciting that teaching. They neglect retreat, and are not committed to internal serenity of heart. That mendicant is called one who rehearses a lot, not one who lives by the teaching.

Furthermore, a mendicant thinks about and considers the teaching in their heart, examining it with the mind as they learned and memorized it. They spend too much time thinking about that teaching. They neglect retreat, and are not committed to internal serenity of heart. That mendicant is called one who thinks a lot, not one who lives by the teaching.

Take a mendicant who memorizes the teaching—statements, mixed prose & verse, discussions, verses, inspired exclamations, legends, stories of past lives, amazing stories, and elaborations. They don’t spend too much time studying that teaching. They don’t neglect retreat, and they’re committed to internal serenity of heart. That’s how a mendicant is one who lives by the teaching.

So, mendicant, I’ve taught you the one who studies a lot, the one who advocates a lot, the one who rehearses a lot, the one who thinks a lot, and the one who lives by the teaching. Out of sympathy, I’ve done what a teacher should do who wants what’s best for their disciples. Here are these roots of trees, and here are these empty huts. Practice absorption, mendicant! Don’t be negligent! Don’t regret it later! This is my instruction to you.”

AN 5.74 One Who Lives by the Teaching (2nd) Dutiyadhammavihārīsutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of ‘one who lives by the teaching’. How is a mendicant who lives by the teaching defined?”

“Mendicant, take a mendicant who memorizes the teaching—statements, mixed prose & verse, discussions, verses, inspired exclamations, legends, stories of past lives, amazing stories, and elaborations. But they don’t understand the higher meaning. That mendicant is called one who studies a lot, not one who lives by the teaching.

Furthermore, a mendicant teaches Dhamma in detail to others as they learned and memorized it. But they don’t understand the higher meaning. That mendicant is called one who advocates a lot, not one who lives by the teaching.

Furthermore, a mendicant rehearses the teaching in detail as they learned and memorized it. But they don’t understand the higher meaning. That mendicant is called one who rehearses a lot, not one who lives by the teaching.

Furthermore, a mendicant thinks about and considers the teaching in their heart, examining it with the mind as they learned and memorized it. But they don’t understand the higher meaning. That mendicant is called one who thinks a lot, not one who lives by the teaching.

Take a mendicant who memorizes the teaching—statements, mixed prose & verse, discussions, verses, inspired exclamations, legends, stories of past lives, amazing stories, and elaborations. And they do understand the higher meaning. That’s how a mendicant is one who lives by the teaching.

So, mendicant, I’ve taught you the one who studies a lot, the one who advocates a lot, the one who rehearses a lot, the one who thinks a lot, and the one who lives by the teaching. Out of sympathy, I’ve done what a teacher should do who wants what’s best for their disciples. Here are these roots of trees, and here are these empty huts. Practice absorption, mendicant! Don’t be negligent! Don’t regret it later! This is my instruction to you.”

AN 5.75 Warriors (1st) Paṭhamayodhājīvasutta

“Mendicants, these five warriors are found in the world. What five?

Firstly, one warrior falters and founders at the mere sight of a cloud of dust. He doesn’t stay firm, and fails to plunge into battle. Some warriors are like that. This is the first warrior found in the world.

Furthermore, one warrior can prevail over a cloud of dust, but he falters and founders at the mere sight of a banner’s crest. He doesn’t stay firm, and fails to plunge into battle. Some warriors are like that. This is the second warrior found in the world.

Furthermore, one warrior can prevail over a cloud of dust and a banner’s crest, but he falters and founders at the mere sound of turmoil. He doesn’t stay firm, and fails to plunge into battle. Some warriors are like that. This is the third warrior found in the world.

Furthermore, one warrior can prevail over a cloud of dust and a banner’s crest and turmoil, but he’s killed or injured when blows are struck. Some warriors are like that. This is the fourth warrior found in the world.

Furthermore, one warrior can prevail over a cloud of dust and a banner’s crest and turmoil and being struck. He wins victory in battle, establishing himself as foremost in battle. Some warriors are like that. This is the fifth warrior found in the world.

These are the five warriors found in the world.

In the same way, these five individuals similar to warriors are found among the monks. What five?

Firstly, one monk falters and founders at the mere sight of a cloud of dust. He doesn’t stay firm, and fails to keep up the spiritual life. Declaring his inability to continue training, he resigns it and returns to a lesser life. What is his ‘cloud of dust’? It’s when a monk hears: ‘In such-and-such village or town there’s a woman or a girl who is attractive, good-looking, lovely, of surpassing beauty.’ Hearing this, he falters and founders. He doesn’t stay firm, and fails to keep up the spiritual life. Declaring his inability to continue training, he resigns it and returns to a lesser life. This is his ‘cloud of dust’.

I say that this individual is like the warrior who falters and founders at the mere sight of a cloud of dust. Some individuals are like that. This is the first individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

Furthermore, one monk can prevail over a cloud of dust, but at the mere sight of a banner’s crest he falters and founders. He doesn’t stay firm, and fails to keep up the spiritual life. Declaring his inability to continue training, he resigns it and returns to a lesser life. What is his ‘banner’s crest’? It’s when a monk doesn’t hear: ‘In such-and-such village or town there’s a woman or a girl who is attractive, good-looking, lovely, of surpassing beauty.’ But he sees for himself a woman or a girl who is attractive, good-looking, lovely, of surpassing beauty. Seeing her, he falters and founders. He doesn’t stay firm, and fails to keep up the spiritual life. Declaring his inability to continue training, he resigns it and returns to a lesser life. This is his ‘banner’s crest’.

I say that this individual is like the warrior who can prevail over a cloud of dust, but he falters and founders at the mere sight of a banner’s crest. Some individuals are like that. This is the second individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

Furthermore, one monk can prevail over a cloud of dust and a banner’s crest, but he falters and founders at the mere sound of turmoil. He doesn’t stay firm, and fails to keep up the spiritual life. Declaring his inability to continue training, he resigns it and returns to a lesser life. What is his ‘turmoil’? It’s when a mendicant who has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut is approached by a lady. She smiles, chats, laughs, and teases him. He falters and founders. He doesn’t stay firm, and fails to keep up the spiritual life. Declaring his inability to continue training, he resigns it and returns to a lesser life. This is his ‘turmoil’.

I say that this individual is like the warrior who can prevail over a cloud of dust and a banner’s crest, but he falters and founders at the mere sound of turmoil. Some individuals are like that. This is the third individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

Furthermore, one monk can prevail over a cloud of dust and a banner’s crest and turmoil, but he’s killed or injured when blows are struck. What is his ‘blows are struck’? It’s when a mendicant who has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut is approached by a lady. She sits right by him, lies down, or embraces him. Without resigning the training and declaring his inability to continue, he indulges in sex. This is his ‘blows are struck’.

I say that this individual is like the warrior who can prevail over a cloud of dust and a banner’s crest and turmoil, but is killed or injured when blows are struck. Some individuals are like that. This is the fourth individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

Furthermore, one monk can prevail over a cloud of dust and a banner’s crest and turmoil, and being struck. He wins victory in battle, establishing himself as foremost in battle. What is his ‘victory in battle’? It’s when a mendicant who has gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut is approached by a lady. She sits right by him, lies down, or embraces him. But he disentangles and frees himself, and goes wherever he wants. He frequents a secluded lodging—a wilderness, the root of a tree, a hill, a ravine, a mountain cave, a charnel ground, a forest, the open air, a heap of straw.

Gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, he sits down cross-legged, sets his body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present. Giving up covetousness for the world, he meditates with a heart rid of covetousness, cleansing the mind of covetousness. Giving up ill will and malevolence, he meditates with a mind rid of ill will, full of sympathy for all living beings, cleansing the mind of ill will. Giving up dullness and drowsiness, he meditates with a mind rid of dullness and drowsiness, perceiving light, mindful and aware, cleansing the mind of dullness and drowsiness. Giving up restlessness and remorse, he meditates without restlessness, his mind settled internally, cleansing the mind of restlessness and remorse. Giving up doubt, he meditates having gone beyond doubt, not undecided about skillful qualities, cleansing the mind of doubt. He gives up these five hindrances, corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom. Then, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, he enters and remains in the first absorption … second absorption … third absorption … fourth absorption.

When his mind has become immersed in samādhi like this—purified, bright, flawless, rid of corruptions, pliable, workable, steady, and imperturbable—he extends it toward knowledge of the ending of defilements. He truly understands: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. He truly understands: ‘These are defilements’ … ‘This is the origin of defilements’ … ‘This is the cessation of defilements’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of defilements’. Knowing and seeing like this, his mind is freed from the defilements of sensuality, desire to be reborn, and ignorance. When he’s freed, he knows he’s freed.

He understands: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’ This is his ‘victory in battle’.

I say that this individual is like the warrior who can prevail over a cloud of dust and a banner’s crest and turmoil and being struck. He wins victory in battle, establishing himself as foremost in battle. Some individuals are like that. This is the fifth individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

These five individuals similar to warriors are found among the monks.”

AN 5.76 Warriors (2nd) Dutiyayodhājīvasutta

“Mendicants, these five warriors are found in the world. What five?

Firstly, one warrior dons his sword and shield, fastens his bow and arrows, and plunges into the thick of battle. He strives and struggles in the battle, but his foes kill him and finish him off. Some warriors are like that. This is the first warrior found in the world.

Furthermore, one warrior dons his sword and shield, fastens his bow and arrows, and plunges into the thick of battle. He strives and struggles in the battle, but his foes wound him. He’s carried off and taken to his relatives, but he dies on the road before he reaches them. Some warriors are like that. This is the second warrior found in the world.

Furthermore, one warrior dons his sword and shield, fastens his bow and arrows, and plunges into the thick of battle. He strives and struggles in the battle, but his foes wound him. He’s carried off and taken to his relatives, who nurse him and care for him. But he dies of his injuries while in their care. Some warriors are like that. This is the third warrior found in the world.

Furthermore, one warrior dons his sword and shield, fastens his bow and arrows, and plunges into the thick of battle. He strives and struggles in the battle, but his foes wound him. He’s carried off and taken to his relatives, who nurse him and care for him. And while in their care, he recovers from his injuries. Some warriors are like that. This is the fourth warrior found in the world.

Furthermore, one warrior dons his sword and shield, fastens his bow and arrows, and plunges into the thick of battle. He wins victory in battle, establishing himself as foremost in battle. Some warriors are like that. This is the fifth warrior found in the world. These are the five warriors found in the world.

In the same way, these five individuals similar to warriors are found among the monks. What five? Firstly, a mendicant lives supported by a town or village. He robes up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, enters a village or town for alms without guarding body, speech, and mind, without establishing mindfulness, and without restraining the sense faculties. There he sees a lady scantily clad, with revealing clothes. Lust infects his mind, and, without resigning the training and declaring his inability to continue, he indulges in sex.

I say that this individual is like the warrior who is killed and finished off by his foes. Some individuals are like that. This is the first individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives supported by a town or village. He robes up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, enters a village or town for alms without guarding body, speech, and mind, without establishing mindfulness, and without restraining the sense faculties. There he sees a lady scantily clad, with revealing clothes. Lust infects his mind, and his body and mind burn with it. He thinks: ‘Why don’t I visit the monastery and tell the monks:

“Reverends, I am overcome with lust, mired in lust. I am unable to keep up the spiritual life. I declare my inability to continue training. I resign it and will return to a lesser life.”’ But while traveling on the road, before he reaches the monastery he declares his inability to continue training. He resigns and returns to a lesser life.

I say that they are like the warrior who is taken to his relatives for care, but he dies on the road before he reaches them. Some individuals are like that. This is the second individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives supported by a town or village. He robes up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, enters a village or town for alms without guarding body, speech, and mind, without establishing mindfulness, and without restraining the sense faculties. There he sees a lady scantily clad, with revealing clothes. Lust infects his mind, and his body and mind burn with it. He thinks: ‘Why don’t I visit the monastery and tell the monks:

“Reverends, I am overcome with lust, mired in lust. I am unable to keep up the spiritual life. I declare my inability to continue training. I resign and will return to a lesser life.”’ He goes to the monastery and tells the monks: ‘Reverends, I am overcome with lust, mired in lust. I am unable to keep up the spiritual life. I declare my inability to continue training. I disavow it and will return to a lesser life.’

His spiritual companions advise and instruct him: ‘Reverend, the Buddha says that sensual pleasures give little gratification and much suffering and distress, and they are all the more full of drawbacks. With the similes of a skeleton … a scrap of meat … a grass torch … a pit of glowing coals … a dream … borrowed goods … fruit on a tree … a butcher’s knife and chopping board … swords and spears … a cobra’s head, the Buddha says that sensual pleasures give little gratification and much suffering and distress, and they are all the more full of drawbacks. Be happy with the spiritual life. Venerable, please don’t declare your inability to continue training, resign it and return to a lesser life.’

When thus advised and instructed by his spiritual companions, he says: ‘Reverends, even though the Buddha says that sensual pleasures give little gratification and much suffering and distress, and they are all the more full of drawbacks, I am unable to keep up the spiritual life. I declare my inability to continue training. I resign it and will return to a lesser life.’ Declaring his inability to continue training, he resigns it and returns to a lesser life.

I say that they are like the warrior who dies of his injuries while in the care of his relatives. Some individuals are like that. This is the third individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives supported by a town or village. He robes up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, enters a village or town for alms without guarding body, speech, and mind, without establishing mindfulness, and without restraining the sense faculties. There he sees a lady scantily clad, with revealing clothes. Lust infects his mind, and his body and mind burn with it. He thinks: ‘Why don’t I visit the monastery and tell the monks:

“Reverends, I am overcome with lust, mired in lust. I am unable to keep up the spiritual life. I declare my inability to continue training. I resign it and will return to a lesser life.”’ He goes to the monastery and tells the monks: ‘Reverends, I am overcome with lust, mired in lust. I am unable to keep up the spiritual life. I declare my inability to continue training. I resign it and will return to a lesser life.’

His spiritual companions advise and instruct him: ‘Reverend, the Buddha says that sensual pleasures give little gratification and much suffering and distress, and they are all the more full of drawbacks. With the simile of a skeleton … a scrap of meat … a grass torch … a pit of glowing coals … a dream … borrowed goods … fruit on a tree … a butcher’s knife and chopping board … swords and spears … a cobra’s head, the Buddha says that sensual pleasures give little gratification and much suffering and distress, and they are all the more full of drawbacks. Be happy with the spiritual life. Venerable, please don’t declare your inability to continue training, resign it and return to a lesser life.’

When thus advised and instructed by his spiritual companions, he says: ‘I’ll make an attempt, reverends, I’ll struggle, I’ll be happy. I won’t now declare my inability to continue training, resign it and return to a lesser life.’

I say that this individual is like the warrior who recovers from his injuries while in the care of his relatives. Some individuals are like that. This is the fourth individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives supported by a town or village. He robes up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, enters a village or town, guarding body, speech, and mind, establishing mindfulness, and restraining the sense faculties. Seeing a sight with his eyes, he doesn’t get caught up in the features and details. If the faculty of sight were left unrestrained, bad unskillful qualities of covetousness and displeasure would become overwhelming. For this reason, he practices restraint, protecting the faculty of sight, and achieving its restraint. Hearing a sound with his ears … Smelling an odor with his nose … Tasting a flavor with his tongue … Encountering a touch with his body … Knowing an idea with his mind, he doesn’t get caught up in the features and details. If the faculty of mind were left unrestrained, bad unskillful qualities of covetousness and displeasure would become overwhelming. For this reason, he practices restraint, protecting the faculty of mind, and achieving its restraint. Then after the meal, on his return from almsround, he frequents a secluded lodging—a wilderness, the root of a tree, a hill, a ravine, a mountain cave, a charnel ground, a forest, the open air, a heap of straw. Gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, he sits down cross-legged, sets his body straight, and brings mindfulness to the present. He gives up these five hindrances, corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom. Then, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, he enters and remains in the first absorption … second absorption … third absorption … fourth absorption.

When his mind has become immersed in samādhi like this—purified, bright, flawless, rid of corruptions, pliable, workable, steady, and imperturbable—he extends it toward knowledge of the ending of defilements. He truly understands: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. He truly understands: ‘These are defilements’ … ‘This is the origin of defilements’ … ‘This is the cessation of defilements’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of defilements’. Knowing and seeing like this, his mind is freed from the defilements of sensuality, desire to be reborn, and ignorance. When he’s freed, he knows he’s freed. He understands: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’

I say that this individual is like the warrior who dons his sword and shield, fastens his bow and arrows, and plunges into the thick of battle. He wins victory in battle, establishing himself as foremost in battle. Some individuals are like that. This is the fifth individual similar to a warrior found among the monks.

These five individuals similar to warriors are found among the monks.”

AN 5.77 Future Perils (1st) Paṭhamaanāgatabhayasutta

“Mendicants, seeing these five future perils is quite enough for a wilderness mendicant to meditate diligently, keenly, and resolutely for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized.

What five? Firstly, a wilderness mendicant reflects: ‘Currently I’m living alone in a wilderness. While living here alone I might get bitten by a snake, a scorpion, or a centipede. And if I died from that it would be an obstacle to my progress. I’d better rouse up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized.’ This is the first future peril …

Furthermore, a wilderness mendicant reflects: ‘Currently I’m living alone in a wilderness. While living here alone I might stumble off a cliff, or get food poisoning, or suffer a disturbance of bile, phlegm, or piercing winds. And if I died from that it would be an obstacle to my progress. I’d better rouse up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized.’ This is the second future peril …

Furthermore, a wilderness mendicant reflects: ‘Currently I’m living alone in a wilderness. While living here alone I might encounter wild beasts—a lion, a tiger, a leopard, a bear, or a hyena—which might take my life. And if I died from that it would be an obstacle to my progress. I’d better rouse up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized.’ This is the third future peril …

Furthermore, a wilderness mendicant reflects: ‘Currently I’m living alone in a wilderness. While living here alone I might encounter youths escaping a crime or on their way to commit one, and they might take my life. And if I died from that it would be an obstacle to my progress. I’d better rouse up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized.’ This is the fourth future peril …

Furthermore, a wilderness mendicant reflects: ‘Currently I’m living alone in a wilderness. But in a wilderness there are savage monsters who might take my life. And if I died from that it would be an obstacle to my progress. I’d better rouse up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized.’ This is the fifth future peril …

These are the five future perils, seeing which is quite enough for a wilderness mendicant to meditate diligently, keenly, and resolutely for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized.”

AN 5.78 Future Perils (2nd) Dutiyaanāgatabhayasutta

“Mendicants, seeing these five future perils is quite enough for a mendicant to meditate diligently, keenly, and resolutely for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized. What five?

A mendicant reflects: ‘Currently I’m a youth, young, with pristine black hair, blessed with youth, in the prime of life. But there will come a time when this body is struck with old age. When you’re old, overcome by old age, it’s not easy to focus on the instructions of the Buddhas, and it’s not easy to frequent remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. Before that unlikable, undesirable, and disagreeable thing happens, I’d better preempt it by rousing up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized. That way, when it happens, I’ll live comfortably even though I’m old.’ This is the first future peril …

Furthermore, a mendicant reflects: ‘Currently, I’m rarely ill or unwell. My stomach digests well, being neither too hot nor too cold, but just right, and fit for meditation. But there will come a time when this body is struck with sickness. When you’re sick, overcome by sickness, it’s not easy to focus on the instructions of the Buddhas, and it’s not easy to frequent remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. Before that unlikable, undesirable, and disagreeable thing happens, I’d better preempt it by rousing up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized. That way, when it happens, I’ll live comfortably even though I’m sick.’ This is the second future peril …

Furthermore, a mendicant reflects: ‘Currently, there’s plenty of food, a good harvest, so it’s easy to get almsfood, and easy to keep going by collecting alms. But there will come a time of famine, a bad harvest, when it’s hard to get almsfood, and not easy to keep going by collecting alms. In a time of famine, people move to where there’s plenty of food, where they live crowded and cramped together. When you live crowded and cramped together, it’s not easy to focus on the instructions of the Buddhas, and it’s not easy to frequent remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. Before that unlikable, undesirable, and disagreeable thing happens, I’d better preempt it by rousing up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized. That way, when it happens, I’ll live comfortably even though there’s a famine.’ This is the third future peril …

Furthermore, a mendicant reflects: ‘Currently, people live in harmony, appreciating each other, without dispute, blending like milk and water, and regarding each other with kindly eyes. But there will come a time of peril due to turmoil in the wilds, so the countryfolk mount their vehicles and flee everywhere. In a time of peril, people move to where there’s sanctuary, where they live crowded and cramped together. When you live crowded and cramped together, it’s not easy to focus on the instructions of the Buddhas, and it’s not easy to frequent remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. Before that unlikable, undesirable, and disagreeable thing happens, I’d better preempt it by rousing up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized. That way, when it happens, I’ll live comfortably even in a time of peril.’ This is the fourth future peril …

Furthermore, a mendicant reflects: ‘Currently, the Saṅgha lives comfortably, in harmony, appreciating each other, without dispute, with one recitation. But there will come a time of schism in the Saṅgha. When there is schism in the Saṅgha, it’s not easy to focus on the instructions of the Buddhas, and it’s not easy to frequent remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. Before that unlikable, undesirable, and disagreeable thing happens, I’d better preempt it by rousing up energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized. That way, when it happens, I’ll live comfortably even though there’s schism in the Saṅgha.’ This is the fifth future peril …

These are the five future perils, seeing which is quite enough for a mendicant to meditate diligently, keenly, and resolutely for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized.”

AN 5.79 Future Perils (3rd) Tatiyaanāgatabhayasutta

“Mendicants, these five future perils have not currently arisen, but they will arise in the future. You should look out for them and try to give them up.

What five? In a future time there will be mendicants who have not developed their physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom. They will ordain others, but be unable to guide them in the higher ethics, mind, and wisdom. They too will not develop their physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom. They too will ordain others, but be unable to guide them in the higher ethics, mind, and wisdom. They too will not develop their physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom. And that is how corrupt training comes from corrupt teachings, and corrupt teachings come from corrupt training. This is the first future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

Furthermore, in a future time there will be mendicants who have not developed their physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom. They will give dependence to others, but be unable to guide them in the higher ethics, mind, and wisdom. They too will not develop their physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom. They too will give dependence to others, but be unable to guide them in the higher ethics, mind, and wisdom. They too will not develop their physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom. And that is how corrupt training comes from corrupt teachings, and corrupt teachings come from corrupt training. This is the second future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

Furthermore, in a future time there will be mendicants who have not developed their physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom. In discussion about the teachings and elaborations they’ll fall into dark ideas without realizing it. And that is how corrupt training comes from corrupt teachings, and corrupt teachings come from corrupt training. This is the third future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

Furthermore, in a future time there will be mendicants who have not developed their physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom. When discourses spoken by the Realized One—deep, profound, transcendent, dealing with emptiness—are being recited they won’t want to listen. They won’t actively listen or try to understand, nor will they think those teachings are worth learning and memorizing. But when discourses composed by poets—poetry, with fancy words and phrases, composed by outsiders or spoken by disciples—are being recited they will want to listen. They’ll actively listen and try to understand, and they’ll think those teachings are worth learning and memorizing. And that is how corrupt training comes from corrupt teachings, and corrupt teachings come from corrupt training. This is the fourth future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

Furthermore, in a future time there will be mendicants who have not developed their physical endurance, ethics, mind, and wisdom. The senior mendicants will be indulgent and slack, leaders in backsliding, neglecting seclusion, not rousing energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized. Those who come after them will follow their example. They too will become indulgent and slack, leaders in backsliding, neglecting seclusion, not rousing energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized. And that is how corrupt training comes from corrupt teachings, and corrupt teachings come from corrupt training. This is the fifth future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

These are the five future perils that have not currently arisen, but will arise in the future. You should look out for them, and try to give them up.”

AN 5.80 Future Perils (4th) Catutthaanāgatabhayasutta

“Mendicants, these five future perils have not currently arisen, but they will arise in the future. You should look out for them and try to give them up.

What five? In a future time there will be mendicants who like nice robes. They will neglect the practice of wearing rag robes and the practice of frequenting remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. They will come down to the villages, towns, and capital cities and make their homes there. And they will employ many kinds of improper solicitation for the sake of a robe. This is the first future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

Furthermore, in a future time there will be mendicants who like nice almsfood. They will neglect the practice of walking for almsfood and the practice of frequenting remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. They will come down to the villages, towns, and capital cities and make their home there. And they will employ many kinds of improper solicitation for the sake of almsfood. This is the second future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

Furthermore, in a future time there will be mendicants who like nice lodgings. They will neglect the practice of staying at the root of a tree and the practice of frequenting remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. They will come down to the villages, towns, and capital cities and make their home there. And they will employ many kinds of improper solicitation for the sake of lodgings. This is the third future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

Furthermore, in a future time there will be mendicants who mix closely with nuns, trainee nuns, and novice nuns. In such conditions, it can be expected that they will lead the spiritual life dissatisfied, or commit one of the corrupt offenses, or resign the training and return to a lesser life. This is the fourth future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

Furthermore, in a future time there will be mendicants who mix closely with monastery attendants and novices. In such conditions it can be expected that they will engage in storing up goods for their own use, and making obvious hints about digging the earth and cutting plants. This is the fifth future peril that has not currently arisen, but will arise in the future …

These are the five future perils that have not currently arisen, but will arise in the future. You should look out for them and try to give them up.”

The Chapter on Benefit

AN 6.96 Appearance Pātubhāvasutta

“Mendicants, the appearance of six things is rare in the world. What six? A Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha. A teacher of the teaching and training proclaimed by a Realized One. Rebirth in a civilized region. Unimpaired sense faculties. Being bright and clever. Enthusiasm for skillful qualities. The appearance of these six things is rare in the world.”

AN 6.97 Benefit Ānisaṁsasutta

“Mendicants, these are the six benefits of realizing the fruit of stream-entry. What six? You’re bound for the true teaching. You’re not liable to decline. You suffer only for a limited period. You have distinct knowledge. You’ve clearly seen causes and the phenomena that arise from causes. These are the six benefits of realizing the fruit of stream-entry.”

AN 6.98 Impermanence Aniccasutta

“Mendicants, it is quite impossible for a mendicant who regards any condition as permanent to accept views that conform with the teaching. Without accepting views that conform with the teaching, it’s impossible to step into the sure path. Without stepping into the sure path, it’s impossible to realize the fruit of stream-entry, once-return, non-return, or perfection.

It’s quite possible for a mendicant who regards all conditions as impermanent to accept views that conform with the teaching. Having accepted views that conform with the teaching, it’s possible to step into the sure path. Having stepped into the sure path, it’s possible to realize the fruit of stream-entry, once-return, non-return, or perfection.”

AN 6.99 Suffering Dukkhasutta

“Mendicants, it is quite impossible for a mendicant who regards any condition as pleasurable to accept views that agree with the teaching. … It’s quite possible for a mendicant who regards all conditions as suffering to accept views that agree with the teaching. …”

AN 6.100 Not-Self Anattasutta

“Mendicants, it is quite impossible for a mendicant who regards any thing as self to accept views that agree with the teaching. … It’s quite possible for a mendicant who regards all things as not-self to accept views that agree with the teaching. …”

AN 6.101 Extinguished Nibbānasutta

“Mendicants, it is quite impossible for a mendicant who regards extinguishment as suffering to accept views that conform with the teaching. …

It’s quite possible for a mendicant who regards extinguishment as pleasurable to accept views that conform with the teaching. …”

AN 6.102 Transience Anavatthitasutta

“Mendicants, seeing six benefits is quite enough to establish the perception of impermanence in all conditions without qualification. What six? ‘All conditions will appear to me as transient.’ ‘My mind will not delight anywhere in the world.’ ‘My mind will rise above the whole world.’ ‘My heart will incline to extinguishment.’ ‘My fetters will be given up.’ ‘I will achieve the ultimate goal of the ascetic life.’ Seeing these six benefits is quite enough to establish the perception of impermanence in all conditions without qualification.”

AN 6.103 With a Drawn Sword Ukkhittāsikasutta

“Mendicants, seeing six benefits is quite enough to establish the perception of suffering in all conditions without qualification. What six? ‘Perception of disillusionment will be established in me for all conditions, like a killer with a drawn sword.’ ‘My mind will rise above the whole world.’ ‘I will see extinguishment as peaceful.’ ‘My underlying tendencies will be uprooted.’ ‘I will fulfill my duty.’ ‘I will have served my Teacher with love.’ Seeing these six benefits is quite enough to establish the perception of suffering in all conditions without qualification.”

AN 6.104 Not Determined by Anything Atammayasutta

“Mendicants, seeing six benefits is quite enough to establish the perception of not-self in all things without qualification. What six? ‘I will not be determined by anything in the world.’ ‘My I-making will stop.’ ‘My mine-making will stop.’ ‘I will have distinct knowledge.’ ‘I will clearly see causes and the phenomena that arise from causes.’ Seeing these six benefits is quite enough to establish the perception of not-self in all things without qualification.”

AN 6.105 States of Existence Bhavasutta

“Mendicants, you should give up these three states of existence. And you should train in three trainings. What are the three states of existence you should give up? Existence in the sensual realm, the realm of luminous form, and the formless realm. These are the three states of existence you should give up. What are the three trainings you should train in? The training in the higher ethics, the higher mind, and the higher wisdom. These are the three trainings you should train in. When a mendicant has given up these three states of existence and has trained in these three trainings they’re called a mendicant who has cut off craving, cast off the fetters, and by rightly comprehending conceit has made an end of suffering.”

AN 6.106 Craving Taṇhāsutta

“Mendicants, you should give up these three cravings and three conceits. What three cravings should you give up? Craving for sensual pleasures, craving for continued existence, and craving for nonexistence. These are the three cravings you should give up. What three conceits should you give up? Conceit, inferiority complex, and superiority complex. These are the three conceits you should give up. When a mendicant has given up these three cravings and these three conceits they’re called a mendicant who has cut off craving, cast off the fetters, and by rightly comprehending conceit has made an end of suffering.”

The Chapter on Unsurpassable

AN 6.21 At Sāma Village Sāmakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans near the little village of Sāma, by a lotus pond.

Then, late at night, a glorious deity, lighting up the entire lotus pond, went up to the Buddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him, “Sir, three qualities lead to the decline of a mendicant. What three? Relishing work, talk, and sleep. These three qualities lead to the decline of a mendicant.”

That is what that deity said, and the Teacher concurred. Then that deity, knowing that the Teacher concurred, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before vanishing right there.

Then, when the night had passed, the Buddha told the mendicants all that had happened, adding:

“It’s unfortunate for those of you who even the deities know are declining in skillful qualities. I will teach you three more qualities that lead to decline. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what, mendicants, are three qualities that lead to decline? Enjoyment of company, being hard to admonish, and having bad friends. These three qualities lead to decline.

Whether in the past, future, or present, all those who decline in skillful qualities do so because of these six qualities.”

AN 6.22 Non-decline Aparihāniyasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you these six principles that prevent decline. … And what, mendicants, are the six principles that prevent decline? Not relishing work, talk, sleep, and company, being easy to admonish, and having good friends. These six qualities prevent decline.

Whether in the past, future, or present, all those who have not declined in skillful qualities do so because of these six qualities.”

AN 6.23 Dangers Bhayasutta

“‘Danger’, mendicants, is a term for sensual pleasures. ‘Suffering’, ‘disease’, ‘boil’, ‘chain’, and ‘bog’ are terms for sensual pleasures.

And why is ‘danger’ a term for sensual pleasures? Someone who is besotted by sensual greed and shackled by lustful desire is not freed from dangers in this life or in lives to come. That is why ‘danger’ is a term for sensual pleasures.

And why are ‘suffering’, ‘disease’, ‘boil’, ‘chain’, and ‘bog’ terms for sensual pleasures? Someone who is besotted by sensual greed and shackled by lustful desire is not freed from suffering, disease, boils, chains, or bogs in this life or in lives to come. That is why these are terms for sensual pleasures.

Danger, suffering, disease, boils,
and chains and bogs both.
These describe the sensual pleasures
to which ordinary people are attached.

Seeing the danger in grasping,
the origin of birth and death,
the unattached are freed
with the ending of birth and death.

Happy, they’ve come to a safe place,
quenched in this very life.
They’ve gone beyond all enmities and fears,
and risen above all suffering.”

AN 6.24 The Himalaya Himavantasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant who has six qualities could shatter Himalaya, the king of mountains, let alone this wretched ignorance! What six? It’s when a mendicant is skilled in entering immersion, skilled in remaining in immersion, skilled in emerging from immersion, skilled in positivity for immersion, skilled in the territory of immersion, and skilled in projecting the mind purified by immersion. A mendicant who possesses these six qualities could shatter Himalaya, the king of mountains, let alone this wretched ignorance!”

AN 6.25 Topics for Recollection Anussatiṭṭhānasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six topics for recollection. What six?

Firstly, a noble disciple recollects the Realized One: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ When a noble disciple recollects the Realized One their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving. They’ve left behind greed; they’re free of it and have risen above it. ‘Greed’ is a term for the five kinds of sensual stimulation. Relying on this, some sentient beings are purified in this way.

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’ When a noble disciple recollects the teaching their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. …

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.’ When a noble disciple recollects the Saṅgha their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. …

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects their own ethical precepts, which are intact, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. When a noble disciple recollects their ethical precepts their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. …

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects their generosity: ‘I’m so fortunate, so very fortunate! Among people full of the stain of stinginess I live at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share.’ When a noble disciple recollects their generosity their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. …

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects the deities: ‘There are the gods of the four great kings, the gods of the thirty-three, the gods of Yama, the joyful gods, the gods who love to create, the gods who control what is created by others, the gods of the Divinity’s host, and gods even higher than these. When those deities passed away from here, they were reborn there because of their faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. I, too, have the same kind of faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom.’

When a noble disciple recollects the faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom of both themselves and the deities their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving. They’ve left behind greed; they’re free of it and have risen above it. ‘Greed’ is a term for the five kinds of sensual stimulation. Relying on this, some sentient beings are purified in this way.

These are the six topics for recollection.”

AN 6.26 With Mahākaccāna Mahākaccānasutta

There Mahākaccāna addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Venerable Mahākaccāna said this:

“It’s incredible, reverends, it’s amazing! How this Blessed One who knows and sees, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha, has found an opening amid confinement; that is, the six topics for recollection. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment. What six?

Firstly, a noble disciple recollects the Realized One: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ When a noble disciple recollects the Realized One their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving. They’ve left behind greed; they’re free of it and have risen above it. ‘Greed’ is a term for the five kinds of sensual stimulation. That noble disciple meditates with a heart just like space, abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Relying on this, some sentient beings become pure in this way.

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’ When a noble disciple recollects the teaching their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. …

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.’ When a noble disciple recollects the Saṅgha their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. …

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects their own ethical precepts, which are intact, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. When a noble disciple recollects their ethical precepts their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. …

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects their generosity: ‘I’m so fortunate, so very fortunate! Among people full of the stain of stinginess I live at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share.’ When a noble disciple recollects their generosity their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. …

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects the deities: ‘There are the gods of the four great kings, the gods of the thirty-three, the gods of Yama, the joyful gods, the gods who love to create, the gods who control what is created by others, the gods of the Divinity’s host, and gods even higher than these. When those deities passed away from here, they were reborn there because of their faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. I, too, have the same kind of faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom.’ When a noble disciple recollects the faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom of both themselves and the deities their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving. They’ve left behind greed; they’re free of it and have risen above it. ‘Greed’ is a term for the five kinds of sensual stimulation. That noble disciple meditates with a heart just like space, abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Relying on this, some sentient beings become pure in this way.

It’s incredible, reverends, it’s amazing! How this Blessed One who knows and sees, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha, has found an opening amid confinement; that is, the six topics for recollection. They are in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.”

AN 6.27 Proper Occasions (1st) Paṭhamasamayasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, how many occasions are there for going to see an esteemed mendicant?”

“Mendicant, there are six occasions for going to see an esteemed mendicant. What six?

Firstly, there’s a time when a mendicant’s heart is overcome and mired in sensual desire, and they don’t truly understand the escape from sensual desire that has arisen. On that occasion they should go to an esteemed mendicant and say: ‘My heart is overcome and mired in sensual desire, and I don’t truly understand the escape from sensual desire that has arisen. Venerable, please teach me how to give up sensual desire.’ Then that esteemed mendicant teaches them how to give up sensual desire. This is the first occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.

Furthermore, there’s a time when a mendicant’s heart is overcome and mired in ill will … This is the second occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.

Furthermore, there’s a time when a mendicant’s heart is overcome and mired in dullness and drowsiness … This is the third occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.

Furthermore, there’s a time when a mendicant’s heart is overcome and mired in restlessness and remorse … This is the fourth occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.

Furthermore, there’s a time when a mendicant’s heart is overcome and mired in doubt … This is the fifth occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.

Furthermore, there’s a time when a mendicant doesn’t understand what kind of meditation they need to focus on in order to end the defilements without delay. On that occasion they should go to an esteemed mendicant and say: ‘I don’t understand what kind of meditation to focus on in order to end the defilements without delay. Venerable, please teach me how to end the defilements.’ Then that esteemed mendicant teaches them how to end the defilements. This is the sixth occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.

These are the six occasions for going to see an esteemed mendicant.”

AN 6.28 Proper Occasions (2nd) Dutiyasamayasutta

At one time several senior mendicants were staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana. Then after the meal, on their return from almsround, this discussion came up among them while sitting together in the pavilion.

“Reverends, how many occasions are there for going to see an esteemed mendicant?”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to the senior mendicants:

“Reverends, there’s a time after an esteemed mendicant’s meal when they return from almsround. Having washed their feet they sit down cross-legged, set their body straight, and bring mindfulness to the present. That is the proper occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to that mendicant:

“Reverend, that’s not the proper occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant. For at that time the fatigue from walking and from eating has not faded away. There’s a time late in the afternoon when an esteemed mendicant comes out of retreat. They sit cross-legged in the shade of their porch, set their body straight, and bring mindfulness to the present. That is the proper occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to that mendicant:

“Reverend, that’s not the proper occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant. For at that time they are still practicing the same meditation subject as a basis of immersion that they focused on during the day. There’s a time when an esteemed mendicant has risen at the crack of dawn. They sit down cross-legged, set their body straight, and bring mindfulness to the present. That is the proper occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to that mendicant:

“Reverend, that’s not the proper occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant. For at that time their body is full of vitality and they find it easy to focus on the instructions of the Buddhas.”

When this was said, Venerable Mahākaccāna said to those senior mendicants:

“Reverends, I have heard and learned this in the presence of the Buddha: ‘Mendicant, there are six occasions for going to see an esteemed mendicant.

What six? Firstly, there’s a time when a mendicant’s heart is overcome and mired in sensual desire, and they don’t truly understand the escape from sensual desire that has arisen. On that occasion they should go to an esteemed mendicant and say:

“My heart is overcome and mired in sensual desire, and I don’t truly understand the escape from sensual desire that has arisen. Venerable, please teach me how to give up sensual desire.” Then that esteemed mendicant teaches them how to give up sensual desire. This is the first occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.

Furthermore, there’s a time when a mendicant’s heart is overcome and mired in ill will … dullness and drowsiness … restlessness and remorse … doubt …

Furthermore, there’s a time when a mendicant doesn’t understand what kind of meditation they need to focus on in order to end the defilements without delay. On that occasion they should go to an esteemed mendicant and say, “I don’t understand what kind of meditation to focus on in order to end the defilements without delay. Venerable, please teach me how to end the defilements.” Then that esteemed mendicant teaches them how to end the defilements. This is the sixth occasion for going to see an esteemed mendicant.’

Reverends, I have heard and learned this in the presence of the Buddha: ‘These are the six occasions for going to see an esteemed mendicant.’”

AN 6.29 With Udāyī Udāyīsutta

Then the Buddha said to Udāyī, “Udāyī, how many topics for recollection are there?”

When he said this, Udāyī kept silent.

And a second time … and a third time, the Buddha said to him, “Udāyī, how many topics for recollection are there?”

And a second time and a third time Udāyī kept silent.

Then Venerable Ānanda said to Venerable Udāyī, “Reverend Udāyī, the Teacher is addressing you.”

“Reverend Ānanda, I hear the Buddha.

It’s when a mendicant recollects many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. They remember: ‘There, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn somewhere else. There, too, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn here.’ And so they recollect their many kinds of past lives, with features and details. This is a topic for recollection.”

Then the Buddha said to Venerable Ānanda: “Ānanda, I know that this futile man Udāyī is not committed to the higher mind. Ānanda, how many topics for recollection are there?”

“Sir, there are five topics for recollection. What five?

Firstly, a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption … second absorption … third absorption. When this topic of recollection is developed and cultivated in this way it leads to blissful meditation in this very life.

Furthermore, a mendicant focuses on the perception of light, focusing on the perception of day regardless of whether it’s night or day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, they develop a mind that’s full of radiance. When this topic of recollection is developed and cultivated in this way it leads to knowledge and vision.

Furthermore, a mendicant examines their own body up from the soles of the feet and down from the tips of the hairs, wrapped in skin and full of many kinds of filth. ‘In this body there is head hair, body hair, nails, teeth, skin, flesh, sinews, bones, bone marrow, kidneys, heart, liver, diaphragm, spleen, lungs, intestines, mesentery, undigested food, feces, bile, phlegm, pus, blood, sweat, fat, tears, grease, saliva, snot, synovial fluid, urine.’ When this topic of recollection is developed and cultivated in this way it leads to giving up sensual desire.

Furthermore, suppose a mendicant were to see a corpse thrown in a charnel ground. And it had been dead for one, two, or three days, bloated, livid, and festering. They’d compare it with their own body: ‘This body is also of that same nature, that same kind, and cannot go beyond that.’

Or suppose they were to see a corpse thrown in a charnel ground being devoured by crows, hawks, vultures, hounds, jackals, and many kinds of little creatures. They’d compare it with their own body: ‘This body is also of that same nature, that same kind, and cannot go beyond that.’

Furthermore, suppose they were to see a corpse thrown in a charnel ground, a skeleton with flesh and blood, held together by sinews … A skeleton without flesh but smeared with blood, and held together by sinews … A skeleton rid of flesh and blood, held together by sinews … Bones rid of sinews scattered in every direction. Here a hand-bone, there a foot-bone, here a shin-bone, there a thigh-bone, here a hip-bone, there a rib-bone, here a back-bone, there an arm-bone, here a neck-bone, there a jaw-bone, here a tooth, there the skull … White bones, the color of shells … Decrepit bones, heaped in a pile … Bones rotted and crumbled to powder. They’d compare it with their own body: ‘This body is also of that same nature, that same kind, and cannot go beyond that.’ When this topic of recollection is developed and cultivated in this way it leads to uprooting the conceit ‘I am’.

Furthermore, giving up pleasure and pain, and ending former happiness and sadness, a mendicant enters and remains in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness. When this topic of recollection is developed and cultivated in this way it leads to the penetration of many elements. These are the five topics for recollection.”

“Good, good, Ānanda. Well then, Ānanda, you should also remember this sixth topic for recollection. In this case, a mendicant goes out mindfully, returns mindfully, stands mindfully, sits mindfully, lies down mindfully, and focuses on work mindfully. When this topic of recollection is developed and cultivated in this way it leads to mindfulness and situational awareness.”

AN 6.30 Unsurpassable Anuttariyasutta

“Mendicants, these six things are unsurpassable. What six? The unsurpassable seeing, listening, acquisition, training, service, and recollection.

And what is the unsurpassable seeing? Some people go to see an elephant-treasure, a horse-treasure, a jewel-treasure, or a diverse spectrum of sights; or ascetics and brahmins of wrong view and wrong practice. There is such a seeing, I don’t deny it. That seeing is low, crude, ordinary, ignoble, and pointless. It doesn’t lead to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. The unsurpassable seeing is when someone with settled faith and fondness, sure and devoted, goes to see a Realized One or their disciple. This is in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment. This is called the unsurpassable seeing. Such is the unsurpassable seeing.

But what of the unsurpassable hearing? Some people go to hear the sound of drums, arched harps, singing, or a diverse spectrum of sounds; or ascetics and brahmins of wrong view and wrong practice. There is such a hearing, I don’t deny it. That hearing … doesn’t lead to extinguishment. The unsurpassable hearing is when someone with settled faith and fondness, sure and devoted, goes to hear the teaching of a Realized One or one of his disciples. … This is called the unsurpassable hearing. Such is the unsurpassable seeing and hearing.

But what of the unsurpassable acquisition? Some people acquire a child, a wife, wealth, or a diverse spectrum of things; or they acquire faith in an ascetic or brahmin of wrong view and wrong practice. There is such an acquisition, I don’t deny it. That acquisition … doesn’t lead to extinguishment. The unsurpassable acquisition is when someone with settled faith and fondness, sure and devoted, acquires faith in a Realized One or their disciple. … This is called the unsurpassable acquisition. Such is the unsurpassable seeing, hearing, and acquisition.

But what of the unsurpassable training? Some people train in elephant riding, horse riding, chariot driving, archery, swordsmanship, or a diverse spectrum of things; or they train under an ascetic or brahmin of wrong view and wrong practice. There is such a training, I don’t deny it. That training … doesn’t lead to extinguishment. The unsurpassable training is when someone with settled faith and fondness, sure and devoted, trains in the higher ethics, the higher mind, and the higher wisdom in the teaching and training proclaimed by a Realized One. … This is called the unsurpassable training. Such is the unsurpassable seeing, hearing, acquisition, and training.

But what of the unsurpassable service? Some people serve an aristocrat, a brahmin, a householder, or a diverse spectrum of people; or they serve ascetics and brahmins of wrong view and wrong practice. There is such service, I don’t deny it. That service … doesn’t lead to extinguishment. The unsurpassable service is when someone with settled faith and fondness, sure and devoted, serves a Realized One or their disciple. … This is called the unsurpassable service. Such is the unsurpassable seeing, listening, acquisition, training, and service.

But what of the unsurpassable recollection? Some people recollect a child, a wife, wealth, or a diverse spectrum of things; or they recollect an ascetic or brahmin of wrong view and wrong practice. There is such recollection, I don’t deny it. That recollection is low, crude, ordinary, ignoble, and pointless. It doesn’t lead to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. The unsurpassable recollection is when someone with settled faith and fondness, sure and devoted, recollects a Realized One or their disciple. … This is called the unsurpassable recollection.

These are the six unsurpassable things.

They’ve gained the unsurpassed seeing,
the unsurpassed hearing,
and the unsurpassable acquisition.
They enjoy the unsurpassable training

and serve with care.
Then they develop recollection
connected with seclusion,
which is safe, and leads to freedom from death.

They rejoice in diligence,
alert and ethically restrained.
And in time they arrive
at the place where suffering ceases.”

The Chapter with Dhammika

AN 6.43 The Giant Nāgasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Then the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Sāvatthī for alms. Then, after the meal, on his return from almsround, he addressed Venerable Ānanda, “Come, Ānanda, let’s go to the stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother in the Eastern Monastery for the day’s meditation.”

“Yes, sir,” Ānanda replied.

So the Buddha went with Ānanda to the Eastern Monastery. In the late afternoon the Buddha came out of retreat and addressed Ānanda, “Come, Ānanda, let’s go to the eastern gate to bathe.”

“Yes, sir,” Ānanda replied. So the Buddha went with Ānanda to the eastern gate to bathe. When he had bathed and emerged from the water he stood in one robe drying his limbs.

Now, at that time King Pasenadi had a giant bull elephant called “White”. It emerged from the eastern gate to the beating and playing of musical instruments.

When people saw it they said, “The royal giant is so handsome! The royal giant is so good-looking! The royal giant is so lovely! The royal giant has such a big body!”

When they said this, Venerable Udāyī said to the Buddha, “Sir, is it only when they see elephants with such a big, formidable body that people say: ‘A giant, such a giant’? Or do they say it when they see any other creatures with big, formidable bodies?”

“Udāyī, when they see elephants with such a big, formidable body people say: ‘A giant, such a giant!’

And also when they see a horse with a big, formidable body …

When they see a bull with a big, formidable body …

When they see a serpent with a big, formidable body …

When they see a tree with a big, formidable body …

And when they see a human being with such a big, formidable body people say: ‘A giant, such a giant!’

But Udāyī, one who does nothing monstrous by way of body, speech, and mind is who I call a ‘giant’ in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.”

“It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! How well said this was by the Buddha: ‘But Udāyī, one who does nothing monstrous by way of body, speech, and mind is who I call a “giant” in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.’ And I celebrate the well-spoken words of the Buddha with these verses:

Awakened as a human being,
self-tamed and immersed in samādhi,
following the spiritual path,
he loves peace of mind.

Revered by people,
gone beyond all things,
even the gods revere him;
so I’ve heard from the perfected one.

He has transcended all fetters
and escaped from entanglements.
Delighting to renounce sensual pleasures,
he’s freed like lustrous gold from stone.

That giant outshines all,
like the Himalaya beside other mountains.
Of all those named ‘giant’,
he is truly named, supreme.

I shall extol the giant for you,
for he does nothing monstrous.
Gentleness and harmlessness
are two feet of the giant.

Fervor and chastity
are his two other feet.
Faith is the giant’s trunk,
and equanimity his white tusks.

Mindfulness is his neck, his head is wisdom—
inquiry and thinking about principles.
His belly is the sacred hearth of the Dhamma,
and his tail is seclusion.

Practicing absorption, enjoying the breath,
he is serene within.
The giant is serene when walking,
the giant is serene when standing,

the giant is serene when lying down,
and when sitting, the giant is serene.
The giant is restrained everywhere:
this is the accomplishment of the giant.

He eats blameless things,
he doesn’t eat blameworthy things.
When he gets food and clothes,
he avoids storing them up.

Having severed all bonds,
fetters large and small,
wherever he goes,
he goes without concern.

A white lotus,
fragrant and delightful,
sprouts in water and grows there,
but water does not stick to it.

Just so the Buddha is born in the world,
and lives in the world,
but the world does not stick to him,
as water does not stick to the lotus.

A great blazing fire
dies down when the fuel runs out.
When the coals have gone out
it’s said to be ‘quenched’.

This simile is taught by the discerning
to express the meaning clearly.
Great giants will understand
what the giant taught the giant.

Free of greed, free of hate,
free of delusion, undefiled;
the giant, giving up his body,
being undefiled, will be fully quenched.”

AN 6.44 With Migasālā Migasālāsutta

Then Venerable Ānanda robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of the laywoman Migasālā, where he sat down on the seat spread out.

Then the laywoman Migasālā went up to Ānanda, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Honorable Ānanda, how on earth are we supposed to understand the teaching taught by the Buddha, when the chaste and the unchaste are both reborn in exactly the same place in the next life?

My father Purāṇa was chaste, set apart, refraining from the vulgar act of sex. When he passed away the Buddha declared that, since he was a once-returner, he was reborn in the host of joyful gods.

But my uncle Isidatta was not chaste; he lived content with his wife. When he passed away the Buddha declared that, since he too was a once-returner, he was reborn in the host of joyful gods.

How on earth are we supposed to understand the teaching taught by the Buddha, when the chaste and the unchaste are both reborn in exactly the same place in the next life?”

“You’re right, sister, but that’s how the Buddha declared it.”

Then Ānanda, after receiving almsfood at Migasālā’s home, rose from his seat and left. Then after the meal, on his return from almsround, Ānanda went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“Ānanda, who is this laywoman Migasālā, a foolish incompetent aunty, with an aunty’s wit? And who is it that knows how to assess individual persons? These six individuals are found in the world. What six?

Take a certain individual who is gentle and pleasant to be with. And spiritual companions enjoy living together with them. And they’ve not listened or learned or penetrated theoretically or found even temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a lower place, not a higher. They’re going to a lower place, not a higher.

Take another individual who is gentle and pleasant to be with. And spiritual companions enjoy living together with them. And they’ve listened and learned and penetrated theoretically and found temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a higher place, not a lower. They’re going to a higher place, not a lower.

Judgmental people compare them, saying: ‘This one has just the same qualities as the other, so why is one worse and one better?’ This will be for their lasting harm and suffering.

In this case, the individual who is gentle … and has listened, learned, penetrated theoretically, and found temporary freedom is better and finer than the other individual. Why is that? Because the stream of the teaching carries them along. But who knows the difference between them except a Realized One?

So, Ānanda, don’t be judgmental about individuals. Don’t pass judgment on individuals. Those who pass judgment on individuals harm themselves. I, or someone like me, may pass judgment on individuals.

Take another individual who is angry and conceited, and from time to time has greedy thoughts. And they’ve not listened or learned or penetrated theoretically or found even temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a lower place, not a higher. They’re going to a lower place, not a higher.

Take another individual who is angry and conceited, and from time to time has greedy thoughts. … Because the stream of the teaching carries them along. … When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a higher place, not a lower. They’re going to a higher place, not a lower.

Judgmental people compare them …

I, or someone like me, may pass judgment on people.

Take another individual who is angry and conceited, and from time to time has the impulse to speak inappropriately. And they’ve not listened or learned or penetrated theoretically or found even temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a lower place, not a higher. They’re going to a lower place, not a higher.

Take another individual who is angry and conceited, and from time to time has the impulse to speak inappropriately. But they’ve listened and learned and penetrated theoretically and found temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a higher place, not a lower. They’re going to a higher place, not a lower.

Judgmental people compare them, saying: ‘This one has just the same qualities as the other, so why is one worse and one better?’ This will be for their lasting harm and suffering.

In this case, the individual who is angry and conceited, but has listened, learned, penetrated theoretically, and found temporary freedom is better and finer than the other individual. Why is that? Because the stream of the teaching carries them along. But who knows the difference between them except a Realized One?

So, Ānanda, don’t be judgmental about individuals. Don’t pass judgment on individuals. Those who pass judgment on individuals harm themselves. I, or someone like me, may pass judgment on individuals.

Who is this laywoman Migasālā, a foolish incompetent aunty, with an aunty’s wit? And who is it that knows how to assess individual persons? These six individuals are found in the world.

If Isidatta had achieved Purāṇa’s level of ethical conduct, Purāṇa could not have even known Isidatta’s destination. And if Purāṇa had achieved Isidatta’s level of wisdom, Isidatta could not have even known Purāṇa’s destination. So both individuals were lacking in one respect.”

AN 6.45 Debt Iṇasutta

“Mendicants, isn’t poverty suffering in the world for a person who enjoys sensual pleasures?”

“Yes, sir.”

“When a poor, penniless person falls into debt, isn’t being in debt also suffering in the world for a person who enjoys sensual pleasures?”

“Yes, sir.”

“When a poor person who has fallen into debt agrees to pay interest, isn’t the interest also suffering in the world for a person who enjoys sensual pleasures?”

“Yes, sir.”

“When a poor person who has fallen into debt and agreed to pay interest fails to pay it when it falls due, they get a warning. Isn’t being warned suffering in the world for a person who enjoys sensual pleasures?”

“Yes, sir.”

“When a poor person fails to pay after getting a warning, they’re prosecuted. Isn’t being prosecuted suffering in the world for a person who enjoys sensual pleasures?”

“Yes, sir.”

“When a poor person fails to pay after being prosecuted, they’re imprisoned. Isn’t being imprisoned suffering in the world for a person who enjoys sensual pleasures?”

“Yes, sir.”

“So mendicants, poverty, debt, interest, warnings, prosecution, and imprisonment are suffering in the world for those who enjoy sensual pleasures. In the same way, whoever has no faith, conscience, prudence, energy, and wisdom when it comes to skillful qualities is called poor and penniless in the training of the Noble One.

Since they have no faith, conscience, prudence, energy, or wisdom when it comes to skillful qualities, they do bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. This is how they’re in debt, I say.

In order to conceal the bad things they do by way of body, speech, and mind they harbor corrupt wishes. They wish, plan, speak, and act with the thought: ‘May no one find me out!’ This is how they pay interest, I say.

Good-hearted spiritual companions say this about them: ‘This venerable acts like this, and behaves like that.’ This is how they’re warned, I say.

When they go to a wilderness, the root of a tree, or an empty hut, they’re beset by remorseful, unskillful thoughts. This is how they’re prosecuted, I say.

That poor, penniless person has done bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re trapped in the prison of hell or the animal realm. I don’t see a single prison that’s as grim, as vicious, and such an obstacle to reaching the supreme sanctuary from the yoke as the prison of hell or the animal realm.

Poverty is said to be suffering in the world,
and so is being in debt.
A poor person who has fallen into debt
frets even when spending the loan.

And then they’re prosecuted,
or even thrown in jail.
Such imprisonment is true suffering
for someone who prays for pleasure and possessions.

In the same way, in the Noble One’s training
whoever has no faith,
no conscience or prudence,
contemplates bad deeds.

After doing bad things
by way of body,
speech, and mind,
they wish, ‘May no one find me out!’

Their behavior is creepy
by body, speech, and mind.
They pile up bad deeds
on and on, life after life.

That simpleton evildoer,
knowing their own misdeeds,
is a poor person who has fallen into debt,
and frets even when spending the loan.

And when in village or wilderness
they’re prosecuted
by painful mental plans,
which are born of remorse.

That simpleton evildoer,
knowing their own misdeeds,
goes to one of the animal realms,
or is trapped in hell.

Such imprisonment is true suffering,
from which the attentive are released.
With confident heart, they give
with wealth that is properly earned.

That faithful householder of discernment
holds a winning hand on both counts:
welfare and benefit in this life,
and happiness in lives to come.
This is how, for a householder,
merit grows by generosity.

In the same way, in the Noble One’s training,
whoever is grounded in faith,
with conscience and prudence,
wise, and ethically restrained,

is said to live happily
in the Noble One’s training.
After gaining pleasure not of the flesh,
they concentrate on equanimity.

They give up the five hindrances,
constantly energetic,
and enter the absorptions,
unified, alert, and mindful.

Truly knowing in this way
regards the ending of all fetters,
by not grasping in any way,
their mind is rightly freed.

To that unaffected one, rightly freed
with the end of the fetters of continued existence,
the knowledge comes:
‘My freedom is unshakable.’

This is the ultimate knowledge.
This is the supreme happiness.
Sorrowless, stainless, secure:
this is the highest freedom from debt.”

AN 6.46 By Mahācunda Mahācundasutta

So I have heard. At one time Venerable Mahācunda was staying in the land of the Cetis at Sahajāti. There he addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Venerable Mahācunda said this:

“Take a case where mendicants who practice discernment of principles rebuke mendicants who practice absorption: ‘They say, “We practice absorption meditation! We practice absorption meditation!” And they meditate and concentrate and contemplate and ruminate. Why do they practice absorption meditation? In what way do they practice absorption meditation? How do they practice absorption meditation?’ In this case the mendicants who practice discernment of principles are not inspired, and the mendicants who practice absorption are not inspired. And they’re not acting for the welfare and happiness of the people, for the people, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.

Now, take a case where mendicants who practice absorption meditation rebuke mendicants who practice discernment of principles: ‘They say, “We practice discernment of principles! We practice discernment of principles!” But they’re haughty, insolent, fickle, scurrilous, loose-tongued, unmindful, lacking situational awareness and immersion, with straying minds and undisciplined faculties. Why do they practice discernment of principles? In what way do they practice discernment of principles? How do they practice discernment of principles?’ In this case the mendicants who practice absorption are not inspired, and the mendicants who practice discernment of principles are not inspired. And they’re not acting for the welfare and happiness of the people, for the people, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.

Now, take a case where mendicants who practice discernment of principles praise only others like them, not mendicants who practice absorption. In this case the mendicants who practice discernment of principles are not inspired, and the mendicants who practice absorption are not inspired. And they’re not acting for the welfare and happiness of the people, for the people, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.

And take a case where mendicants who practice absorption praise only others like them, not mendicants who practice discernment of principles. In this case the mendicants who practice absorption are not inspired, and the mendicants who practice discernment of principles are not inspired. And they’re not acting for the welfare and happiness of the people, for the people, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.

So you should train like this: ‘As mendicants who practice discernment of principles, we will praise mendicants who practice absorption.’ That’s how you should train. Why is that? Because it’s rare to find such incredible individuals in the world who have direct meditative experience of the element free of death.

So you should train like this: ‘As mendicants who practice absorption, we will praise mendicants who practice discernment of principles.’ That’s how you should train. Why is that? Because it’s incredibly rare to find individuals in the world who see the meaning of a deep saying with penetrating wisdom.”

AN 6.47 Apparent in the Present Life (1st) Paṭhamasandiṭṭhikasutta

And then the wanderer Moḷiyasīvaka went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Sir, they speak of ‘a teaching apparent in the present life’. In what way is the teaching apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves?”

“Well then, Sīvaka, I’ll ask you about this in return, and you can answer as you like. What do you think, Sīvaka? When there’s greed in you, do you understand ‘I have greed in me’? And when there’s no greed in you, do you understand ‘I have no greed in me’?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Since you know this, this is how the teaching is apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.

What do you think, Sīvaka? When there’s hate … delusion … greedy ideas … hateful ideas … When there are delusional ideas in you, do you understand ‘I have delusional ideas in me’? And when there are no delusional ideas in you, do you understand ‘I have no delusional ideas in me’?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Since you know this, this is how the teaching is apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.”

“Excellent, sir! Excellent! From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 6.48 Apparent in the Present Life (2nd) Dutiyasandiṭṭhikasutta

Then a certain brahmin went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, they speak of ‘a teaching apparent in the present life’. In what way is the teaching apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves?”

“Well then, brahmin, I’ll ask you about this in return, and you can answer as you like. What do you think, brahmin? When there’s greed in you, do you understand ‘I have greed in me’? And when there’s no greed in you, do you understand ‘I have no greed in me’?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Since you know this, this is how the teaching is apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.

What do you think, brahmin? When there’s hate … delusion … corruption that leads to physical deeds … corruption that leads to speech … When there’s corruption that leads to mental deeds in you, do you understand ‘I have corruption that leads to mental deeds in me’? And when there’s no corruption that leads to mental deeds in you, do you understand ‘I have no corruption that leads to mental deeds in me’?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Since you know this, this is how the teaching is apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.”

“Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 6.49 With Khema Khemasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Now at that time Venerable Khema and Venerable Sumana were staying near Sāvatthī in the Dark Forest. Then they went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. Venerable Khema said to the Buddha:

“Sir, a mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—does not think: ‘There is someone better than me, or equal to me, or worse than me.’”

That is what Khema said, and the Teacher concurred. Then Khema, knowing that the Teacher concurred, got up from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

And then, not long after Khema had left, Sumana said to the Buddha:

“Sir, a mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—does not think: ‘There is no one better than me, or equal to me, or worse than me.’”

That is what Sumana said, and the Teacher concurred. Then Sumana, knowing that the Teacher concurred, got up from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

Then, not long after Khema and Sumana had left, the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, this is how gentlemen declare enlightenment. The goal is spoken of, but the self is not involved. But it seems that there are some futile men here who declare enlightenment as a joke. Later they will fall into distress.

They don’t represent themselves
as being among superiors, inferiors, or equals.
Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed.
They live freed from fetters.”

AN 6.50 Sense Restraint Indriyasaṁvarasutta

“Mendicants, when there is no sense restraint, one who lacks sense restraint has destroyed a vital condition for ethical conduct. When there is no ethical conduct, one who lacks ethics has destroyed a vital condition for right immersion. When there is no right immersion, one who lacks right immersion has destroyed a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is no true knowledge and vision, one who lacks true knowledge and vision has destroyed a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is no disillusionment and dispassion, one who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that lacked branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would not grow to fullness.

In the same way, when there is no sense restraint, one who lacks sense restraint has destroyed a vital condition for ethical conduct. … One who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

When there is sense restraint, one who has fulfilled sense restraint has fulfilled a vital condition for ethical conduct. When there is ethical conduct, one who has fulfilled ethical conduct has fulfilled a vital condition for right immersion. When there is right immersion, one who has fulfilled right immersion has fulfilled a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is true knowledge and vision, one who has fulfilled true knowledge and vision has fulfilled a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is disillusionment and dispassion, one who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that was complete with branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would all grow to fullness.

In the same way, when there is sense restraint, one who has fulfilled sense restraint has fulfilled a vital condition for ethical conduct. … One who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.”

AN 6.51 With Ānanda Ānandasutta

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to Venerable Sāriputta, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, Ānanda sat down to one side, and said to Sāriputta:

“Reverend Sāriputta, how does a mendicant get to hear a teaching they haven’t heard before? How do they remember those teachings they have heard? How do they keep exercising the teachings with which they are already familiar? And how do they come to understand what they haven’t understood before?”

“Well, Venerable Ānanda, you’re very learned. Why don’t you clarify this yourself?”

“Well then, Reverend Sāriputta, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, reverend,” Sāriputta replied. Ānanda said this:

“Reverend Sāriputta, take a mendicant who memorizes the teaching—statements, mixed prose & verse, discussions, verses, inspired exclamations, legends, stories of past lives, amazing stories, and elaborations.

Then, just as they learned and memorized it, they teach others in detail, make them recite in detail, they rehearse it themselves in detail, and they think about and consider the teaching in their heart, examining it with the mind.

They enter the rains retreat in a monastery with senior mendicants who are very learned, inheritors of the heritage, who have memorized the teachings, the monastic law, and the outlines. From time to time they go up to those mendicants and ask them questions: ‘Why, sir, does it say this? What does that mean?’ Those venerables reveal what is hidden, clarify what is unclear, and dispel doubt regarding the many doubtful matters.

This is how a mendicant gets to hear a teaching they haven’t heard before. It’s how they remember those teachings they have heard. It’s how they keep exercising the teachings with which they are already familiar. And it’s how they come to understand what they haven’t understood before.”

“It’s incredible, reverend, it’s amazing! How well said this was by Venerable Ānanda! And we will remember Venerable Ānanda as someone who possesses these six qualities.

For Ānanda memorizes the teaching … statements, mixed prose & verse, discussions, verses, inspired exclamations, legends, stories of past lives, amazing stories, and elaborations. Those venerables reveal to Ānanda what is hidden, clarify what is unclear, and dispel doubt regarding the many doubtful matters.”

AN 6.52 Aristocrats Khattiyasutta

And then the brahmin Jānussoṇi went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Aristocrats, worthy Gotama, have what as their ambition? What is their preoccupation? What are they fixated on? What do they insist on? What is their ultimate goal?”

“Aristocrats, brahmin, have wealth as their ambition. They’re preoccupied with wisdom. They’re fixated on power. They insist on territory. Their ultimate goal is authority.”

“Brahmins, worthy Gotama, have what as their ambition? What is their preoccupation? What are they fixated on? What do they insist on? What is their ultimate goal?”

“Brahmins have wealth as their ambition. They’re preoccupied with wisdom. They’re fixated on the hymns. They insist on sacrifice. Their ultimate goal is the realm of divinity.”

“Householders, worthy Gotama, have what as their ambition? What is their preoccupation? What are they fixated on? What do they insist on? What is their ultimate goal?”

“Householders have wealth as their ambition. They’re preoccupied with wisdom. They’re fixated on their profession. They insist on work. Their ultimate goal is to complete their work.”

“Women, worthy Gotama, have what as their ambition? What is their preoccupation? What are they fixated on? What do they insist on? What is their ultimate goal?”

“Women have a man as their ambition. They’re preoccupied with adornments. They’re fixated on their children. They insist on being without a co-wife. Their ultimate goal is authority.”

“Bandits, worthy Gotama, have what as their ambition? What is their preoccupation? What are they fixated on? What do they insist on? What is their ultimate goal?”

“Bandits have theft as their ambition. They’re preoccupied with a hiding place. They’re fixated on their sword. They insist on darkness. Their ultimate goal is invisibility.”

“Ascetics, worthy Gotama, have what as their ambition? What is their preoccupation? What are they fixated on? What do they insist on? What is their ultimate goal?”

“Ascetics have patience and gentleness as their ambition. They’re preoccupied with wisdom. They’re fixated on ethical conduct. They insist on owning nothing. Their culmination is extinguishment.”

“It’s incredible, worthy Gotama, it’s amazing! The worthy Gotama knows the ambition, preoccupation, fixation, insistence, and ultimate goal of aristocrats, brahmins, householders, women, bandits, and ascetics. Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 6.53 Diligence Appamādasutta

Then a certain brahmin went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, is there one thing that, when developed and cultivated, secures benefits for both this life and lives to come?”

“There is, brahmin.”

“So what is it?”

“Diligence, brahmin, is one thing that, when developed and cultivated, secures benefits for both this life and lives to come.

The footprints of all creatures that walk can fit inside an elephant’s footprint. So an elephant’s footprint is said to be the biggest of them all. In the same way, diligence is one thing that, when developed and cultivated, secures benefits for both this life and lives to come.

The rafters of a bungalow all lean to the peak, slope to the peak, and meet at the peak, so the peak is said to be the topmost of them all. In the same way, diligence is one thing …

A reed-cutter, having cut the reeds, grabs them at the top and shakes them down, shakes them about, and shakes them off. In the same way, diligence is one thing …

When the stalk of a bunch of mangoes is cut, all the mangoes attached to the stalk will follow along. In the same way, diligence is one thing …

All lesser rulers are vassals of a wheel-turning monarch, so the wheel-turning monarch is said to be the foremost of them all. In the same way, diligence is one thing …

The radiance of all the stars is not worth a sixteenth part of the moon’s radiance, so the moon’s radiance is said to be the best of them all. In the same way, diligence is one thing that, when developed and cultivated, secures benefits for both this life and lives to come.

This is the one thing that, when developed and cultivated, secures benefits for both this life and lives to come.”

“Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 6.54 About Dhammika Dhammikasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain.

Now at that time Venerable Dhammika was a resident in all seven monasteries of his native land. There he abused visiting mendicants; he insulted, harmed, attacked, and harassed them. The visiting mendicants who were treated in this way did not stay. They left, abandoning the monastery.

Then the local lay followers thought to themselves, “We have supplied the mendicant Saṅgha with robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. But the visiting mendicants don’t stay. They leave, abandoning the monastery. What is the cause, what is the reason for this?”

Then the local lay followers thought to themselves, “This Venerable Dhammika abuses visiting mendicants; he insults, harms, attacks, and harasses them. The visiting mendicants who were treated in this way do not stay. They leave, abandoning the monastery. Why don’t we banish Venerable Dhammika?”

Then the local lay followers went up to Venerable Dhammika and said to him, “Sir, please leave this monastery. You’ve stayed here long enough.”

Then Venerable Dhammika left and went to another monastery. There he abused visiting mendicants; he insulted, harmed, attacked, and harassed them. The visiting mendicants who were treated in this way did not stay. They left, abandoning the monastery.

Then the local lay followers thought to themselves: …

They said to Venerable Dhammika, “Sir, please leave this monastery. You’ve stayed here long enough.”

Then Venerable Dhammika left and went to another monastery. There he abused visiting mendicants; he insulted, harmed, attacked, and harassed them. The visiting mendicants who were treated in this way did not stay. They left, abandoning the monastery.

Then the local lay followers thought to themselves, “Why don’t we banish Venerable Dhammika from all seven monasteries in our native land?”

Then the local lay followers went up to Venerable Dhammika and said to him, “Sir, please leave all seven monasteries in our native land.”

Then Venerable Dhammika thought, “I’ve been banished by the local lay followers from all seven monasteries in my native land. Where am I to go now?” He thought, “Why don’t I go to see the Buddha?”

Then Venerable Dhammika took his bowl and robe and set out for Rājagaha. Eventually he came to Rājagaha and the Vulture’s Peak. He went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him, “So, Brahmin Dhammika, where have you come from?”

“Sir, I’ve been banished by the local lay followers from all seven monasteries in my native land.”

“Enough, Brahmin Dhammika, what’s that to you? Now that you’ve been banished from all of those places, you have come to me.

Once upon a time, some sea-merchants set sail for the ocean deeps, taking with them a land-spotting bird. When their ship was out of sight of land, they released the bird. It flew right away to the east, the west, the north, the south, upwards, and in-between. If it saw land on any side, it went there and stayed. But if it saw no land on any side it returned to the ship. In the same way, now that you’ve been banished from all of those places, you have come to me.

Once upon a time, King Koravya had a royal banyan tree with five trunks called ‘Well Planted’. It was shady and lovely. Its canopy spread over twelve leagues, while the network of roots spread for five leagues. Its fruits were as large as a rice pot. And they were as sweet as pure wild honey. The king and harem made use of one trunk, the troops another, the people of town and country another, ascetics and brahmins another, and beasts and birds another. No one guarded the fruit, yet no one damaged another’s fruits.

Then a certain person ate as much as he liked of the fruit, then broke off a branch and left. Then the deity haunting the royal banyan tree thought, ‘Oh lord, how incredible, how amazing! How wicked this person is, to eat as much as they like, then break off a branch and leave! Why don’t I make sure that the royal banyan tree gives no fruit in future?’ Then the royal banyan tree gave no more fruit.

Then King Koravya went up to Sakka, lord of gods, and said to him, ‘Please good fellow, you should know that the royal banyan tree called Well Planted gives no fruit.’ Then Sakka used his psychic powers to will that a violent storm come. And it felled and uprooted the royal banyan tree. Then the deity haunting the tree stood to one side, miserable and sad, weeping, with a tearful face.

Then Sakka went up to that deity, and said, ‘Why, god, are you standing to one side, miserable and sad, weeping, with a tearful face?’

‘Because, my good fellow, a violent storm came and felled and uprooted my home.’

‘Well, did you stand by your tree’s duty when the storm came?’

‘But my good fellow, how does a tree stand by its duty?’

‘It’s when those who need the tree’s roots, bark, leaves, flowers, or fruit take what they need. Yet the deity is not displeased or upset because of this. This is how a tree stands by its duty.’

‘I was not standing by a tree’s duty when the storm came and felled and uprooted my home.’

‘God, if you were to stand by a tree’s duty, your home may be as it was before.’

‘I will stand by a tree’s duty! May my home be as it was before!’

Then Sakka used his psychic power to will that a violent storm come. And it raised up that mighty banyan tree and the bark of the roots was healed.

In the same way, Brahmin Dhammika, were you standing by an ascetic’s duty when the local lay followers banished you from all seven of the monasteries in your native land?”

“But sir, how do I stand by an ascetic’s duty?”

“When someone abuses, annoys, or argues with an ascetic, the ascetic doesn’t abuse, annoy, or argue back at them. That’s how an ascetic stands by an ascetic’s duty.”

“I was not standing by an ascetic’s duty when the local lay followers banished me from all seven of the monasteries in my native land.”

“Once upon a time, there was a teacher named Sunetta. He was a religious founder and was free of desire for sensual pleasures. He had many hundreds of disciples. He taught them a Dhamma for rebirth in the company of Divinity. Those lacking confidence in Sunetta were—when their body broke up, after death—reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. Those full of confidence in Sunetta were—when their body broke up, after death—reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

Once upon a time, there was a teacher named Mūgapakkha … Aranemi … Kuddālaka … Hatthipāla … Jotipāla. He was a religious founder and was free of desire for sensual pleasures. He had many hundreds of disciples. He taught them a Dhamma for rebirth in the company of Divinity. Those lacking confidence in Jotipāla were—when their body broke up, after death—reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. Those full of confidence in Jotipāla were—when their body broke up, after death—reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

What do you think, Brahmin Dhammika? If someone with malicious intent were to abuse and insult these six teachers with their hundreds of followers, would they not brim with much wickedness?”

“Yes, sir.”

“They would indeed. But someone who abuses and insults a single individual accomplished in view with malicious intent brims even more with wickedness. Why is that? Brahmin Dhammika, I say that any injury done by those outside of the Buddhist community does not compare with what is done to one’s own spiritual companions. So you should train like this: ‘We will have no malicious intent for those who we want to have as our spiritual companions.’ That is how you should train.

Sunetta and Mūgapakkha,
and Aranemi the brahmin,
Hatthipāla the student,
and Kuddālaka were Teachers.

And Jotipāla Govinda
was priest for seven kings.
These six famous teachers,
harmless ones of the past,

were free of putrefaction, compassionate,
gone beyond the fetter of sensuality.
Detached from sensual desire,
they were reborn in the realm of divinity.

Many hundreds of
their disciples were also
free of putrefaction-stench, compassionate,
gone beyond the fetter of sensuality.
Detached from sensual desire,
they were reborn in the realm of divinity.

One who insults
with malicious intent
these non-Buddhist seers,
free of desire, immersed in samādhi;
such a man
brims with much wickedness.

But one who insults
with malicious intent
a single individual accomplished in view,
a mendicant disciple of the Buddha;
that man
brims even more with wickedness.

You shouldn’t attack a holy person,
who has given up the grounds for views.
This individual is called
the seventh of the noble Saṅgha.

They’re not free of desire for sensual pleasures,
and their faculties are still immature:
faith, mindfulness, and energy,
serenity and discernment.

If you attack such a mendicant,
you first hurt yourself.
Having hurt yourself,
you harm the other.

But if you protect yourself,
the other is also protected.
So you should protect yourself.
An astute person is always uninjured.”

The Second Fifty

The Great Chapter

AN 6.55 With Soṇa Soṇasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain.

Now at that time Venerable Soṇa was staying near Rājagaha in the Cool Grove. Then as he was in private retreat this thought came to his mind, “I am one of the Buddha’s most energetic disciples. Yet my mind is not freed from defilements by not grasping. But my family has wealth. I could enjoy that wealth and make merit. Why don’t I resign the training and return to a lesser life, so I can enjoy my wealth and make merit?”

Then the Buddha knew Venerable Soṇa’s train of thought. As easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, he vanished from the Vulture’s Peak and reappeared in the Cool Grove in front of Soṇa, and sat down on the seat spread out. Soṇa bowed to the Buddha and sat down to one side.

The Buddha said to him, “Soṇa, as you were in private retreat didn’t this thought come to your mind: ‘I am one of the Buddha’s most energetic disciples. Yet my mind is not freed from defilements by not grasping. But my family has wealth. I could enjoy that wealth and make merit. Why don’t I resign the training and return to a lesser life, so I can enjoy my wealth and make merit?’”

“Yes, sir.”

“What do you think, Soṇa? When you were still a layman, weren’t you a good player of the arched harp?”

“Yes, sir.”

“When your harp’s strings were tuned too tight, was it resonant and playable?”

“No, sir.”

“When your harp’s strings were tuned too slack, was it resonant and playable?”

“No, sir.”

“But when your harp’s strings were tuned neither too tight nor too slack, but fixed at an even tension, was it resonant and playable?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, Soṇa, when energy is too forceful it leads to restlessness. When energy is too slack it leads to laziness. So, Soṇa, you should focus on energy and serenity, find a balance of the faculties, and learn the character of this situation.”

“Yes, sir,” Soṇa replied.

After advising Soṇa like this, the Buddha, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, vanished from the Cool Grove and reappeared on the Vulture’s Peak.

After some time Soṇa focused on energy and serenity, found a balance of the faculties, and learned the pattern of this situation. Then Soṇa, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And Venerable Soṇa became one of the perfected.

Then, when Soṇa had attained perfection, he thought, “Why don’t I go to the Buddha and declare my enlightenment in his presence?” Then Soṇa went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, a mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—is dedicated to six things. They are dedicated to renunciation, seclusion, kindness, the ending of craving, the ending of grasping, and mental clarity.

It may be, sir, that one of the venerables here thinks: ‘Maybe this venerable is dedicated to renunciation solely out of mere faith.’ But it should not be seen like this. A mendicant with defilements ended does not see in themselves anything more to do, or anything that needs improvement. They’re dedicated to renunciation because they’re free of greed, hate, and delusion with the end of greed, hate, and delusion.

It may be, sir, that one of the venerables here thinks: ‘Maybe this venerable is dedicated to seclusion because they enjoy possessions, honor, and popularity.’ But it should not be seen like this. …

It may be, sir, that one of the venerables here thinks: ‘Maybe this venerable is dedicated to kindness because they believe that adhering to precepts and observances is essential.’ But it should not be seen like this. …

They’re dedicated to the ending of craving because they’re free of greed, hate, and delusion with the end of greed, hate, and delusion.

They’re dedicated to the ending of grasping because they’re free of greed, hate, and delusion with the end of greed, hate, and delusion.

They’re dedicated to clarity of mind because they’re free of greed, hate, and delusion with the end of greed, hate, and delusion.

When a mendicant’s mind is rightly freed like this, even if compelling sights come into the range of vision they don’t overcome their mind. Their mind is quite untainted. It is steady, imperturbable, observing disappearance. Even if compelling sounds … smells … tastes … touches … and ideas come into the range of the mind they don’t overcome the mind. Their mind is quite untainted. It is steady, imperturbable, observing disappearance.

Suppose there was a mountain that was one solid mass of rock, without cracks or holes. Even if violent storms were to blow up out of the east, the west, the north, and the south, they couldn’t make it shake or rock or tremble.

In the same way, when a mendicant’s mind is rightly freed like this, even if compelling sights come into the range of vision they don’t overcome their mind. … Their mind is quite untainted. It is steady, imperturbable, observing disappearance.

When you’re dedicated to renunciation
and seclusion of the heart;
when you’re dedicated to kindness
and the end of grasping;

when you’re dedicated to the ending of craving
and clarity of heart;
and you’ve seen the arising of the senses,
your mind is rightly freed.

For that one, rightly freed,
a mendicant with peaceful mind,
there’s nothing to be improved,
and nothing more to do.

As the wind cannot stir
a solid mass of rock,
so too sights, tastes, sounds,
smells, and touches—the lot—

and ideas, whether liked or disliked,
don’t disturb the unaffected one.
Their mind is steady and free
as they observe fall.”

AN 6.56 With Phagguna Phaggunasutta

Now at that time Venerable Phagguna was sick, suffering, gravely ill. Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, Venerable Phagguna is sick. Sir, please go to Venerable Phagguna out of sympathy.” The Buddha consented with silence.

Then in the late afternoon, the Buddha came out of retreat and went to Venerable Phagguna. Venerable Phagguna saw the Buddha coming off in the distance and stirred in his cot.

The Buddha said to him, “It’s all right, Phagguna, don’t get up. There are some seats spread out by others, I will sit there.”

He sat down on the seat spread out and said to Venerable Phagguna: “I hope you’re keeping well, Phagguna; I hope you’re all right. I hope your pain is fading, not growing; that its fading is evident, not its growing.”

“Sir, I’m not keeping well, I’m not getting by. My pain is terrible and growing, not fading; its growing is evident, not its fading.

The winds piercing my head are so severe, it feels like a strong man drilling into my head with a sharp point. I’m not keeping well.

The pain in my head is so severe, it feels like a strong man tightening a strong leather strap around my head. I’m not keeping well.

The winds slicing my belly are so severe, like a deft butcher or their apprentice were slicing open a cow’s belly with a sharp meat cleaver. I’m not keeping well.

The burning in my body is so severe, it feels like two strong men grabbing a weaker man by the arms to burn and scorch him on a pit of glowing coals. I’m not keeping well, I’m not getting by. My pain is terrible and growing, not fading; its growing is evident, not its fading.”

Then the Buddha educated, encouraged, fired up, and inspired Venerable Phagguna with a Dhamma talk, after which he rose from his seat and left.

Not long after the Buddha left, Venerable Phagguna passed away. At the time of his death, his faculties were bright and clear. Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, soon after the Buddha left, Venerable Phagguna died. At the time of his death, his faculties were bright and clear.”

“And why shouldn’t his faculties be bright and clear? The mendicant Phagguna’s mind was not freed from the five lower fetters. But when he heard that teaching his mind was freed from them.

Ānanda, there are these six benefits to hearing the teaching at the right time and examining the meaning at the right time. What six?

Firstly, take the case of a mendicant whose mind is not freed from the five lower fetters. At the time of death they get to see the Realized One. The Realized One teaches Dhamma to them that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And he reveals a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. When they hear that teaching their mind is freed from the five lower fetters. This is the first benefit of listening to the teaching.

Next, take the case of another mendicant whose mind is not freed from the five lower fetters. At the time of death they don’t get to see the Realized One, but they get to see a Realized One’s disciple. The Realized One’s disciple teaches them Dhamma … When they hear that teaching their mind is freed from the five lower fetters. This is the second benefit of listening to the teaching.

Next, take the case of another mendicant whose mind is not freed from the five lower fetters. At the time of death they don’t get to see the Realized One, or to see a Realized One’s disciple. But they think about and consider the teaching in their heart, examining it with the mind as they learned and memorized it. As they do so their mind is freed from the five lower fetters. This is the third benefit of listening to the teaching.

Next, take the case of a mendicant whose mind is freed from the five lower fetters, but not with the supreme ending of attachments. At the time of death they get to see the Realized One. The Realized One teaches them Dhamma … When they hear that teaching their mind is freed with the supreme ending of attachments. This is the fourth benefit of listening to the teaching.

Next, take the case of another mendicant whose mind is freed from the five lower fetters, but not with the supreme ending of attachments. At the time of death they don’t get to see the Realized One, but they get to see a Realized One’s disciple. The Realized One’s disciple teaches them Dhamma … When they hear that teaching their mind is freed with the supreme ending of attachments. This is the fifth benefit of listening to the teaching.

Next, take the case of another mendicant whose mind is freed from the five lower fetters, but not with the supreme ending of attachments. At the time of death they don’t get to see the Realized One, or to see a Realized One’s disciple. But they think about and consider the teaching in their heart, examining it with the mind as they learned and memorized it. As they do so their mind is freed with the supreme ending of attachments. This is the sixth benefit of listening to the teaching.

These are the six benefits to hearing the teaching at the right time and examining the meaning at the right time.”

AN 6.57 The Six Classes of Rebirth Chaḷabhijātisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain. Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, Pūraṇa Kassapa describes six classes of rebirth: black, blue, red, yellow, white, and ultimate white.

The black class of rebirth consists of slaughterers of sheep, pigs, poultry, or deer, hunters or fishers, bandits, executioners, butchers of cattle, jailers, and any others with a cruel livelihood.

The blue class of rebirth consists of mendicants whose life is thorny, and any others who teach the efficacy of deeds and action.

The red class of rebirth consists of the Jain ascetics who wear one cloth.

The yellow class of rebirth consists of the lay people dressed in white who are disciples of the naked ascetics.

The white class of rebirth consists of male and female Ājīvaka ascetics.

And the ultimate white class of rebirth consists of Nanda Vaccha, Kisa Saṅkicca, and the bamboo-staffed ascetic Gosāla.

These are the six classes of rebirth that Pūraṇa Kassapa describes.”

“But Ānanda, did the whole world authorize Pūraṇa Kassapa to describe these six classes of rebirth?”

“No, sir.”

“It’s as if they were to force a chop on a poor, penniless person, telling them, ‘Eat this meat and pay for it!’ In the same way, Pūraṇa Kassapa has described these six classes of rebirth without the consent of those ascetics and brahmins. And he has done so in a foolish, incompetent, unskilled way, lacking common sense.

I, however, also describe six classes of rebirth. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Ānanda replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what, Ānanda, are the six classes of rebirth? Someone born into a dark class gives rise to a dark result. Someone born into a dark class gives rise to a bright result. Someone born into a dark class gives rise to extinguishment, which is neither dark nor bright. Someone born into a bright class gives rise to a dark result. Someone born into a bright class gives rise to a bright result. Someone born into a bright class gives rise to extinguishment, which is neither dark nor bright.

And how does someone born into a dark class give rise to a dark result? It’s when someone is reborn in a low family—a family of corpse-workers, hunters, bamboo-workers, chariot-makers, or scavengers—poor, with little to eat or drink, where life is tough, and food and shelter are hard to find. And they’re ugly, unsightly, deformed, sickly—one-eyed, crippled, lame, or half-paralyzed. They don’t get to have food, drink, clothes, and vehicles; garlands, fragrance, and makeup; or bed, house, and lighting. And they do bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. That’s how someone born into a dark class gives rise to a dark result.

And how does someone born into a dark class give rise to a bright result? It’s when some person is reborn in a low family … But they do good things by way of body, speech, and mind. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. That’s how someone born into a dark class gives rise to a bright result.

And how does someone born into a dark class give rise to extinguishment, which is neither dark nor bright? It’s when some person is reborn in a low family … They shave off their hair and beard, dress in ocher robes, and go forth from the lay life to homelessness. They give up the five hindrances, corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom. They firmly establish their mind in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. They truly develop the seven awakening factors. And then they give rise to extinguishment, which is neither dark nor bright. That’s how someone born in a dark class gives rise to extinguishment, which is neither dark nor bright.

And how does someone born into a bright class give rise to a dark result? It’s when someone is reborn in an eminent family—a well-to-do family of aristocrats, brahmins, or householders—rich, affluent, and wealthy, with lots of gold and silver, lots of property and assets, and lots of money and grain. And they’re attractive, good-looking, lovely, of surpassing beauty. They get to have food, drink, clothes, and vehicles; garlands, fragrance, and makeup; and bed, house, and lighting. But they do bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. That’s how someone born into a bright class gives rise to a dark result.

And how does someone born into a bright class give rise to a bright result? It’s when some person is reborn in an eminent family … And they do good things by way of body, speech, and mind. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm. That’s how someone born into a bright class give rise to a bright result.

And how does someone born into a bright class give rise to extinguishment, which is neither dark nor bright? It’s when some person is reborn in an eminent family … They shave off their hair and beard, dress in ocher robes, and go forth from the lay life to homelessness. They give up the five hindrances, corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom. They firmly establish their mind in the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. They truly develop the seven awakening factors. And then they give rise to extinguishment, which is neither dark nor bright. That’s how someone born into a bright class gives rise to extinguishment, which is neither dark nor bright.

These are the six classes of rebirth.”

AN 6.58 Defilements Āsavasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What six?

It’s a mendicant who, by restraint, has given up the defilements that should be given up by restraint. By using, they’ve given up the defilements that should be given up by using. By enduring, they’ve given up the defilements that should be given up by enduring. By avoiding, they’ve given up the defilements that should be given up by avoiding. By dispelling, they’ve given up the defilements that should be given up by dispelling. By developing, they’ve given up the defilements that should be given up by developing.

And what are the defilements that should be given up by restraint? Take a mendicant who, reflecting rationally, lives restraining the eye faculty. For the distressing and feverish defilements that might arise in someone who lives without restraint of the eye faculty do not arise when there is such restraint. Reflecting rationally, they live restraining the ear faculty … the nose faculty … the tongue faculty … the body faculty … the mind faculty. For the distressing and feverish defilements that might arise in someone who lives without restraint of the mind faculty do not arise when there is such restraint. These are called the defilements that should be given up by restraint.

And what are the defilements that should be given up by using? Take a mendicant who, reflecting rationally, makes use of robes: ‘Only for the sake of warding off cold and heat; for warding off the touch of flies, mosquitoes, wind, sun, and reptiles; and for covering up the private parts.’ Reflecting rationally, they make use of almsfood: ‘Not for fun, indulgence, adornment, or decoration, but only to sustain this body, to avoid harm, and to support spiritual practice. In this way, I shall put an end to old discomfort and not give rise to new discomfort, and I will have the means to keep going, blamelessness, and a comfortable abiding.’ Reflecting rationally, they make use of lodgings: ‘Only for the sake of warding off cold and heat; for warding off the touch of flies, mosquitoes, wind, sun, and reptiles; to shelter from harsh weather and to enjoy retreat.’ Reflecting rationally, they make use of medicines and supplies for the sick: ‘Only for the sake of warding off the pains of illness and to promote good health.’ For the distressing and feverish defilements that might arise in someone who lives without using these things do not arise when they are used. These are called the defilements that should be given up by using.

And what are the defilements that should be given up by enduring? Take a mendicant who, reflecting rationally, endures cold, heat, hunger, and thirst. They endure the touch of flies, mosquitoes, wind, sun, and reptiles. They endure rude and unwelcome criticism. And they put up with physical pain—sharp, severe, acute, unpleasant, disagreeable, and life-threatening. For the distressing and feverish defilements that might arise in someone who lives without enduring these things do not arise when they are endured. These are called the defilements that should be given up by enduring.

And what are the defilements that should be given up by avoiding? Take a mendicant who, reflecting rationally, avoids a wild elephant, a wild horse, a wild ox, a wild dog, a snake, a stump, thorny ground, a pit, a cliff, a swamp, and a sewer. Reflecting rationally, they avoid sitting on inappropriate seats, walking in inappropriate neighborhoods, and mixing with bad friends—whatever sensible spiritual companions would believe to be a bad setting. For the distressing and feverish defilements that might arise in someone who lives without avoiding these things do not arise when they are avoided. These are called the defilements that should be given up by avoiding.

And what are the defilements that should be given up by dispelling? Take a mendicant who, reflecting rationally, doesn’t tolerate a sensual, malicious, or cruel thought that has arisen, but gives it up, dispels it, eliminates it, and obliterates it. They don’t tolerate any bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen, but give them up, dispel them, eliminate them, and obliterate them. For the distressing and feverish defilements that might arise in someone who lives without dispelling these things do not arise when they are dispelled. These are called the defilements that should be given up by dispelling.

And what are the defilements that should be given up by developing? Take a mendicant who, reflecting rationally, develops the awakening factors of mindfulness, investigation of principles, energy, rapture, tranquility, immersion, and equanimity, which rely on seclusion, fading away, and cessation, and ripen as letting go. For the distressing and feverish defilements that might arise in someone who lives without developing these things do not arise when they are developed. These are called the defilements that should be given up by developing.

A mendicant with these six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 6.59 With Dārukammika Dārukammikasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying at Ñātika in the brick house.

Then the householder Dārukammika went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him, “Householder, I wonder whether your family gives gifts?”

“It does, sir. Gifts are given to those mendicants who are perfected or on the path to perfection; they live in the wilderness, eat only almsfood, and wear rag robes.”

“Householder, as a layman enjoying sensual pleasures, living at home with your children, using sandalwood imported from Kāsi, wearing garlands, fragrance, and makeup, and accepting gold and currency, it’s hard for you to know who is perfected or on the path to perfection.

If a mendicant living in the wilderness is haughty, insolent, fickle, scurrilous, loose-tongued, unmindful, lacking situational awareness and immersion, with straying mind and undisciplined faculties, then in this respect they’re reprehensible. If a mendicant living in the wilderness is not haughty, insolent, fickle, scurrilous, or loose-tongued, but has established mindfulness, situational awareness and immersion, with unified mind and restrained faculties, then in this respect they’re praiseworthy.

If a mendicant who lives within a village is restless … then in this respect they’re reprehensible. If a mendicant who lives within a village is not restless … then in this respect they’re praiseworthy.

If a mendicant who eats only almsfood is restless … then in this respect they’re reprehensible. If a mendicant who eats only almsfood is not restless … then in this respect they’re praiseworthy.

If a mendicant who accepts invitations is restless … then in this respect they’re reprehensible. If a mendicant who accepts invitations is not restless … then in this respect they’re praiseworthy.

If a mendicant who wears rag robes is restless … then in this respect they’re reprehensible. If a mendicant who wears rag robes is not restless … then in this respect they’re praiseworthy.

If a mendicant who wears robes offered by householders is haughty, insolent, fickle, scurrilous, loose-tongued, unmindful, lacking situational awareness and immersion, with straying mind and undisciplined faculties, then in this respect they’re reprehensible. If a mendicant who wears robes offered by householders is not haughty, insolent, fickle, scurrilous, or loose-tongued, but has established mindfulness, situational awareness and immersion, with unified mind and restrained faculties, then in this respect they’re praiseworthy.

Go ahead, householder, give gifts to the Saṅgha. Your mind will become bright and clear, and when your body breaks up, after death, you’ll be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

“Sir, from this day forth I will give gifts to the Saṅgha.”

AN 6.60 With Hatthisāriputta Hatthisāriputtasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana.

Now at that time several senior mendicants, after the meal, on their return from almsround, sat together in the pavilion talking about the teachings. Venerable Citta Hatthisāriputta interrupted them while they were talking.

Then Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita said to Venerable Citta Hatthisāriputta, “Venerable, please don’t interrupt the senior mendicants while they’re talking about the teachings. Wait until the end of the discussion.”

When he said this, Citta Hatthisāriputta’s companions said to Mahākoṭṭhita, “Venerable, please don’t rebuke Citta Hatthisāriputta. He is astute, and quite capable of talking about the teachings with the senior mendicants.”

“It’s not easy to know this, reverends, for those who don’t encompass another’s mind.

Take an individual who is the gentlest of the gentle, the most placid of the placid, the calmest of the calm, so long as they live relying on the Teacher or a spiritual companion in a teacher’s role. But when they’re separated from the Teacher or a spiritual companion in a teacher’s role, they mix closely with monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen; with rulers and their chief ministers, and with monastics of other religions and their disciples. As they mix closely, they become familiar and loose, spending time chatting, and so lust infects their mind. They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

Suppose an ox fond of crops was tied up or shut in a pen. Would it be right to say that that ox will never again invade the crops?”

“No it would not, reverend. For it’s quite possible that that ox will snap the ropes or break out of the pen, and then invade the crops.”

“In the same way, take an individual who is the gentlest of the gentle … As they mix closely, they become familiar and loose, spending time chatting, and so lust infects their mind. They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

And take an individual who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. Thinking, ‘I get the first absorption!’ they mix closely with monks … They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

Suppose the heavens were raining heavily at the crossroads so that the dust vanished and mud appeared. Would it be right to say that now dust will never appear at this crossroad again?”

“No it would not, reverend. For it is quite possible that people or cattle and so on will cross over the crossroad, or that the wind and sun will evaporate the moisture so that the dust appears again.”

“In the same way, take an individual who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. Thinking, ‘I get the first absorption!’ they mix closely with monks … They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

And take an individual who, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled … enters and remains in the second absorption. Thinking, ‘I get the second absorption!’ they mix closely with monks … They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

Suppose there was a large pond not far from a town or village. After the heavens have rained heavily there, the clams and mussels, and pebbles and gravel would vanish. Would it be right to say that now the clams and mussels, and pebbles and gravel will never appear here again?”

“No it would not, reverend. For it’s quite possible that people or cattle and so on will drink from the pond, or that the wind and sun will evaporate it so that the clams and mussels, and pebbles and gravel appear again.”

“In the same way, take an individual who, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled … enters and remains in the second absorption. Thinking, ‘I get the second absorption!’ they mix closely with monks … They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

And take an individual who, with the fading away of rapture … enters and remains in the third absorption. Thinking, ‘I get the third absorption!’ they mix closely with monks … They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

Suppose a person had finished a delicious meal. They’d have no appetite for leftovers. Would it be right to say that now food will never appeal to this person again?”

“No it would not, reverend. For it’s quite possible that other food won’t appeal to that person as long as the nourishment is still present. But when the nourishment vanishes food will appeal again.”

“In the same way, take an individual who, with the fading away of rapture … enters and remains in the third absorption. Thinking, ‘I get the third absorption!’ they mix closely with monks … They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

And take an individual who, giving up pleasure and pain … enters and remains in the fourth absorption. Thinking, ‘I get the fourth absorption!’ they mix closely with monks … They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

Suppose that in a mountain glen there was a lake, placid and free of waves. Would it be right to say that now waves will never appear in this lake again?”

“No it would not, reverend. For it is quite possible that a violent storm could blow up out of the east, west, north, or south, and stir up waves in that lake.”

“In the same way, take an individual who, giving up pleasure and pain … enters and remains in the fourth absorption. Thinking, ‘I get the fourth absorption!’ they mix closely with monks … They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

And take an individual who, not focusing on any signs, enters and remains in the signless immersion of the heart. Thinking, ‘I get the signless immersion of the heart!’ they mix closely with monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen; with rulers and their chief ministers, and with monastics of other religions and their disciples. As they mix closely, they become familiar and loose, spending time chatting, and so lust infects their mind. They resign the training and return to a lesser life.

Suppose a ruler or their chief minister, while walking along the road with an army of four divisions, was to arrive at a forest grove where they set up camp for the night. There, because of the noise of the elephants, horses, chariots, soldiers, and the drums, kettledrums, horns, and cymbals, the chirping of crickets would vanish. Would it be right to say that now the chirping of crickets will never be heard in this woodland grove again?”

“No it would not, reverend. For it is quite possible that the ruler or their chief minister will leave that woodland grove so that the chirping of crickets will be heard there again.”

“In the same way, take an individual who, not focusing on any signs, enters and remains in the signless immersion of the heart … They resign the training and return to a lesser life.”

Then after some time Venerable Citta Hatthisāriputta resigned the training and returned to a lesser life. Then the mendicants who were his companions went up to Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita and said, “Did Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita encompass Citta Hatthisāriputta’s mind and know that he had gained this and that meditative attainments, yet he would still resign the training and return to a lesser life? Or did deities tell you about it?”

“Reverends, I encompassed his mind and knew this. And deities also told me.”

Then the mendicants who were Citta Hatthisāriputta’s companions went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, Citta Hatthisāriputta, who had gained this and that meditative attainments, has still resigned the training and returned to a lesser life.”

“Mendicants, soon Citta will remember renunciation.”

And not long after Citta Hatthisāriputta shaved off his hair and beard, dressed in ocher robes, and went forth from the lay life to homelessness. Then Citta Hatthisāriputta, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And Venerable Citta Hatthisāriputta became one of the perfected.

AN 6.61 In the Middle Majjhesutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Varanasi in the deer park at Isipatana.

Now at that time, after the meal, on return from almsround, several senior mendicants sat together in the pavilion and this discussion came up among them, “Reverends, this was said by the Buddha in ‘The Way to the Far Shore’, in ‘The Questions of Metteyya’:

‘The thoughtful one, knowing both ends,
is not stuck in the middle.
He is a great man, I declare;
he has escaped the seamstress here.’

But what is one end? What’s the second end? What’s the middle? And who is the seamstress?” When this was said, one of the mendicants said to the senior mendicants:

“Contact, reverends, is one end. The origin of contact is the second end. The cessation of contact is the middle. And craving is the seamstress, for craving weaves one to being regenerated in one state of existence or another. That’s how a mendicant directly knows what should be directly known and completely understands what should be completely understood. Knowing and understanding thus they make an end of suffering in this very life.”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to the senior mendicants:

“The past, reverends, is one end. The future is the second end. The present is the middle. And craving is the seamstress … That’s how a mendicant directly knows … an end of suffering in this very life.”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to the senior mendicants:

“Pleasant feeling, reverends, is one end. Painful feeling is the second end. Neutral feeling is the middle. And craving is the seamstress … That’s how a mendicant directly knows … an end of suffering in this very life.”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to the senior mendicants:

“Name, reverends, is one end. Form is the second end. Consciousness is the middle. And craving is the seamstress … That’s how a mendicant directly knows … an end of suffering in this very life.”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to the senior mendicants:

“The six interior sense fields, reverends, are one end. The six exterior sense fields are the second end. Consciousness is the middle. And craving is the seamstress … That’s how a mendicant directly knows … an end of suffering in this very life.”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to the senior mendicants:

“Substantial reality, reverends, is one end. The origin of substantial reality is the second end. The cessation of substantial reality is the middle. And craving is the seamstress, for craving weaves one to being regenerated in one state of existence or another. That’s how a mendicant directly knows what should be directly known and completely understands what should be completely understood. Knowing and understanding thus they make an end of suffering in this very life.”

When this was said, one of the mendicants said to the senior mendicants:

“Each of us has spoken from the heart. Come, reverends, let’s go to the Buddha, and inform him about this. As he answers, so we’ll remember it.”

“Yes, reverend,” those senior mendicants replied. Then those senior mendicants went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and informed the Buddha of all they had discussed. They asked, “Sir, who has spoken well?”

“Mendicants, you’ve all spoken well in a way. However, this is what I was referring to in ‘The Way to the Far Shore’, in ‘The Questions of Metteyya’ when I said:

‘The thoughtful one, knowing both ends,
is not stuck in the middle.
He is a great man, I declare;
he has escaped the seamstress here.’

Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Contact, mendicants, is one end. The origin of contact is the second end. The cessation of contact is the middle. And craving is the seamstress, for craving weaves one to being regenerated in one state of existence or another. That’s how a mendicant directly knows what should be directly known and completely understands what should be completely understood. Knowing and understanding thus they make an end of suffering in this very life.”

AN 6.62 Knowledge of the Faculties of Persons Purisindriyañāṇasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was wandering in the land of the Kosalans together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants when he arrived at a town of the Kosalans named Daṇḍakappaka. The Buddha left the road and sat at the root of a tree on the seat spread out. The mendicants entered Daṇḍakappaka to look for a guest house.

Then Venerable Ānanda together with several mendicants went to the Aciravatī River to bathe. When he had bathed and emerged from the water he stood in one robe drying his limbs.

Then a certain mendicant went up to Venerable Ānanda, and said to him, “Reverend Ānanda, when the Buddha declared that Devadatta was going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable, did he do so after wholeheartedly deliberating, or was this just a way of speaking?”

“You’re right, reverend, that’s how the Buddha declared it.”

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“Ānanda, that mendicant must be junior, recently gone forth, or else a foolish, incompetent senior mendicant. How on earth can he take something that I have declared categorically to be ambiguous? I do not see a single other individual about whom I have given such whole-hearted deliberation before making a declaration as I did in the case of Devadatta.

As long as I saw even a fraction of a hair’s tip of goodness in Devadatta I did not declare that he was going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable. But when I saw that there was not even a fraction of a hair’s tip of goodness in Devadatta I declared that he was going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable.

Suppose there was a sewer deeper than a man’s height, full to the brim with feces, and someone was sunk into it over their head. Then along comes a person who wants to help make them safe, who wants to lift them out of that sewer. But circling all around the sewer they couldn’t see even a fraction of a hair’s tip of that person that was not smeared with feces.

In the same way, when I saw that there was not even a fraction of a hair’s tip of goodness in Devadatta I declared that he was going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable. If you would all listen, Ānanda, I will analyze the Realized One’s knowledges of the faculties of persons.”

“Now is the time, Blessed One! Now is the time, Holy One! Let the Buddha analyze the faculties of persons. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, Ānanda, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Ānanda replied. The Buddha said this:

“Ānanda, when I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand: ‘Both skillful and unskillful qualities are found in this individual.’ After some time I encompass their mind and understand: ‘The skillful qualities of this individual have vanished, but the unskillful qualities are still present. Nevertheless, their skillful root is unbroken, and from that the skillful will appear. So this individual is not liable to decline in the future.’ Suppose some seeds were intact, unspoiled, not weather-damaged, fertile, and well-kept. And they were sown in a well-prepared, productive field. Wouldn’t you know that those seeds would grow, increase, and mature?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, when I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand … This individual is not liable to decline in the future … This is how another individual is known to the Realized One by encompassing their mind. And this is how the Realized One knows a person’s faculties by encompassing their mind. And this is how the Realized One knows the future origination of a person’s qualities by encompassing their mind.

When I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand: ‘Both skillful and unskillful qualities are found in this individual.’ After some time I encompass their mind and understand: ‘The unskillful qualities of this individual have vanished, but the skillful qualities are still present. Nevertheless, their unskillful root is unbroken, and from that the unskillful will appear. So this individual is still liable to decline in the future.’ Suppose some seeds were intact, unspoiled, not weather-damaged, fertile, and well-kept. And they were sown on a broad rock. Wouldn’t you know that those seeds would not grow, increase, and mature?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, when I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand … This individual is still liable to decline in the future … This is how another individual is known to the Realized One …

When I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand: ‘Both skillful and unskillful qualities are found in this individual.’ After some time I encompass their mind and understand: ‘This individual has not even a fraction of a hair’s tip of goodness. They have absolutely dark, unskillful qualities. When their body breaks up, after death, they will be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.’ Suppose some seeds were broken, spoiled, weather-damaged. And they were sown in a well-prepared, productive field. Wouldn’t you know that those seeds would not grow, increase, and mature?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, when I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand … ‘This individual has not even a fraction of a hair’s tip of goodness. They have absolutely dark, unskillful qualities. When their body breaks up, after death, they will be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.’ …”

When he said this, Venerable Ānanda said to the Buddha, “Sir, can you describe three other individuals who share a portion of these three?”

“I can, Ānanda,” said the Buddha. “Ānanda, when I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand: ‘Both skillful and unskillful qualities are found in this individual.’ After some time I encompass their mind and understand: ‘The skillful qualities of this individual have vanished, but the unskillful qualities are still present. Nevertheless, their skillful root is unbroken, but it’s about to be totally destroyed. So this individual is still liable to decline in the future.’ Suppose there were some burning coals, blazing and glowing, placed on a broad rock. Wouldn’t you know that those coals would not grow, increase, and spread?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Or suppose it’s the late afternoon and the sun was going down. Wouldn’t you know that the light was about to vanish and darkness appear?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Or suppose that it’s nearly time for the midnight meal. Wouldn’t you know that the light had vanished and the darkness appeared?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, when I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand … This individual is still liable to decline in the future …

When I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand: ‘Both skillful and unskillful qualities are found in this individual.’ After some time I encompass their mind and understand: ‘The unskillful qualities of this individual have vanished, but the skillful qualities are still present. Nevertheless, their unskillful root is unbroken, but it’s about to be totally destroyed. So this individual is not liable to decline in the future.’ Suppose there were some burning coals, blazing and glowing, placed on a pile of grass or timber. Wouldn’t you know that those coals would grow, increase, and spread?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Or suppose it’s the crack of dawn and the sun is rising. Wouldn’t you know that the dark will vanish and the light appear?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Or suppose that it’s nearly time for the midday meal. Wouldn’t you know that the dark had vanished and the light appeared?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, when I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand … This individual is not liable to decline in the future …

When I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand: ‘Both skillful and unskillful qualities are found in this individual.’ After some time I encompass their mind and understand: ‘This individual has not even a fraction of a hair’s tip of unskillful qualities. They have absolutely bright, blameless qualities. They will become extinguished in this very life.’ Suppose there were some cool, quenched coals, placed on a pile of grass or timber. Wouldn’t you know that those coals would not grow, increase, and spread?”

“Yes, sir.”

“In the same way, when I’ve comprehended the mind of an individual, I understand … ‘This individual has not even a fraction of a hair’s tip of unskillful qualities. They have absolutely bright, blameless qualities. They will become extinguished in this very life.’ This is how another individual is known to the Realized One by encompassing their mind. And this is how the Realized One knows a person’s faculties by encompassing their mind. And this is how the Realized One knows the future origination of a person’s qualities by encompassing their mind.

And so, Ānanda, of the first three individuals one is not liable to decline, one is liable to decline, and one is bound for a place of loss, hell. And of the second three individuals, one is liable to decline, one is not liable to decline, and one is bound to become extinguished.”

AN 6.63 Penetrative Nibbedhikasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you a penetrative exposition of the teaching. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, what is the penetrative exposition of the teaching? Sensual pleasures should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.

Feelings should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.

Perceptions should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.

Defilements should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.

Deeds should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.

Suffering should be known. And its source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation should be known.

‘Sensual pleasures should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? There are these five kinds of sensual stimulation. Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds known by the ear … Smells known by the nose … Tastes known by the tongue … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. However, these are not sensual pleasures. In the training of the Noble One they’re called ‘kinds of sensual stimulation’.

Greedy intention is a person’s sensual pleasure.
The world’s pretty things aren’t sensual pleasures.
Greedy intention is a person’s sensual pleasure.
The world’s pretty things stay just as they are,
but the attentive remove desire for them.

And what is the source of sensual pleasures? Contact is their source.

And what is the diversity of sensual pleasures? The sensual desire for sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches are all different. This is called the diversity of sensual pleasures.

And what is the result of sensual pleasures? When one who desires sensual pleasures generates a corresponding incarnation, partaking of either good or bad deeds—this is called the result of sensual pleasures.

And what is the cessation of sensual pleasures? When contact ceases, sensual pleasures cease. The practice that leads to the cessation of sensual pleasures is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

When a noble disciple understands sensual pleasures in this way—and understands their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation—they understand that this penetrative spiritual life is the cessation of sensual pleasures. ‘Sensual pleasures should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘Feelings should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? There are these three feelings: pleasant, painful, and neutral.

And what is the source of feelings? Contact is their source.

And what is the diversity of feelings? There are pleasant feelings of the flesh, pleasant feelings not of the flesh, painful feelings of the flesh, painful feelings not of the flesh, neutral feelings of the flesh, and neutral feelings not of the flesh. This is called the disparity of feelings.

And what is the result of feelings? When one who feels generates a corresponding incarnation, partaking of either good or bad deeds—this is called the result of feelings.

And what is the cessation of feelings? When contact ceases, feelings cease. The practice that leads to the cessation of feelings is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

When a noble disciple understands feelings in this way … they understand that this penetrative spiritual life is the cessation of feelings. ‘Feelings should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘Perceptions should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? There are these six perceptions: perceptions of sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas.

And what is the source of perceptions? Contact is their source.

And what is the diversity of perceptions? The perceptions of sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas are all different. This is called the diversity of perceptions.

And what is the result of perceptions? Communication is the result of perception, I say. You communicate something in whatever manner you perceive it, saying ‘That’s what I perceived.’ This is called the result of perceptions.

And what is the cessation of perception? When contact ceases, perception ceases. The practice that leads to the cessation of perceptions is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

When a noble disciple understands perception in this way … they understand that this penetrative spiritual life is the cessation of perception. ‘Perceptions should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘Defilements should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? There are these three defilements: the defilements of sensuality, desire to be reborn, and ignorance.

And what is the source of defilements? Ignorance is the source of defilements.

And what is the disparity of defilements? There are defilements that lead to rebirth in hell, the animal realm, the ghost realm, the human world, and the world of the gods. This is called the disparity of defilements.

And what is the result of defilements? When one who is ignorant generates a corresponding incarnation, partaking of either good or bad deeds—this is called the result of defilements.

And what is the cessation of defilements? When ignorance ceases, defilements cease. The practice that leads to the cessation of defilements is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

When a noble disciple understands defilements in this way … they understand that this penetrative spiritual life is the cessation of defilements. ‘Defilements should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘Deeds should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? It is intention that I call deeds. For after making a choice one acts by way of body, speech, and mind.

And what is the source of deeds? Contact is their source.

And what is the disparity of deeds? There are deeds that lead to rebirth in hell, the animal realm, the ghost realm, the human world, and the world of the gods. This is called the disparity of deeds.

And what is the result of deeds? The result of deeds is threefold, I say: in this very life, on rebirth in the next life, or at some later time. This is called the result of deeds.

And what is the cessation of deeds? When contact ceases, deeds cease. The practice that leads to the cessation of deeds is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

When a noble disciple understands deeds in this way … they understand that this penetrative spiritual life is the cessation of deeds. ‘Deeds should be known. And their source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘Suffering should be known. And its source, disparity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Rebirth is suffering; old age is suffering; illness is suffering; death is suffering; sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress are suffering; not getting what you wish for is suffering. In brief, the five grasping aggregates are suffering.

And what is the source of suffering? Craving is the source of suffering.

And what is the disparity of suffering? There is suffering that is severe, mild, slow to fade, and quick to fade. This is called the disparity of suffering.

And what is the result of suffering? It’s when someone who is overcome and overwhelmed by suffering sorrows and wails and laments, beating their breast and falling into confusion. Or else, overcome by that suffering, they begin an external search, wondering: ‘Who knows one or two phrases to stop this suffering?’ The result of suffering is either confusion or a search, I say. This is called the result of suffering.

And what is the cessation of suffering? When craving ceases, suffering ceases. The practice that leads to the cessation of suffering is simply this noble eightfold path, that is: right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

When a noble disciple understands suffering in this way … they understand that this penetrative spiritual life is the cessation of suffering. ‘Suffering should be known. And its source, diversity, result, cessation, and the practice that leads to its cessation should be known.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

This is the penetrative exposition of the teaching.”

AN 6.64 The Lion’s Roar Sīhanādasutta

“Mendicants, the Realized One possesses six powers of a Realized One. With these he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel. What six?

Firstly, the Realized One truly understands the possible as possible and the impossible as impossible. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. Relying on this he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel.

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands the result of deeds undertaken in the past, future, and present in terms of grounds and causes. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One truly understands corruption, cleansing, and emergence regarding the absorptions, liberations, immersions, and attainments. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One recollects many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. He remembers: ‘There, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn somewhere else. There, too, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn here.’ And so he recollects his many kinds of past lives, with features and details. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, the Realized One sees sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. He understands how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. …

Furthermore, the Realized One has realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And he lives having realized it with his own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. Since he truly understands this, this is a power of the Realized One. Relying on this he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel. These are the six powers of a Realized One that the Realized One possesses. With these he claims the bull’s place, roars his lion’s roar in the assemblies, and turns the divine wheel.

If others come to the Realized One and ask questions about his true knowledge of the possible as possible and the impossible as impossible, the Realized One answers them in whatever manner he has truly known it.

If others come to the Realized One and ask questions about his true knowledge of the result of deeds undertaken in the past, future, and present in terms of grounds and causes, the Realized One answers them in whatever manner he has truly known it.

If others come to the Realized One and ask questions about his true knowledge of corruption, cleansing, and emergence regarding the absorptions, liberations, immersions, and attainments, the Realized One answers them in whatever manner he has truly known it.

If others come to the Realized One and ask questions about his true knowledge of recollection of past lives, the Realized One answers them in whatever manner he has truly known it.

If others come to the Realized One and ask questions about his true knowledge of passing away and rebirth of sentient beings, the Realized One answers them in whatever manner he has truly known it.

If others come to the Realized One and ask questions about his true knowledge of the ending of defilements, the Realized One answers them in whatever manner he has truly known it.

And I say that true knowledge of the possible as possible and the impossible as impossible is for those with immersion, not for those without immersion. And true knowledge of the result of deeds undertaken in the past, future, and present in terms of grounds and causes is for those with immersion, not for those without immersion. And true knowledge of corruption, cleansing, and emergence regarding the absorptions, liberations, immersions, and attainments is for those with immersion, not for those without immersion. And true knowledge of the recollection of past lives is for those with immersion, not for those without immersion. And true knowledge of the passing away and rebirth of sentient beings is for those with immersion, not for those without immersion. And true knowledge of the ending of defilements is for those with immersion, not for those without immersion.

And so, mendicants, immersion is the path. No immersion is the wrong path.”

The Chapter on Deities

AN 6.65 The Fruit of Non-Return Anāgāmiphalasutta

“Mendicants, without giving up six things you can’t realize the fruit of non-return. What six? Lack of faith, conscience, and prudence; laziness, unmindfulness, and witlessness. Without giving up these six things you can’t realize the fruit of non-return.

After giving up six things you can realize the fruit of non-return. What six? Lack of faith, conscience, and prudence; laziness, unmindfulness, and witlessness. After giving up these six things you can realize the fruit of non-return.”

AN 6.66 Perfection Arahattasutta

“Mendicants, without giving up six things you can’t realize perfection. What six? Dullness, drowsiness, restlessness, remorse, lack of faith, and negligence. Without giving up these six things you can’t realize perfection.

After giving up six things you can realize perfection. What six? Dullness, drowsiness, restlessness, remorse, lack of faith, and negligence. After giving up these six things you can realize perfection.”

AN 6.67 Friends Mittasutta

“Mendicants, it is quite impossible that a mendicant with bad friends, companions, and associates, while frequenting, accompanying, and attending, and following their example, will fulfill the practice dealing with the supplementary regulations. Without fulfilling the practice dealing with supplementary regulations, it’s impossible to fulfill the practice of a trainee. Without fulfilling the practice of a trainee, it’s impossible to fulfill ethics. Without fulfilling ethics, it’s impossible to give up sensual desire, or desire to be reborn in the realm of luminous form or in the formless realm.

It’s quite possible that a mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates, while frequenting, accompanying, and attending, and following their example, will fulfill the practice dealing with the supplementary regulations. Having fulfilled the practice dealing with supplementary regulations, it’s possible to fulfill the practice of a trainee. Having fulfilled the practice of a trainee, it’s possible to fulfill ethics. Having fulfilled ethics, it’s possible to give up sensual desire, and desire to be reborn in the realm of luminous form and in the formless realm.”

AN 6.68 Enjoying Company Saṅgaṇikārāmasutta

“Mendicants, it is quite impossible that a mendicant who enjoys company and groups, who loves them and likes to enjoy them, should take pleasure in being alone in seclusion. Without taking pleasure in being alone in seclusion, it’s impossible to learn the patterns of the mind. Without learning the mind’s character, it’s impossible to fulfill right view. Without fulfilling right view, it’s impossible to fulfill right immersion. Without fulfilling right immersion, it’s impossible to give up the fetters. Without giving up the fetters, it’s impossible to realize extinguishment.

It’s quite possible that a mendicant who doesn’t enjoy company and groups, who doesn’t love them and like to enjoy them, should take pleasure in being alone in seclusion. For someone who takes pleasure in being alone in seclusion, it’s possible to learn the mind’s character. For someone who learns the mind’s character, it’s possible to fulfill right view. Having fulfilled right view, it’s possible to fulfill right immersion. Having fulfilled right immersion, it’s possible to give up the fetters. Having given up the fetters, it’s possible to realize extinguishment.”

AN 6.69 A God Devatāsutta

Then, late at night, a glorious deity, lighting up the entire Jeta’s Grove, went up to the Buddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, these six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant. What six? Respect for the Teacher, for the teaching, for the Saṅgha, for the training; being easy to admonish, and good friendship. These six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant.”

That is what that deity said, and the Teacher concurred. Then that deity, knowing that the Teacher concurred, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before vanishing right there.

Then, when the night had passed, the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Tonight, a glorious deity, lighting up the entire Jeta’s Grove, came to me, bowed, stood to one side, and said to me: ‘Sir, these six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant. What six? Respect for the Teacher, for the teaching, for the Saṅgha, for the training; being easy to admonish, and good friendship. These six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant.’

That is what that deity said. Then he bowed and respectfully circled me, keeping me on his right side, before vanishing right there.”

When he said this, Venerable Sāriputta said to the Buddha:

“Sir, this is how I understand the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement. It’s when a mendicant personally respects the Teacher and praises such respect. And they encourage other mendicants who lack such respect to respect the Teacher. And they praise other mendicants who respect the Teacher at the right time, truthfully and correctly. They personally respect the teaching … They personally respect the Saṅgha … They personally respect the training … They are personally easy to admonish … They personally have good friends, and praise such friendship. And they encourage other mendicants who lack good friends to develop good friendship. And they praise other mendicants who have good friends at the right time, truthfully and correctly. That’s how I understand the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! It’s good that you understand the detailed meaning of what I’ve said in brief like this.

It’s when a mendicant personally respects the Teacher … They personally respect the teaching … They personally respect the Saṅgha … They personally respect the training … They are personally easy to admonish … They personally have good friends, and praise such friendship. And they encourage other mendicants who lack good friends to develop good friendship. And they praise other mendicants who have good friends at the right time, truthfully and correctly. This is how to see the detailed meaning of what I said in brief.”

AN 6.70 Immersion Samādhisutta

“Mendicants, it is quite impossible that a mendicant without immersion that is peaceful, refined, tranquil, and unified will wield the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again; materializing and dematerializing; going unobstructed through a wall, a rampart, or a mountain as if through space; diving in and out of the earth as if it were water; walking on water as if it were earth; flying cross-legged through the sky like a bird; touching and stroking with the hand the sun and moon, so mighty and powerful. They control the body as far as the realm of divinity.

It’s impossible that with clairaudience that is purified and superhuman, they’ll hear both kinds of sounds, human and heavenly, whether near or far.

It’s impossible that they’ll understand the minds of other beings and individuals, having encompassed them with their own mind, understanding mind with greed as ‘mind with greed’ … and freed mind as ‘freed mind’.

It’s impossible that they’ll recollect many kinds of past lives, with features and details.

It’s impossible that with clairvoyance that is purified and surpasses the human, they’ll understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds.

It’s impossible that they’ll realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

But it’s quite possible that a mendicant who has immersion that is peaceful, refined, tranquil, and unified will wield the many kinds of psychic power …

It’s possible that with clairaudience that is purified and superhuman, they’ll hear both kinds of sounds …

It’s possible that they’ll understand the minds of other beings …

It’s possible that they’ll recollect many kinds of past lives, with features and details.

It’s possible that with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, they’ll understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds.

It’s possible that they’ll realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

AN 6.71 Capable of Realizing Sakkhibhabbasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with six qualities is incapable of realizing anything that can be realized, since each and every one is within range. What six? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t truly understand which qualities make things worse, which keep things steady, which lead to distinction, and which lead to penetration. And they don’t practice carefully or do what’s suitable. A mendicant with these six qualities is incapable of realizing anything that can be realized, since each and every one is within range.

A mendicant with six qualities is capable of realizing anything that can be realized, since each and every one is within range. What six? It’s when a mendicant truly understands which qualities make things worse, which keep things steady, which lead to distinction, and which lead to penetration. And they practice carefully and do what’s suitable. A mendicant with these six qualities is capable of realizing anything that can be realized, since each and every one is within range.”

AN 6.72 Strength Balasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant who has six qualities can’t attain strength in immersion. What six? It’s when a mendicant is not skilled in entering immersion, skilled in remaining in immersion, or skilled in emerging from immersion. And they don’t practice carefully and persistently, and they don’t do what’s suitable. A mendicant who possesses these six qualities can’t attain strength in immersion.

A mendicant who has six qualities can attain strength in immersion. What six? It’s when a mendicant is skilled in entering immersion, skilled in remaining in immersion, and skilled in emerging from immersion. And they practice carefully and persistently, and do what’s suitable. A mendicant who possesses these six qualities can attain strength in immersion.”

AN 6.73 First Absorption (1st) Paṭhamatajjhānasutta

“Mendicants, without giving up these six qualities you can’t enter and remain in the first absorption. What six? Desire for sensual pleasures, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. And the drawbacks of sensual pleasures have not been truly seen clearly with right wisdom. Without giving up these six qualities you can’t enter and remain in the first absorption.

But after giving up these six qualities you can enter and remain in the first absorption. What six? Desire for sensual pleasures, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. And the drawbacks of sensual pleasures have been truly seen clearly with right wisdom. After giving up these six qualities you can enter and remain in the first absorption.”

AN 6.74 First Absorption (2nd) Dutiyatajjhānasutta

“Mendicants, without giving up these six qualities you can’t enter and remain in the first absorption. What six? Sensual, malicious, and cruel thoughts; and sensual, malicious, and cruel perceptions. Without giving up these six qualities you can’t enter and remain in the first absorption.

But after giving up these six qualities you can enter and remain in the first absorption. What six? Sensual, malicious, and cruel thoughts; and sensual, malicious, and cruel perceptions. After giving up these six qualities you can enter and remain in the first absorption.”

The First Fifty

The Chapter on Worthy of Offerings

AN 6.1 Worthy of Offerings (1st) Paṭhamaāhuneyyasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, a mendicant with six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What six?

It’s a mendicant who, when they see a sight with their eyes, is neither happy nor sad. They remain equanimous, mindful and aware.

When they hear a sound with their ears …

When they smell an odor with their nose …

When they taste a flavor with their tongue …

When they feel a touch with their body …

When they know an idea with their mind, they’re neither happy nor sad. They remain equanimous, mindful and aware.

A mendicant with these six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, the mendicants approved what the Buddha said.

AN 6.2 Worthy of Offerings (2nd) Dutiyaāhuneyyasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What six?

It’s a mendicant who wields the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying themselves and becoming one again; materializing and dematerializing; going unobstructed through a wall, a rampart, or a mountain as if through space; diving in and out of the earth as if it were water; walking on water as if it were earth; flying cross-legged through the sky like a bird; touching and stroking with the hand the sun and moon, so mighty and powerful. They control the body as far as the realm of divinity.

With clairaudience that is purified and superhuman, they hear both kinds of sounds, human and heavenly, whether near or far.

They understand the minds of other beings and individuals, having encompassed them with their own mind. They understand mind with greed as ‘mind with greed’, and mind without greed as ‘mind without greed’. They understand mind with hate … mind without hate … mind with delusion … mind without delusion … constricted mind … scattered mind … expansive mind … unexpansive mind … mind that is not supreme … mind that is supreme … mind immersed in samādhi … mind not immersed in samādhi … freed mind … They understand unfreed mind as ‘unfreed mind’.

They recollect many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. They remember: ‘There, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn somewhere else. There, too, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn here.’ And so they recollect their many kinds of past lives, with features and details.

With clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, they see sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. They understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds: ‘These dear beings did bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. They denounced the noble ones; they had wrong view; and they chose to act out of that wrong view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. These dear beings, however, did good things by way of body, speech, and mind. They never denounced the noble ones; they had right view; and they chose to act out of that right view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’ And so, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, they see sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. They understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds.

They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

A mendicant with these six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 6.3 Faculties Indriyasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What six? The faculties of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. And they realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 6.4 Powers Balasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What six? The powers of faith, energy, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. And they realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 6.5 The Thoroughbred (1st) Paṭhamaājānīyasutta

“Mendicants, a fine royal thoroughbred with six factors is worthy of a king, fit to serve a king, and is reckoned a factor of kingship.

What six? It’s when a fine royal thoroughbred can endure sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches. And it’s beautiful. A fine royal thoroughbred with these six factors is worthy of a king, fit to serve a king, and is reckoned a factor of kingship.

In the same way, a mendicant with six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What six? It’s when a mendicant can endure sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas. A mendicant with these six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 6.6 The Thoroughbred (2nd) Dutiyaājānīyasutta

“Mendicants, a fine royal thoroughbred with six factors is worthy of a king, fit to serve a king, and is reckoned a factor of kingship. What six? It’s when a fine royal thoroughbred can endure sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches. And it’s strong. A fine royal thoroughbred with these six factors is worthy of a king, fit to serve a king, and is reckoned a factor of kingship.

In the same way, a mendicant with six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What six? It’s when a mendicant can endure sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas. A mendicant with these six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 6.7 The Thoroughbred (3rd) Tatiyaājānīyasutta

“Mendicants, a fine royal thoroughbred with six factors is worthy of a king, fit to serve a king, and is reckoned a factor of kingship. What six? It’s when a fine royal thoroughbred can endure sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches. And it’s fast. A fine royal thoroughbred with these six factors is worthy of a king, fit to serve a king, and is reckoned a factor of kingship.

In the same way, a mendicant with six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What six? It’s when a mendicant can endure sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, and ideas. A mendicant with these six qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 6.8 Unsurpassable Anuttariyasutta

“Mendicants, these six things are unsurpassable. What six? The unsurpassable seeing, listening, acquisition, training, service, and recollection. These are the six unsurpassable things.”

AN 6.9 Topics for Recollection Anussatiṭṭhānasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six topics for recollection. What six? The recollection of the Buddha, the teaching, the Saṅgha, ethics, generosity, and the deities. These are the six topics for recollection.”

AN 6.10 With Mahānāma Mahānāmasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Then Mahānāma the Sakyan went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, when a noble disciple has reached the fruit and understood the instructions, what kind of meditation do they frequently practice?”

“Mahānāma, when a noble disciple has reached the fruit and understood the instructions they frequently practice this kind of meditation.

Firstly, a noble disciple recollects the Realized One: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ When a noble disciple recollects the Realized One their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving, based on the Realized One. A noble disciple whose mind is unswerving finds inspiration in the meaning and the teaching, and finds joy connected with the teaching. When they’re joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, they feel bliss. And when they’re blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and develop the recollection of the Buddha.

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’ When a noble disciple recollects the teaching their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. … This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and develop the recollection of the teaching.

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.’ When a noble disciple recollects the Saṅgha their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. … This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and develop the recollection of the Saṅgha.

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects their own ethical precepts, which are intact, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. When a noble disciple recollects their ethical precepts their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. … This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and develop the recollection of ethics.

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects their generosity: ‘I’m so fortunate, so very fortunate! Among people full of the stain of stinginess I live at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share.’ When a noble disciple recollects their generosity their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. … This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and develop the recollection of generosity.

Furthermore, a noble disciple recollects the deities: ‘There are the gods of the four great kings, the gods of the thirty-three, the gods of Yama, the joyful gods, the gods who love to create, the gods who control what is created by others, the gods of the Divinity’s host, and gods even higher than these. When those deities passed away from here, they were reborn there because of their faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. I, too, have the same kind of faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom.’ When a noble disciple recollects the faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom of both themselves and the deities their mind is not full of greed, hate, and delusion. At that time their mind is quite unswerving, based on the deities. A noble disciple whose mind is unswerving finds inspiration in the meaning and the teaching, and finds joy connected with the teaching. When you’re joyful, rapture springs up. When the mind is full of rapture, the body becomes tranquil. When the body is tranquil, you feel bliss. And when you’re blissful, the mind becomes immersed in samādhi. This is called a noble disciple who lives in balance among people who are unbalanced, and lives untroubled among people who are troubled. They’ve entered the stream of the teaching and develop the recollection of the deities.

When a noble disciple has reached the fruit and understood the instructions this is the kind of meditation they frequently practice.”

The Chapter on Deities

AN 6.31 A Trainee Sekhasutta

“These six things lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee. What six? They relish work, talk, sleep, and company. They don’t guard the sense doors, and they eat too much. These six things lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

These six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee. What six? They don’t relish work, talk, sleep, and company. They guard the sense doors, and they don’t eat too much. These six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.”

AN 6.32 Non-decline (1st) Paṭhamaaparihānasutta

Then, late at night, a glorious deity, lighting up the entire Jeta’s Grove, went up to the Buddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, these six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant. What six? Respect for the Teacher, for the teaching, for the Saṅgha, for the training, for diligence, and for hospitality. These six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant.”

That is what that deity said, and the Teacher concurred. Then that deity, knowing that the Teacher concurred, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before vanishing right there.

Then, when the night had passed, the Buddha told the mendicants all that had happened, adding:

“Respect for the Teacher and the teaching,
and keen respect for the Saṅgha;
a mendicant who respects diligence
and hospitality
can’t decline,
and has drawn near to extinguishment.”

AN 6.33 Non-decline (2nd) Dutiyaaparihānasutta

“Tonight, a glorious deity, lighting up the entire Jeta’s Grove, came to me, bowed, stood to one side, and said to me: ‘Sir, these six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant. What six? Respect for the Teacher, for the teaching, for the Saṅgha, for the training, for conscience, and for prudence. These six things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant.’

That is what that deity said. Then he bowed and respectfully circled me, keeping me on his right side, before vanishing right there.

One respectful of the Teacher and the teaching,
keenly respecting the Saṅgha;
endowed with conscience and prudence,
reverential and respectful—
it is impossible for them to decline;
they have drawn near to extinguishment.”

AN 6.34 With Mahāmoggallāna Mahāmoggallānasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Then as Venerable Mahāmoggallāna was in private retreat this thought came to his mind, “Which gods know that they are stream-enterers, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening?”

Now, at that time a monk named Tissa had recently passed away and been reborn in a realm of divinity. There they knew that The divinity Tissa was very mighty and powerful.

And then Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, vanished from Jeta’s Grove and reappeared in that realm of divinity.

Tissa saw Moggallāna coming off in the distance, and said to him, “Come, my good fellow Moggallāna! Welcome, my good fellow! It’s been a long time since you took the opportunity to come here. Sit, my good Moggallāna, this seat is for you.” Moggallāna sat down on the seat spread out. Then Tissa bowed to Moggallāna and sat to one side.

Moggallāna said to him, “Tissa, which gods know that they are stream-enterers, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening?”

“The gods of the four great kings know this.”

“But do all of them know this?”

“No, my good Moggallāna, not all of them. Those who lack experiential confidence in the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and lack the ethics loved by the noble ones, do not know that they are stream-enterers. But those who have experiential confidence in the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and have the ethics loved by the noble ones, do know that they are stream-enterers.”

“But Tissa, is it only the gods of the four great kings who know that they are stream-enterers, or do the gods of the thirty-three … the gods of Yama … the joyful gods … the gods who love to create … and the gods who control what is created by others know that they are stream-enterers, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening?”

“The gods of these various classes know this.”

“But do all of them know this?”

“No, my good Moggallāna, not all of them. Those who lack experiential confidence in the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and lack the ethics loved by the noble ones, do not know that they are stream-enterers. But those who have experiential confidence in the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and have the ethics loved by the noble ones, do know that they are stream-enterers.”

Moggallāna approved and agreed with what the divinity Tissa said. Then, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, he vanished from that realm of divinity and reappeared in Jeta’s Grove.

AN 6.35 Things That Play a Part in Realization Vijjābhāgiyasutta

“These six things play a part in realization. What six? The perception of impermanence, the perception of suffering in impermanence, the perception of not-self in suffering, the perception of giving up, the perception of fading away, and the perception of cessation. These are the six things that play a part in realization.”

AN 6.36 Roots of Dispute Vivādamūlasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six roots of dispute. What six? Firstly, a mendicant is irritable and acrimonious. Such a mendicant lacks respect and reverence for the Teacher, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and they don’t fulfill the training. They create a dispute in the Saṅgha, which is for the detriment and unhappiness of the people, against the people, for the harm, detriment, and suffering of gods and humans. If you see such a root of dispute in yourselves or others, you should try to give up this bad thing. If you don’t see it, you should practice so that it doesn’t come up in the future. That’s how to give up this bad root of dispute, so it doesn’t come up in the future.

Furthermore, a mendicant is offensive and contemptuous … They’re jealous and stingy … They’re devious and deceitful … They have corrupt wishes and wrong view … They’re attached to their own views, holding them tight, and refusing to let go. Such a mendicant lacks respect and reverence for the Teacher, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and they don’t fulfill the training. They create a dispute in the Saṅgha, which is for the detriment and unhappiness of the people, against the people, for the harm, detriment, and suffering of gods and humans. If you see such a root of dispute in yourselves or others, you should try to give up this bad thing. If you don’t see it, you should practice so that it doesn’t come up in the future. That’s how to give up this bad root of dispute, so it doesn’t come up in the future. These are the six roots of dispute.”

AN 6.37 A Gift With Six Factors Chaḷaṅgadānasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Now at that time Veḷukaṇṭakī, Nanda’s mother, was preparing a religious donation with six factors for the mendicant Saṅgha headed by Sāriputta and Moggallāna. The Buddha saw her doing this, with his clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, and he addressed the mendicants:

“This Veḷukaṇṭakī, Nanda’s mother, is preparing a religious donation with six factors for the mendicant Saṅgha headed by Sāriputta and Moggallāna.

And how does a religious donation have six factors? Three factors apply to the donor and three to the recipients.

What three factors apply to the donor? It’s when a donor is in a good mood before giving, while giving they feel confident, and after giving they’re uplifted. These three factors apply to the donor.

What three factors apply to the recipients? It’s when the recipients are free of greed, hate, and delusion, or practicing to be free of them. These three factors apply to the recipients.

Thus three factors apply to the donor and three to the recipients. That’s how a religious donation has six factors.

It’s not easy to grasp the merit of such a six-factored donation by saying that this is the extent of their overflowing merit, overflowing goodness that nurtures happiness and is conducive to heaven, ripening in happiness and leading to heaven. And it leads to what is likable, desirable, agreeable, to welfare and happiness. It’s simply reckoned as an incalculable, immeasurable, great mass of merit.

It’s like trying to grasp how much water is in the ocean. It’s not easy to say how many gallons, how many hundreds, thousands, hundreds of thousands of gallons there are. It’s simply reckoned as an incalculable, immeasurable, great mass of water. In the same way, it’s not easy to grasp the merit of such a six-factored donation …

A good mood before giving,
confidence while giving,
feeling uplifted after giving:
this is the perfect sacrifice.

Free of greed, free of hate,
free of delusion, undefiled;
this is the field for the perfect sacrifice,
the disciplined spiritual practitioners.

After rinsing,
you give with your own hands.
This sacrifice is very fruitful
for both yourself and others.

When an intelligent, faithful person,
sacrifices like this, with a mind of letting go,
that astute one is reborn
in a happy, pleasing world.”

AN 6.38 One’s Own Volition Attakārīsutta

Then a certain brahmin went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, this is my doctrine and view: One does not act of one’s own volition, nor does one act of another’s volition.”

“Brahmin, may I never see or hear of anyone holding such a doctrine or view! How on earth can someone who comes and goes on his own say that one does not act of one’s own volition, nor does one act of another’s volition?

What do you think, brahmin, is there an element of initiative?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Since this is so, do we find sentient beings who initiate activity?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Since there is an element of initiative, and sentient beings who initiate activity are found, sentient beings act of their own volition or that of another.

What do you think, brahmin, is there an element of persistence … exertion … strength … endurance … exertion?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Since this is so, do we find sentient beings who have exertion?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Since there is an element of exertion, and sentient beings who have exertion are found, sentient beings act of their own volition or that of another.

Brahmin, may I never see or hear of anyone holding such a doctrine or view! How on earth can someone who comes and goes on his own say that one does not act of one’s own volition, nor does one act of another’s volition?”

“Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 6.39 Sources Nidānasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three sources that give rise to deeds. What three? Greed, hate, and delusion are sources that give rise to deeds. Greed doesn’t give rise to contentment. Rather, greed just gives rise to greed. Hate doesn’t give rise to love. Rather, hate just gives rise to hate. Delusion doesn’t give rise to understanding. Rather, delusion just gives rise to delusion. It’s not because of deeds born of greed, hate, and delusion that gods, humans, or those in any other good places are found. Rather, it’s because of deeds born of greed, hate, and delusion that hell, the animal realm, the ghost realm, or any other bad places are found. These are three sources that give rise to deeds.

Mendicants, there are these three sources that give rise to deeds. What three? Contentment, love, and understanding are sources that give rise to deeds. Contentment doesn’t give rise to greed. Rather, contentment just gives rise to contentment. Love doesn’t give rise to hate. Rather, love just gives rise to love. Understanding doesn’t give rise to delusion. Rather, understanding just gives rise to understanding. It’s not because of deeds born of contentment, love, and understanding that hell, the animal realm, the ghost realm, or any other bad places are found. Rather, it’s because of deeds born of contentment, love, and understanding that gods, humans, or those in any other good places are found. These are three sources that give rise to deeds.”

AN 6.40 With Kimbila Kimilasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Kimbilā in the Freshwater Mangrove Wood. Then Venerable Kimbila went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“What is the cause, sir, what is the reason why the true teaching does not last long after the final quenching of the Realized One?”

“Kimbila, it’s when the monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen lack respect and reverence for the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, diligence, and hospitality after the final quenching of the Realized One. This is the cause, this is the reason why the true teaching does not last long after the final quenching of the Realized One.”

“What is the cause, sir, what is the reason why the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One?”

“Kimbila, it’s when the monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen maintain respect and reverence for the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, diligence, and hospitality after the final quenching of the Realized One. This is the cause, this is the reason why the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One.”

AN 6.41 A Tree Trunk Dārukkhandhasutta

So I have heard. At one time Venerable Sāriputta was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain.

Then Venerable Sāriputta robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, descended the Vulture’s Peak together with several mendicants. At a certain spot he saw a large tree trunk, and he addressed the mendicants, “Reverends, do you see this large tree trunk?”

“Yes, reverend.”

“If they wanted to, a mendicant with psychic powers who has mastered their mind could determine this tree trunk to be nothing but earth. Why is that? Because the earth element exists in the tree trunk. Relying on that a mendicant with psychic powers could determine it to be nothing but earth. If they wanted to, a mendicant with psychic powers who has mastered their mind could determine this tree trunk to be nothing but water. … Or they could determine it to be nothing but fire … Or they could determine it to be nothing but air … Or they could determine it to be nothing but beautiful … Or they could determine it to be nothing but ugly. Why is that? Because the element of ugliness exists in the tree trunk. Relying on that a mendicant with psychic powers could determine it to be nothing but ugly.”

AN 6.42 With Nāgita Nāgitasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was wandering in the land of the Kosalans together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants when he arrived at a village of the Kosalan brahmins named Icchānaṅgala. He stayed in a forest near Icchānaṅgala. The brahmins and householders of Icchānaṅgala heard:

“It seems the ascetic Gotama—a Sakyan, gone forth from a Sakyan family—has arrived at Icchānaṅgala. He is staying in a forest near Icchānaṅgala. He has this good reputation: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ He has realized with his own insight this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, gods and humans—and he makes it known to others. He teaches Dhamma that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And he reveals a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. It’s good to see such perfected ones.” Then, when the night had passed, they took abundant fresh and cooked foods and went to the forest near Icchānaṅgala, where they stood outside the gates making a colossal racket.

Now, at that time Venerable Nāgita was the Buddha’s attendant. Then the Buddha said to Nāgita, “Nāgita, who’s making that colossal racket? You’d think it was fishermen hauling in a catch!”

“Sir, it’s these brahmins and householders of Icchānaṅgala. They’ve brought many fresh and cooked foods, and they’re standing outside the gates wanting to offer it specially to the Buddha and the mendicant Saṅgha.”

“Nāgita, may I never become famous. May fame not come to me. There are those who can’t get the pleasure of renunciation, the pleasure of seclusion, the pleasure of peace, the pleasure of awakening when they want, without trouble or difficulty like I can. Let them enjoy the filthy, lazy pleasure of possessions, honor, and popularity.”

“Sir, may the Blessed One please relent now! May the Holy One relent! Now is the time for the Buddha to relent. Wherever the Buddha now goes, the brahmins and householders, and people of town and country will incline the same way. It’s like when the heavens rain heavily and the water flows downhill. In the same way, wherever the Buddha now goes, the brahmins and householders, and people of town and country will incline the same way. Why is that? Because of the Buddha’s ethics and wisdom.”

“Nāgita, may I never become famous. May fame not come to me. There are those who can’t get the pleasure of renunciation, the pleasure of seclusion, the pleasure of peace, the pleasure of awakening when they want, without trouble or difficulty like I can. Let them enjoy the filthy, lazy pleasure of possessions, honor, and popularity.

Take a mendicant living within a village who I see sitting immersed in samādhi. I think to myself: ‘Now a monastery worker, a novice, or a fellow practitioner will make this venerable fall from immersion.’ So I’m not pleased that that mendicant is living within a village.

Take a mendicant in the wilderness who I see sitting nodding in meditation. I think to myself: ‘Now this venerable, having dispelled that sleepiness and weariness, will focus just on the unified perception of wilderness.’ So I’m pleased that that mendicant is living in the wilderness.

Take a mendicant in the wilderness who I see sitting without being immersed in samādhi. I think to myself: ‘Now if this venerable’s mind is not immersed in samādhi they will immerse it; or if it is immersed in samādhi, they will preserve it.’ So I’m pleased that that mendicant is living in the wilderness.

Take a mendicant in the wilderness who I see sitting immersed in samādhi. I think to myself: ‘Now this venerable will free the unfreed mind or preserve the freed mind.’ So I’m pleased that that mendicant is living in the wilderness.

Take a mendicant who I see living within a village receiving robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. Enjoying possessions, honor, and popularity they neglect retreat, and they neglect remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. They come down to villages, towns, and capital cities and make their home there. So I’m not pleased that that mendicant is living within a village.

Take a mendicant who I see in the wilderness receiving robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. Fending off possessions, honor, and popularity they don’t neglect retreat, and they don’t neglect remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. So I’m pleased that that mendicant is living in the wilderness.

Nāgita, when I’m walking along a road and I don’t see anyone ahead or behind I feel relaxed, even if I need to urinate or defecate.”

Abbreviated Texts Beginning With Greed

AN 6.140 Untitled Discourse on Greed (1st) ~

“For insight into greed, six things should be developed. What six? The unsurpassable seeing, listening, acquisition, training, service, and recollection. For insight into greed, these six things should be developed.”

AN 6.141 Untitled Discourse on Greed (2nd) ~

“For insight into greed, six things should be developed. What six? The recollection of the Buddha, the teaching, the Saṅgha, ethics, generosity, and the deities. For insight into greed, these six things should be developed.”

AN 6.142 Untitled Discourse on Greed (3rd) ~

“For insight into greed, six things should be developed. What six? The perception of impermanence, the perception of suffering in impermanence, the perception of not-self in suffering, the perception of giving up, the perception of fading away, and the perception of cessation. For insight into greed, these six things should be developed.”

AN 6.143–169 Untitled Discourses on Greed, Etc. ~

“For the complete understanding of greed … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … letting go of greed these six things should be developed.”

AN 6.170–649 Untitled Discourses on Hate, Etc. ~

“For insight into hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … jealousy … stinginess … deceitfulness … deviousness … obstinacy … aggression … conceit … arrogance … vanity …

For insight into negligence … complete understanding … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … For the letting go of negligence these six things should be developed.”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, the mendicants approved what the Buddha said.

The Book of the Sixes is finished.

The Chapter on the Ascetic Life

AN 6.117 Observing the Body Kāyānupassīsutta

“Mendicants, without giving up these six qualities you can’t meditate observing an aspect of the body. What six? Relishing work, talk, sleep, and company, not guarding the sense doors, and eating too much. Without giving up these six qualities you can’t meditate observing an aspect of the body.

But after giving up these six qualities you can meditate observing an aspect of the body. What six? Relishing work, talk, sleep, and company, not guarding the sense doors, and eating too much. After giving up these six qualities you can meditate observing an aspect of the body.”

AN 6.118 Observing Principles, Etc. Dhammānupassīsutta

“Mendicants, without giving up six things you can’t meditate observing an aspect of the body internally … body externally … body internally and externally … feelings internally … feelings externally … feelings internally and externally … mind internally … mind externally … mind internally and externally … principles internally … principles externally … principles internally and externally. What six? Relishing work, talk, sleep, and company, not guarding the sense doors, and eating too much. After giving up these six qualities you can meditate observing an aspect of principles internally and externally.”

AN 6.119 About Tapussa Tapussasutta

“Mendicants, having six qualities the householder Tapussa is certain about the Realized One, sees freedom from death and lives having realized freedom from death. What six? Experiential confidence in the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and noble ethics, knowledge, and freedom. Having these six qualities the householder Tapussa is certain about the Realized One, sees freedom from death and lives having realized freedom from death.”

AN 6.120–139 About Bhallika, Etc. Bhallikādisutta

“Mendicants, having six qualities the householders Bhallika … Sudatta Anāthapiṇḍika … Citta of Macchikāsaṇḍa … Hatthaka of Āḷavī … Mahānāma the Sakyan … Ugga of Vesālī … Uggata … Sūrambaṭṭha … Jīvaka Komārabhacca … Nakula’s father … Tavakaṇṇika … Pūraṇa … Isidatta … Sandhāna … Vijaya … Vijayamāhita … Meṇḍaka … the lay followers Vāseṭṭha … Ariṭṭha … and Sāragga are certain about the Realized One, see freedom from death and live having realized freedom from death. What six? Experiential confidence in the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, and noble ethics, knowledge, and freedom. Having these six qualities the lay follower Sāragga is certain about the Realized One, sees freedom from death and lives having realized freedom from death.”

The Chapter on Warm-hearted

AN 6.11 Warm-hearted (1st) Paṭhamasāraṇīyasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six warm-hearted qualities. What six?

Firstly, a mendicant consistently treats their spiritual companions with bodily kindness, both in public and in private. This is a warm-hearted quality.

Furthermore, a mendicant consistently treats their spiritual companions with verbal kindness, both in public and in private. This too is a warm-hearted quality.

Furthermore, a mendicant consistently treats their spiritual companions with mental kindness …

Furthermore, a mendicant shares without reservation any material things they have gained by legitimate means, even the food placed in the alms-bowl, using them in common with their ethical spiritual companions. This too is a warm-hearted quality.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives according to the precepts shared with their spiritual companions, both in public and in private. Those precepts are intact, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. This too is a warm-hearted quality.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives according to the view shared with their spiritual companions, both in public and in private. That view is noble and emancipating, and delivers one who applies it to the complete ending of suffering. This too is a warm-hearted quality.

These are the six warm-hearted qualities.”

AN 6.12 Warm-hearted (2nd) Dutiyasāraṇīyasutta

“Mendicants, these six warm-hearted qualities make for fondness and respect, conducing to inclusion, harmony, and unity, without dispute. What six?

Firstly, a mendicant consistently treats their spiritual companions with bodily kindness, both in public and in private. This warm-hearted quality makes for fondness and respect, conducing to inclusion, harmony, and unity, without dispute.

Furthermore, a mendicant consistently treats their spiritual companions with verbal kindness …

Furthermore, a mendicant consistently treats their spiritual companions with mental kindness …

Furthermore, a mendicant shares without reservation any material things they have gained by legitimate means, even the food placed in the alms-bowl, using them in common with their ethical spiritual companions. This too is a warm-hearted quality.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives according to the precepts shared with their spiritual companions, both in public and in private. Those precepts are intact, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. This too is a warm-hearted quality.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives according to the view shared with their spiritual companions, both in public and in private. That view is noble and emancipating, and delivers one who applies it to the complete ending of suffering. This warm-hearted quality makes for fondness and respect, conducing to inclusion, harmony, and unity, without dispute.

These six warm-hearted qualities make for fondness and respect, conducing to inclusion, harmony, and unity, without quarreling.”

AN 6.13 Elements of Escape Nissāraṇīyasutta

“Mendicants, there are these six elements of escape. What six?

Take a mendicant who says: ‘I’ve developed the heart’s release by love. I’ve cultivated it, made it my vehicle and my basis, kept it up, consolidated it, and properly implemented it. Yet somehow ill will still occupies my mind.’ They should be told, ‘Not so, venerable! Don’t say that. Don’t misrepresent the Buddha, for misrepresentation of the Buddha is not good. And the Buddha would not say that. It’s impossible, reverend, it cannot happen that the heart’s release by love has been developed and properly implemented, yet somehow ill will still occupies the mind. For it is the heart’s release by love that is the escape from ill will.’

Take another mendicant who says: ‘I’ve developed the heart’s release by compassion. I’ve cultivated it, made it my vehicle and my basis, kept it up, consolidated it, and properly implemented it. Yet somehow the thought of harming still occupies my mind.’ They should be told, ‘Not so, venerable! … For it is the heart’s release by compassion that is the escape from thoughts of harming.’

Take another mendicant who says: ‘I’ve developed the heart’s release by rejoicing. I’ve cultivated it, made it my vehicle and my basis, kept it up, consolidated it, and properly implemented it. Yet somehow discontent still occupies my mind.’ They should be told, ‘Not so, venerable! … For it is the heart’s release by rejoicing that is the escape from discontent.’

Take another mendicant who says: ‘I’ve developed the heart’s release by equanimity. I’ve cultivated it, made it my vehicle and my basis, kept it up, consolidated it, and properly implemented it. Yet somehow desire still occupies my mind.’ They should be told, ‘Not so, venerable! … For it is the heart’s release by equanimity that is the escape from desire.’

Take another mendicant who says: ‘I’ve developed the signless release of the heart. I’ve cultivated it, made it my vehicle and my basis, kept it up, consolidated it, and properly implemented it. Yet somehow my consciousness still follows after signs.’ They should be told, ‘Not so, venerable! … For it is the signless release of the heart that is the escape from all signs.’

Take another mendicant who says: ‘I’m rid of the conceit “I am”. And I don’t regard anything as “I am this”. Yet somehow the dart of doubt and indecision still occupies my mind.’ They should be told, ‘Not so, venerable! Don’t say that. Don’t misrepresent the Buddha, for misrepresentation of the Buddha is not good. And the Buddha would not say that. It’s impossible, reverend, it cannot happen that the conceit “I am” has been done away with, and nothing is regarded as “I am this”, yet somehow the dart of doubt and indecision still occupies the mind. For it is the uprooting of the conceit “I am” that is the escape from the dart of doubt and indecision.’

These are the six elements of escape.”

AN 6.14 A Good Death Bhaddakasutta

There Sāriputta addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Sāriputta said this:

“A mendicant lives life so as to not have a good death. And how do they live life so as to not have a good death?

Take a mendicant who relishes work, talk, sleep, company, closeness, and proliferation. They love these things and like to relish them. A mendicant who lives life like this does not have a good death. This is called a mendicant who enjoys substantial reality, who hasn’t given up substantial reality to rightly make an end of suffering.

A mendicant lives life so as to have a good death. And how do they live life so as to have a good death?

Take a mendicant who doesn’t relish work, talk, sleep, company, closeness, and proliferation. They don’t love these things or like to relish them. A mendicant who lives life like this has a good death. This is called a mendicant who delights in extinguishment, who has given up substantial reality to rightly make an end of suffering.

A beast who likes to proliferate,
enjoying proliferation,
fails to win extinguishment,
the supreme sanctuary from the yoke.

But one who gives up proliferation,
enjoying the state of non-proliferation,
wins extinguishment,
the supreme sanctuary from the yoke.”

AN 6.15 Regret Anutappiyasutta

There Sāriputta addressed the mendicants:

“As a mendicant makes their bed, so they must lie in it, and die tormented by regrets. And how do they die tormented by regrets?

Take a mendicant who relishes work, talk, sleep, company, closeness, and proliferation. They love these things and like to relish them. A mendicant who makes their bed like this must lie in it, and die tormented by regrets. This is called a mendicant who enjoys substantial reality, who hasn’t given up substantial reality to rightly make an end of suffering.

As a mendicant makes their bed, so they must lie in it, and die free of regrets. And how do they die free of regrets?

Take a mendicant who doesn’t relish work, talk, sleep, company, closeness, and proliferation. They don’t love these things or like to relish them. A mendicant who makes their bed like this must lie in it, and die free of regrets. This is called a mendicant who delights in extinguishment, who has given up substantial reality to rightly make an end of suffering.

A beast who likes to proliferate,
enjoying proliferation,
fails to win extinguishment,
the supreme sanctuary from the yoke.

But one who gives up proliferation,
enjoying the state of non-proliferation,
wins extinguishment,
the supreme sanctuary from the yoke.”

AN 6.16 Nakula’s Father Nakulapitusutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Bhaggas at Crocodile’s Bellow, in the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood. Now at that time the householder Nakula’s father was sick, suffering, gravely ill. Then the housewife Nakula’s mother said to him:

“Householder, don’t pass away with concerns. Such concern is suffering, and it’s criticized by the Buddha. Householder, you might think: ‘When I’ve gone, the housewife Nakula’s mother won’t be able to provide for the children and keep up the household carpets.’ But you should not see it like this. I’m skilled at spinning cotton and carding wool. I’m able to provide for the children and keep up the household carpets. So householder, don’t pass away with concerns …

Householder, you might think: ‘When I’ve gone, the housewife Nakula’s mother will take another husband.’ But you should not see it like this. Both you and I know that we have remained chaste while at home for the past sixteen years. So householder, don’t pass away with concerns …

Householder, you might think: ‘When I’ve gone, the housewife Nakula’s mother won’t want to see the Buddha and his Saṅgha of mendicants.’ But you should not see it like this. When you’ve gone, I’ll want to see the Buddha and his mendicant Saṅgha even more. So householder, don’t pass away with concerns …

Householder, you might think: ‘The housewife Nakula’s mother won’t fulfill ethics.’ But you should not see it like this. I am one of those white-robed disciples of the Buddha who fulfills their ethics. For whoever doubts this, that Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha is staying in the land of the Bhaggas at Crocodile’s Bellow, in the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood. Let them approach him and ask. So householder, don’t pass away with concerns …

Householder, you might think: ‘The housewife Nakula’s mother doesn’t have internal serenity of heart.’ But you should not see it like this. I am one of those white-robed disciples of the Buddha who has internal serenity of heart. For whoever doubts this, that Blessed One is staying in the land of the Bhaggas at Crocodile’s Bellow, in the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood. Let them approach him and ask. So householder, don’t pass away with concerns …

Householder, you might think: ‘The housewife Nakula’s mother has not found a footing, a firm footing, and solace in this teaching and training. She has not gone beyond doubt, got rid of indecision, and gained assurance. And she’s not independent of others in the Teacher’s instructions.’ But you should not see it like this. I am one of those white-robed disciples of the Buddha who has found a footing, a firm footing, and solace in this teaching and training. I have gone beyond doubt, got rid of indecision, and gained assurance. And I am independent of others in the Teacher’s instructions. For whoever doubts this, that Blessed One is staying in the land of the Bhaggas at Crocodile’s Bellow, in the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood. Let them approach him and ask. So householder, don’t pass away with concerns. Such concern is suffering, and it’s criticized by the Buddha.”

And then, as Nakula’s mother was giving this advice to Nakula’s father, his illness died down on the spot. And that’s how Nakula’s father recovered from that illness. Soon after recovering, leaning on a staff he went to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“You’re fortunate, householder, so very fortunate, to have the housewife Nakula’s mother advise and instruct you out of kindness and sympathy.

She is one of those white-robed disciples of the Buddha who fulfills their ethics.

She is one of those white-robed disciples of the Buddha who has internal serenity of heart.

She is one of those white-robed disciples of the Buddha who has found a footing, a firm footing, and solace in this teaching and training. She has gone beyond doubt, got rid of indecision, and gained assurance. And she is independent of others in the Teacher’s instructions.

You’re fortunate, householder, so very fortunate, to have the housewife Nakula’s mother advise and instruct you out of kindness and sympathy.”

AN 6.17 Sleep Soppasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Then in the late afternoon, the Buddha came out of retreat, went to the assembly hall, and sat down on the seat spread out. Venerable Sāriputta also came out of retreat, went to the assembly hall, bowed to the Buddha and sat down to one side. Venerables Mahāmoggallāna, Mahākassapa, Mahākaccāna, Mahākoṭṭhita, Mahācunda, Mahākappina, Anuruddha, Revata, and Ānanda did the same. The Buddha spent much of the night sitting in meditation, then rose from his seat and entered his dwelling. And soon after the Buddha left those venerables each went to their own dwelling.

But those mendicants who were junior, recently gone forth, newly come to this teaching and training slept until the sun came up, snoring. The Buddha saw them doing this, with his clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman. He went to the assembly hall, sat down on the seat spread out, and addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, where is Sāriputta? Where are Mahāmoggallāna, Mahākassapa, Mahākaccāna, Mahākoṭṭhita, Mahācunda, Mahākappina, Anuruddha, Revata, and Ānanda? Where have these senior disciples gone?”

“Soon after the Buddha left those venerables each went to their own dwelling.”

“So, mendicants, when the senior mendicants left, why did you sleep until the sun came up, snoring?

What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of an anointed aristocratic king who rules his whole life, dear and beloved to the country, while indulging in the pleasures of sleeping, lying down, and drowsing as much as he likes?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing.

What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of an appointed official … a hereditary official … a general … a village chief … or a guild head who runs the guild his whole life, dear and beloved to the guild, while indulging in the pleasures of sleeping, lying down, and drowsing as much as he likes?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing.

What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of an ascetic or brahmin who indulges in the pleasures of sleeping, lying down, and drowsing as much as they like? Their sense doors are unguarded, they eat too much, they’re not dedicated to wakefulness, they’re unable to discern skillful qualities, and they don’t pursue the development of the qualities on the side of awakening in the evening and toward dawn. Yet they realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing.

So you should train like this: ‘We will guard our sense doors, eat in moderation, be dedicated to wakefulness, discern skillful qualities, and pursue the development of the qualities on the side of awakening in the evening and toward dawn.’ That’s how you should train.”

AN 6.18 A Fish Dealer Macchabandhasutta

At one time the Buddha was wandering in the land of the Kosalans together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants.

While walking along the road he saw a fish dealer in a certain spot selling fish that he had killed himself. Seeing this he left the road, sat at the root of a tree on the seat spread out, and addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, do you see that fish dealer selling fish that he killed himself?”

“Yes, sir.”

“What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of a fish dealer selling fish that he killed himself who, by means of that work and livelihood, got to travel by elephant, horse, chariot, or vehicle, or to enjoy wealth, or to live off a large fortune?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing. Why is that? Because when the fish are led to the slaughter he regards them with bad intentions.

What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of a butcher of cattle selling cattle that he killed himself who, by means of that work and livelihood, got to travel by elephant, horse, chariot, or vehicle, or to enjoy wealth, or to live off a large fortune?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing. Why is that? Because when the cattle are led to the slaughter he regards them with bad intentions.

What do you think, mendicants? Have you ever seen or heard of a butcher of sheep … a butcher of pigs … a butcher of poultry … or a deer-hunter selling deer which he killed himself who, by means of that work and livelihood, got to travel by elephant, horse, chariot, or vehicle, or to enjoy wealth, or to live off a large fortune?”

“No, sir.”

“Good, mendicants! I too have never seen or heard of such a thing. Why is that? Because when the deer are led to the slaughter he regards them with bad intentions.

By regarding even animals led to the slaughter with bad intentions he did not get to travel by elephant, horse, chariot, or vehicle, or to enjoy wealth, or to live off a large fortune. How much worse is someone who regards human beings brought to the slaughter with bad intentions! This will be for their lasting harm and suffering. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.”

AN 6.19 Mindfulness of Death (1st) Paṭhamamaraṇassatisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying at Ñātika in the brick house. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, when mindfulness of death is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination. But do you develop mindfulness of death?”

When he said this, one of the mendicants said to the Buddha, “Sir, I develop mindfulness of death.”

“But mendicant, how do you develop it?”

“In this case, sir, I think: ‘Oh, if I’d only live for another day and night, I’d focus on the Buddha’s instructions and I could really achieve a lot.’ That’s how I develop mindfulness of death.”

Another mendicant said to the Buddha, “Sir, I too develop mindfulness of death.”

“But mendicant, how do you develop it?”

“In this case, sir, I think: ‘Oh, if I’d only live for another day, I’d focus on the Buddha’s instructions and I could really achieve a lot.’ That’s how I develop mindfulness of death.”

Another mendicant said to the Buddha, “Sir, I too develop mindfulness of death.”

“But mendicant, how do you develop it?”

“In this case, sir, I think: ‘Oh, if I’d only live as long as it takes to eat a meal of almsfood, I’d focus on the Buddha’s instructions and I could really achieve a lot.’ That’s how I develop mindfulness of death.”

Another mendicant said to the Buddha, “Sir, I too develop mindfulness of death.”

“But mendicant, how do you develop it?”

“In this case, sir, I think: ‘Oh, if I’d only live as long as it takes to chew and swallow four or five mouthfuls, I’d focus on the Buddha’s instructions and I could really achieve a lot.’ That’s how I develop mindfulness of death.”

Another mendicant said to the Buddha, “Sir, I too develop mindfulness of death.”

“But mendicant, how do you develop it?”

“In this case, sir, I think: ‘Oh, if I’d only live as long as it takes to chew and swallow a single mouthful, I’d focus on the Buddha’s instructions and I could really achieve a lot.’ That’s how I develop mindfulness of death.”

Another mendicant said to the Buddha, “Sir, I too develop mindfulness of death.”

“But mendicant, how do you develop it?”

“In this case, sir, I think: ‘Oh, if I’d only live as long as it takes to breathe out after breathing in, or to breathe in after breathing out, I’d focus on the Buddha’s instructions and I could really achieve a lot.’ That’s how I develop mindfulness of death.”

When this was said, the Buddha said to those mendicants:

“As to the mendicants who develop mindfulness of death by wishing to live for a day and night … or to live for a day … or to live as long as it takes to eat a meal of almsfood … or to live as long as it takes to chew and swallow four or five mouthfuls—these are called mendicants who live negligently. They slackly develop mindfulness of death for the ending of defilements.

But as to the mendicants who develop mindfulness of death by wishing to live as long as it takes to chew and swallow a single mouthful … or to live as long as it takes to breathe out after breathing in, or to breathe in after breathing out—these are called mendicants who live diligently. They keenly develop mindfulness of death for the ending of defilements.

So you should train like this: ‘We will live diligently. We will keenly develop mindfulness of death for the ending of defilements.’ That’s how you should train.”

AN 6.20 Mindfulness of Death (2nd) Dutiyamaraṇassatisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying at Ñātika in the brick house. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, when mindfulness of death is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination. And how is mindfulness of death developed and cultivated to be very fruitful and beneficial, with freedom from death as its objective and culmination?

As day passes by and night draws close, a mendicant reflects: ‘I might die of many causes. A snake might bite me, or a scorpion or centipede might sting me. And if I died from that it would be an obstacle to my progress. Or I might stumble off a cliff, or get food poisoning, or suffer a disturbance of bile, phlegm, or piercing winds. And if I died from that it would be an obstacle to my progress.’ That mendicant should reflect: ‘Are there any bad, unskillful qualities that I haven’t given up, which might be an obstacle to my progress if I die tonight?’

Suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows that there are such bad, unskillful qualities. Then in order to give them up they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. Suppose your clothes or head were on fire. In order to extinguish it, you’d apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. In the same way, in order to give up those bad, unskillful qualities, that mendicant should apply extraordinary enthusiasm …

But suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows that there are no such bad, unskillful qualities. Then that mendicant should meditate with rapture and joy, training day and night in skillful qualities.

Or else, as night passes by and day draws close, a mendicant reflects: ‘I might die of many causes. A snake might bite me, or a scorpion or centipede might sting me. And if I died from that it would be an obstacle to my progress. Or I might stumble off a cliff, or get food poisoning, or suffer a disturbance of bile, phlegm, or piercing winds. And if I died from that it would be an obstacle to my progress.’ That mendicant should reflect: ‘Are there any bad, unskillful qualities that I haven’t given up, which might be an obstacle to my progress if I die today?’

Suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows that there are such bad, unskillful qualities. Then in order to give them up they should apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. Suppose your clothes or head were on fire. In order to extinguish it, you’d apply extraordinary enthusiasm, effort, zeal, vigor, perseverance, mindfulness, and situational awareness. In the same way, in order to give up those bad, unskillful qualities, that mendicant should apply extraordinary enthusiasm …

But suppose that, upon checking, a mendicant knows that there are no such bad, unskillful qualities. Then that mendicant should meditate with rapture and joy, training day and night in skillful qualities.

Mindfulness of death, when developed and cultivated in this way, is very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.”

The Chapter on Coolness

AN 6.85 Coolness Sītibhāvasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with six qualities can’t realize supreme coolness. What six? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t keep their mind in check when they should. They don’t exert their mind when they should. They don’t encourage the mind when they should. They don’t watch over the mind with equanimity when they should. They have inferior convictions. They delight in substantial reality. A mendicant with these six qualities can’t realize supreme coolness.

A mendicant with six qualities can realize supreme coolness. What six? It’s when a mendicant keeps their mind in check when they should. They exert their mind when they should. They encourage the mind when they should. They watch over the mind with equanimity when they should. They have excellent convictions. They delight in extinguishment. A mendicant with these six qualities can realize supreme coolness.”

AN 6.86 Obstacles Āvaraṇasutta

“Mendicants, someone with six qualities is unable to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities even when listening to the true teaching. What six? They’re obstructed by deeds, defilements, or results. And they’re faithless, unenthusiastic, and witless. Someone with these six qualities is unable to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities, even when listening to the true teaching.

Someone with six qualities is able to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities when listening to the true teaching. What six? They’re not obstructed by deeds, defilements, or results. And they’re faithful, enthusiastic, and wise. Someone with these six qualities is able to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities when listening to the true teaching.”

AN 6.87 A Murderer Voropitasutta

“Mendicants, someone with six qualities is unable to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities even when listening to the true teaching. What six? They murder their mother or father or a perfected one. They maliciously shed the blood of a Realized One. They cause a schism in the Saṅgha. They’re witless, dull, and idiotic. Someone with these six qualities is unable to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities, even when listening to the true teaching.

Someone with six qualities is able to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities when listening to the true teaching. What six? They don’t murder their mother or father or a perfected one. They don’t maliciously shed the blood of a Realized One. They don’t cause a schism in the Saṅgha. They’re wise, bright, and clever. Someone with these six qualities is able to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities when listening to the true teaching.”

AN 6.88 Wanting to Listen Sussūsatisutta

“Mendicants, someone with six qualities is unable to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities even when listening to the true teaching. What six? When the teaching and practice proclaimed by the Realized One is being taught they don’t want to listen. They don’t actively listen or try to understand. They learn the incorrect meaning and neglect the correct meaning. They accept views that contradict the teaching. Someone with these six qualities is unable to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities, even when listening to the true teaching.

Someone with six qualities is able to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities when listening to the true teaching. What six? When the teaching and practice proclaimed by the Realized One is being taught they want to listen. They actively listen and try to understand. They learn the correct meaning and neglect the incorrect meaning. They accept views that conform with the teaching. Someone with these six qualities is able to step into the sure path with regard to skillful qualities when listening to the true teaching.”

AN 6.89 Not Giving Up Appahāyasutta

“Mendicants, without giving up six things you can’t become accomplished in view. What six? Substantialist view, doubt, misapprehension of precepts and observances, and forms of greed, hate, and delusion that lead to rebirth in places of loss. Without giving up these six things you can’t become accomplished in view.

After giving up six things you can become accomplished in view. What six? Substantialist view, doubt, misapprehension of precepts and observances, and forms of greed, hate, and delusion that lead to rebirth in places of loss. After giving up these six things you can become accomplished in view.”

AN 6.90 Given Up Pahīnasutta

“Mendicants, an individual accomplished in view has given up these six things. What six? Substantialist view, doubt, misapprehension of precepts and observances, and forms of greed, hate, and delusion that lead to rebirth in places of loss. An individual accomplished in view has given up these six things.”

AN 6.91 Can’t Give Rise Abhabbasutta

“Mendicants, an individual accomplished in view can’t give rise to six things. What six? Substantialist view, doubt, misapprehension of precepts and observances, and forms of greed, hate, and delusion that lead to rebirth in places of loss. An individual accomplished in view can’t give rise to these six things.”

AN 6.92 Things That Can’t Be Done (1st) Paṭhamaabhabbaṭṭhānasutta

“Mendicants, these six things can’t be done. What six? An individual accomplished in view can’t live disrespectful and irreverent toward the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, or the training. They can’t establish their belief on unreliable grounds. And they can’t generate an eighth rebirth. These are the six things that can’t be done.”

AN 6.93 Things That Can’t Be Done (2nd) Dutiyaabhabbaṭṭhānasutta

“Mendicants, these six things can’t be done. What six? An individual accomplished in view can’t take conditions to be permanent. They cannot take conditions to be happiness. They cannot take anything to be the self. They can’t do deeds with fixed result in the next life. They can’t fall back on purification through boisterous, superstitious rites. They can’t seek outside of the Buddhist community for those worthy of religious donations. These are the six things that can’t be done.”

AN 6.94 Things That Can’t Be Done (3rd) Tatiyaabhabbaṭṭhānasutta

“Mendicants, these six things can’t be done. What six? An individual accomplished in view can’t murder their mother or father or a perfected one. They can’t maliciously shed the blood of the Realized One. They can’t cause a schism in the Saṅgha. They can’t dedicate themselves to another teacher. These are the six things that can’t be done.”

AN 6.95 Things That Can’t Be Done (4th) Catutthaabhabbaṭṭhānasutta

“Mendicants, these six things can’t be done. What six? An individual accomplished in view can’t fall back on the idea that pleasure and pain are made by oneself, or that they’re made by another, or that they’re made by both. Nor can they fall back on the idea that pleasure and pain arise anomalously, not made by oneself, by another, or by both. Why is that? It is because an individual accomplished in view has clearly seen causes and the phenomena that arise from causes. These are the six things that can’t be done.”

The Chapter on Triads

AN 6.107 Greed Rāgasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? Greed, hate, and delusion. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop the perception of ugliness to give up greed, love to give up hate, and wisdom to give up delusion. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

AN 6.108 Bad Conduct Duccaritasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? Bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop good bodily conduct to give up bad bodily conduct, good verbal conduct to give up bad verbal conduct, and good mental conduct to give up bad mental conduct. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

AN 6.109 Thoughts Vitakkasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? Sensual, malicious, and cruel thoughts. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop thoughts of renunciation to give up sensual thoughts, thoughts of good will to give up malicious thoughts, and thoughts of harmlessness to give up cruel thoughts. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

AN 6.110 Perceptions Saññāsutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? Sensual, malicious, and cruel perceptions. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop perceptions of renunciation to give up sensual perceptions, perceptions of good will to give up malicious perceptions, and perceptions of harmlessness to give up cruel perceptions. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

AN 6.111 Elements Dhātusutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? The elements of sensuality, malice, and cruelty. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop the element of renunciation to give up the element of sensuality, the element of good will to give up the element of malice, and the element of harmlessness to give up the element of cruelty. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

AN 6.112 Gratification Assādasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? The view that things are gratifying, the theory of self, and wrong view. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop the perception of impermanence to give up the view that things are gratifying; the perception of not-self to give up the theory of self; and right view to give up wrong view. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

AN 6.113 Discontent Aratisutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? Discontent, cruelty, and unprincipled conduct. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop rejoicing to give up discontent, harmlessness to give up cruelty, and principled conduct to give up unprincipled conduct. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

AN 6.114 Contentment Santuṭṭhitāsutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? Lack of contentment, lack of situational awareness, and having many wishes. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop contentment to give up lack of contentment, situational awareness to give up lack of situational awareness, and having few wishes to give up having many wishes. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

AN 6.115 Hard to Admonish Dovacassatāsutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? Being hard to admonish, bad friendship, and a scattered mind. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop being easy to admonish to give up being hard to admonish, good friendship to give up bad friendship, and mindfulness of breathing to give up a scattered mind. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

AN 6.116 Restlessness Uddhaccasutta

“Mendicants, there are these three things. What three? Restlessness, lack of restraint, and negligence. These are the three things. To give up these three things you should develop three things. What three? You should develop serenity to give up restlessness, restraint to give up lack of restraint, and diligence to give up negligence. These are the three things you should develop to give up those three things.”

The Chapter on Worthy of Offerings

AN 7.95 Observing Impermanence in the Eye ~

“Mendicants, these seven individuals are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world. What seven?

First, take an individual who meditates observing impermanence in the eye. They perceive impermanence and experience impermanence. Constantly, continually, and without interruption, they apply the mind and fathom with wisdom. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. This is the first individual who is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.

Next, take an individual who meditates observing impermanence in the eye. … Their defilements and their life come to an end at exactly the same time. This is the second individual who is worthy of offerings …

Next, take an individual who meditates observing impermanence in the eye. … With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished upon landing. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished without extra effort. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished with extra effort. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm. … This is the seventh individual.

These are the seven individuals who are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 7.96–614 Observing Suffering in the Eye, Etc. ~

“Mendicants, these seven individuals are worthy of offerings … What seven?

First, take an individual who meditates observing suffering in the eye. … observing not-self in the eye. … observing ending in the eye. … observing vanishing in the eye. … observing fading away in the eye. … observing cessation in the eye. … observing letting go in the eye. …

… ear … nose … tongue … body … mind …

… sights … sounds … smells … tastes … touches … ideas …

… eye consciousness … ear consciousness … nose consciousness … tongue consciousness … body consciousness … mind consciousness …

… eye contact … ear contact … nose contact … tongue contact … body contact … mind contact …

… feeling born of eye contact … feeling born of ear contact … feeling born of nose contact … feeling born of tongue contact … feeling born of body contact … feeling born of mind contact …

perception of sights … perception of sounds … perception of smells … perception of tastes … perception of touches … perception of ideas …

… intention regarding sights … intention regarding sounds … intention regarding smells … intention regarding tastes … intention regarding touches … intention regarding ideas …

… craving for sights … craving for sounds … craving for smells … craving for tastes … craving for touches … craving for ideas …

… thoughts about sights … thoughts about sounds … thoughts about smells … thoughts about tastes … thoughts about touches … thoughts about ideas …

… considerations regarding sights … considerations regarding sounds … considerations regarding smells … considerations regarding tastes … considerations regarding touches … considerations regarding ideas …

… meditates observing impermanence in the five aggregates … the aggregate of form … the aggregate of feeling … the aggregate of perception … the aggregate of choices … the aggregate of consciousness … meditates observing suffering … not-self … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … letting go …”

The Chapter on Tendencies

AN 7.11 Underlying Tendencies (1st) Paṭhamaanusayasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven underlying tendencies. What seven? The underlying tendencies of sensual desire, aversion, views, doubt, conceit, desire for continued existence, and ignorance. These are the seven underlying tendencies.”

AN 7.12 Underlying Tendencies (2nd) Dutiyaanusayasutta

“Mendicants, the spiritual life is lived to give up and cut out these seven underlying tendencies. What seven? The underlying tendencies of sensual desire, aversion, views, doubt, conceit, desire to be reborn, and ignorance. The spiritual life is lived to give up and cut out these seven underlying tendencies.

When a mendicant has given up the underlying tendencies of sensual desire, repulsion, views, doubt, conceit, desire to be reborn, and ignorance—cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so they are unable to arise in the future—they’re called a mendicant who has cut off craving, cast off the fetters, and by rightly comprehending conceit has made an end of suffering.”

AN 7.13 A Family Kulasutta

“Mendicants, visiting a family with seven factors is not worthwhile, or if you’ve already arrived, sitting down is not worthwhile. What seven? They don’t politely rise, bow, or offer a seat. They hide what they have. Even when they have much they give little. Even when they have fine things they give coarse things. They give carelessly, not carefully. Visiting a family with these seven factors is not worthwhile, or if you’ve already arrived, sitting down is not worthwhile.

Visiting a family with seven factors is worthwhile, or if you’ve already arrived, sitting down is worthwhile. What seven? They politely rise, bow, and offer a seat. They don’t hide what they have. When they have much they give much. When they have refined things they give refined things. They give carefully, not carelessly. Visiting a family with these seven factors is worthwhile, or if you’ve already arrived, sitting down is worthwhile.”

AN 7.14 Individuals Puggalasutta

“Mendicants, these seven individuals are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world. What seven? The one freed both ways, the one freed by wisdom, the direct witness, the one attained to view, the one freed by faith, the follower of teachings, and the follower by faith. These are the seven individuals who are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 7.15 A Simile With Water Udakūpamāsutta

“Mendicants, these seven individuals found in the world are like those in water.

What seven? One individual sinks under once and stays under. One individual rises up then sinks under. One individual rises up then stays put. One individual rises up then sees and discerns. One individual rises up then crosses over. One individual rises up then finds a foothold. One individual has risen up, crossed over, and gone to the far shore, a brahmin who stands on solid ground.

And what kind of individual sinks under once and stays under? It’s the kind of individual who has absolutely dark, unskillful qualities. This kind of individual sinks under once and stays under.

And what kind of individual rises up then sinks under? It’s the kind of individual who, rising up, thinks: ‘It’s good to have faith, conscience, prudence, energy, and wisdom regarding skillful qualities.’ However their faith, conscience, prudence, energy, and wisdom don’t last or grow, but dwindle away. This kind of individual rises up then sinks under.

And what kind of individual rises up then stays put? It’s the kind of individual who, rising up, thinks: ‘It’s good to have faith, conscience, prudence, energy, and wisdom regarding skillful qualities.’ And their faith, conscience, prudence, energy, and wisdom lasts, neither dwindling nor growing. This kind of individual rises up then stays put.

And what kind of individual rises up then sees and discerns? It’s the kind of individual who, rising up, thinks: ‘It’s good to have faith, conscience, prudence, energy, and wisdom regarding skillful qualities.’ With the ending of three fetters they’re a stream-enterer, not liable to be reborn in the underworld, assured, destined for awakening. This kind of individual rises up then sees and discerns.

And what kind of individual rises up then crosses over? It’s the kind of individual who, rising up, thinks: ‘It’s good to have faith, conscience, prudence, energy, and wisdom regarding skillful qualities.’ With the ending of three fetters, and the weakening of greed, hate, and delusion, they’re a once-returner. They come back to this world once only, then make an end of suffering. This kind of individual rises up then crosses over.

And what kind of individual rises up then finds a foothold? It’s the kind of individual who, rising up, thinks: ‘It’s good to have faith, conscience, prudence, energy, and wisdom regarding skillful qualities.’ With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. This kind of individual rises up then finds a foothold.

And what kind of individual has risen up, crossed over, and gone to the far shore, a brahmin who stands on solid ground? It’s the kind of individual who, rising up, thinks: ‘It’s good to have faith, conscience, prudence, energy, and wisdom regarding skillful qualities.’ They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. This kind of individual has risen up, crossed over, and gone to the far shore, a brahmin who stands on solid ground.

These seven individuals found in the world are like those in water.”

AN 7.16 Observing Impermanence Aniccānupassīsutta

“Mendicants, these seven individuals are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world. What seven?

First, take an individual who meditates observing impermanence in all conditions. They perceive impermanence and experience impermanence. Constantly, continually, and without interruption, they apply the mind and fathom with wisdom. They’ve realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. This is the first individual.

Next, take an individual who meditates observing impermanence in all conditions. Their defilements and their life come to an end at exactly the same time. This is the second individual.

Next, take an individual who meditates observing impermanence in all conditions. With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished upon landing. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished without extra effort. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished with extra effort. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm. This is the seventh individual.

These are the seven individuals who are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 7.17 Observing Suffering Dukkhānupassīsutta

“Mendicants, these seven individuals are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world. What seven? First, take an individual who meditates observing suffering in all conditions. They perceive suffering and experience suffering. Constantly, continually, and without interruption, they apply the mind and fathom with wisdom. …”

AN 7.18 Observing Not-self Anattānupassīsutta

“First, take an individual who meditates observing not-self in all things. They perceive not-self and experience not-self. Constantly, continually, and without interruption, they apply the mind and fathom with wisdom. …”

AN 7.19 Extinguishment Nibbānasutta

“One meditates observing the happiness in extinguishment. They perceive happiness and experience happiness. Constantly, continually, and without interruption, they apply the mind and fathom with wisdom. They’ve realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. This is the first individual worthy of offerings.

Next, take an individual who meditates observing the happiness in extinguishment. They perceive happiness and experience happiness. Constantly, continually, and without interruption, they apply the mind and fathom with wisdom. Their defilements and their life come to an end at exactly the same time. This is the second individual.

Next, take an individual who meditates observing the happiness in extinguishment. They perceive happiness and experience happiness. Constantly, continually, and without interruption, they apply the mind and fathom with wisdom.

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished upon landing. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished without extra effort. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished with extra effort. …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm. This is the seventh individual.

These are the seven individuals who are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 7.20 Qualifications for Graduation Niddasavatthusutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven qualifications for graduation. What seven? It’s when a mendicant has a keen enthusiasm to undertake the training … to examine the teachings … to get rid of desires … for retreat … to rouse up energy … for mindfulness and alertness … to penetrate theoretically. And they don’t lose these desires in the future. These are the seven qualifications for graduation.”

The Chapter on Deities

AN 7.32 Respect for Diligence Appamādagāravasutta

Then, late at night, a glorious deity, lighting up the entire Jeta’s Grove, went up to the Buddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, these seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant. What seven? Respect for the Teacher, for the teaching, for the Saṅgha, for the training, for immersion, for diligence, and for hospitality. These seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant.”

That is what that deity said, and the Teacher concurred. Then that deity, knowing that the Teacher concurred, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before vanishing right there.

Then, when the night had passed, the Buddha told the mendicants all that had happened, adding:

“Respect for the Teacher and the teaching,
and keen respect for the Saṅgha;
respect for immersion, being energetic,
and keen respect for the training.

A mendicant who respects diligence
and hospitality
can’t decline,
and has drawn near to extinguishment.”

AN 7.33 Respect for Conscience Hirigāravasutta

“Mendicants, tonight, a glorious deity, lighting up the entire Jeta’s Grove, came to me, bowed, stood to one side, and said to me: ‘Sir, these seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant. What seven? Respect for the Teacher, for the teaching, for the Saṅgha, for the training, for immersion, for conscience, and for prudence. These seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant.’

That is what that deity said. Then he bowed and respectfully circled me, keeping me on his right side, before vanishing right there.

One respectful of the Teacher and the teaching,
keenly respecting the Saṅgha;
respecting immersion, being energetic,
and keenly respecting the training;

endowed with conscience and prudence,
reverential and respectful—
it is impossible for them to decline;
they have drawn near to extinguishment.”

AN 7.34 Easy to Admonish (1st) Paṭhamasovacassatāsutta

“Mendicants, tonight a deity … said to me: ‘Sir, these seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant. What seven? Respect for the Teacher, for the teaching, for the Saṅgha, for the training, for immersion; being easy to admonish, and good friendship. These seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant.’

That is what that deity said. Then he bowed and respectfully circled me, keeping me on his right side, before vanishing right there.

Respect for the Teacher and the teaching,
and keen respect for the Saṅgha;
respecting immersion, being energetic,
and keen respect for the training.

One with good friends, easy to admonish,
reverential and respectful,
can’t decline,
and has drawn near to extinguishment.”

AN 7.35 Easy to Admonish (2nd) Dutiyasovacassatāsutta

“Mendicants, tonight a deity … said to me: ‘Sir, these seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant. What seven? Respect for the Teacher, for the teaching, for the Saṅgha, for the training, for immersion; being easy to admonish, and good friendship. These seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant.’

That is what that deity said. Then he bowed and respectfully circled me, keeping me on his right side, before vanishing right there.”

When he said this, Venerable Sāriputta said to the Buddha:

“Sir, this is how I understand the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement.

It’s when a mendicant personally respects the Teacher and praises such respect. And they encourage other mendicants who lack such respect to respect the Teacher. And they praise other mendicants who respect the Teacher at the right time, truthfully and correctly.

They personally respect the teaching …

They personally respect the Saṅgha …

They personally respect the training …

They personally respect immersion …

They are personally easy to admonish …

They personally have good friends, and praise such friendship. And they encourage other mendicants who lack good friends to develop good friendship. And they praise other mendicants who have good friends at the right time, truthfully and correctly.

That’s how I understand the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! It’s good that you understand the detailed meaning of what I’ve said in brief like this.

It’s when a mendicant personally respects the Teacher … And they encourage other mendicants who lack such respect to respect the Teacher. And they praise other mendicants who respect the Teacher at the right time, truthfully and correctly.

They personally respect the teaching …

They personally respect the Saṅgha …

They personally respect the training …

They personally respect immersion …

They are personally easy to admonish …

They personally have good friends, and praise such friendship. And they encourage other mendicants who lack good friends to develop good friendship. And they praise other mendicants who have good friends at the right time, truthfully and correctly.

This is how to see the detailed meaning of what I said in brief.”

AN 7.36 A Friend (1st) Paṭhamamittasutta

“Mendicants, you should associate with a friend who has seven factors. What seven? They give what is hard to give. They do what is hard to do. They endure what is hard to endure. They reveal their secrets to you. They keep your secrets. They don’t abandon you in times of trouble. They don’t look down on you in times of loss. You should associate with a friend who has these seven factors.

A friend gives what is hard to give,
and does what’s hard to do.
They put up with your harsh words,
and with things hard to endure.

They tell you their secrets,
and keep your secrets for you.
They don’t abandon you in times of trouble,
or look down on you in times of loss.

The individual in whom
these things are found is your friend.
If you want to have a friend,
you should keep company with that sort.”

AN 7.37 A Friend (2nd) Dutiyamittasutta

“Mendicants, when a friend has seven qualities you should associate with, accompany, and attend them, even if they drive you away. What seven? They’re liked, agreeable, respected, and admired. They admonish you and they accept admonishment. They speak on deep matters. And they don’t urge you to do bad things. When a friend has these seven qualities you should associate with, accompany, and attend them, even if they drive you away.

They’re liked, respected, and admired,
an admonisher who accepts admonishment,
speaks on deep matters,
and doesn’t urge you to do bad.

The individual in whom
these things are found is your friend.
If you want to have a friend,
benevolent and sympathetic,
then even if they chase you away,
you should keep company with that sort.”

AN 7.38 Textual Analysis (1st) Paṭhamapaṭisambhidāsutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities will soon realize the four kinds of textual analysis and live having achieved them with their own insight. What seven?

It’s when a mendicant truly understands: ‘This is mental sluggishness’.

They truly understand internally constricted mind as ‘internally constricted mind’.

They truly understand externally scattered mind as ‘externally scattered mind’.

They know feelings as they arise, as they remain, and as they go away.

They know perceptions as they arise, as they remain, and as they go away.

They know thoughts as they arise, as they remain, and as they go away.

The patterns of qualities—suitable or unsuitable, inferior or superior, or those with a portion of dark or bright—are properly grasped, focused on, borne in mind, and penetrated with wisdom.

A mendicant with these seven qualities will soon realize the four kinds of textual analysis and live having achieved them with their own insight.”

AN 7.39 Textual Analysis (2nd) Dutiyapaṭisambhidāsutta

“Mendicants, having seven qualities, Sāriputta realized the four kinds of textual analysis and lives having achieved them with his own insight. What seven?

It’s when Sāriputta truly understood: ‘This is mental sluggishness’.

He truly understood internally constricted mind as ‘internally constricted mind’.

He truly understood externally scattered mind as ‘externally scattered mind’.

He knew feelings, perceptions, and thoughts as they arose, as they remained, and as they went away.

The patterns of qualities—suitable or unsuitable, inferior or superior, or those with a portion of dark or bright—were properly grasped, focused on, borne in mind, and penetrated with wisdom.

Having these seven qualities, Sāriputta realized the four kinds of textual analysis and lives having achieved them with his own insight.”

AN 7.40 Mastery of the Mind (1st) Paṭhamavasasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities masters their mind and is not mastered by it. What seven? It’s when a mendicant is skilled at immersion, skilled in entering immersion, skilled in remaining in immersion, skilled in emerging from immersion, skilled in positivity for immersion, skilled in the territory of immersion, and skilled in projecting the mind purified by immersion. A mendicant with these seven qualities masters their mind and is not mastered by it.”

AN 7.41 Mastery of the Mind (2nd) Dutiyavasasutta

“Mendicants, having seven qualities Sāriputta has mastered his mind and is not mastered by it. What seven? Sāriputta is skilled at immersion, skilled in entering immersion, skilled in remaining in immersion, skilled in emerging from immersion, skilled in positivity for immersion, skilled in the territory of immersion, and skilled in projecting the mind purified by immersion. Having these seven qualities Sāriputta has mastered his mind and is not mastered by it.”

AN 7.42 Graduation (1st) Paṭhamaniddasasutta

Then Venerable Sāriputta robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Sāvatthī for alms. Then it occurred to him, “It’s too early to wander for alms in Sāvatthī. Why don’t I visit the monastery for the wanderers of other religions?”

Then he went to the monastery for the wanderers of other religions and exchanged greetings with the wanderers there. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side.

Now at that time while those wanderers of other religions were sitting together this discussion came up among them, “Reverends, anyone who lives the full and pure spiritual life for twelve years is qualified to be called a ‘graduate mendicant’.”

Sāriputta neither approved nor rejected that statement of the wanderers of other religions. He rose from his seat, thinking, “I will learn the meaning of this statement from the Buddha himself.”

Then Sāriputta wandered for alms in Sāvatthī. After the meal, on his return from almsround, he went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened, adding:

“Sir, in this teaching and training can we describe a mendicant as a ‘graduate’ solely because they have completed a certain number of years?”

“No, Sāriputta, we cannot. I make known these seven qualifications for graduation after realizing them with my own insight.

What seven? It’s when a mendicant has a keen enthusiasm to undertake the training … to examine the teachings … to get rid of desires … for retreat … to rouse up energy … for mindfulness and alertness … to penetrate theoretically. And they don’t lose these desires in the future. These are the seven qualifications for graduation that I make known after realizing them with my own insight. A mendicant who has these seven qualifications for graduation is qualified to be called a ‘graduate mendicant’. This is so whether they have lived the full and pure spiritual life for twelve years, twenty-four years, thirty-six years, or forty-eight years.”

AN 7.43 Graduation (2nd) Dutiyaniddasasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery.

Then Venerable Ānanda robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Kosambī for alms. Then it occurred to him, “It’s too early to wander for alms in Kosambī. Why don’t I visit the monastery for the wanderers of other religions?”

Then he went to the monastery for the wanderers of other religions and exchanged greetings with the wanderers there. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side.

Now at that time while those wanderers of other religions were sitting together this discussion came up among them, “Reverends, anyone who lives the full and pure spiritual life for twelve years is qualified to be called a ‘graduate mendicant’.”

Ānanda neither approved nor rejected that statement of the wanderers of other religions. He rose from his seat, thinking, “I will learn the meaning of this statement from the Buddha himself.”

Then Ānanda wandered for alms in Kosambī. After the meal, on his return from almsround, he went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened, adding:

“Sir, in this teaching and training can we describe a mendicant as a ‘graduate’ solely because they have completed a certain number of years?”

“No, Ānanda, we cannot. These are the seven qualifications for graduation that I make known after realizing them with my own insight.

What seven? It’s when someone is faithful, conscientious, prudent, learned, energetic, mindful, and wise. These are the seven qualifications for graduation that I make known after realizing them with my own insight. A mendicant who possesses these seven qualifications for graduation is qualified to be called a ‘graduate mendicant’. This is so whether they have lived the full and pure spiritual life for twelve years, twenty-four years, thirty-six years, or forty-eight years.”

The Second Fifty

The Chapter on the Undeclared Points

AN 7.54 The Undeclared Points Abyākatasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is the cause, what is the reason why a learned noble disciple has no doubts regarding the undeclared points?”

“Mendicant, it’s due to the cessation of views that a learned noble disciple has no doubts regarding the undeclared points. ‘A realized one still exists after death’: this is a misconception. ‘A realized one no longer exists after death’: this is a misconception. ‘A realized one both still exists and no longer exists after death’: this is a misconception. ‘A realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death’: this is a misconception. An unlearned ordinary person doesn’t understand views, their origin, their cessation, or the practice that leads to their cessation. And so their views grow. They’re not freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from suffering, I say.

A learned noble disciple does understand views, their origin, their cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation. And so their views cease. They’re freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re freed from suffering, I say. Knowing and seeing this, a learned noble disciple does not answer: ‘A realized one still exists after death’, ‘A realized one no longer exists after death’, ‘A realized one both still exists and no longer exists after death’, ‘A realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’ Knowing and seeing this, a learned noble disciple does not declare the undeclared points. Knowing and seeing this, a learned noble disciple doesn’t shake, tremble, quake, or get nervous regarding the undeclared points.

‘A realized one still exists after death’: this is just about craving. … it’s just about perception … it’s a conceiving … it’s a proliferation … it’s just about grasping … ‘A realized one still exists after death’: this is a regret. ‘A realized one no longer exists after death’: this is a regret. ‘A realized one both still exists and no longer exists after death’: this is a regret. ‘A realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death’: this is a regret. An unlearned ordinary person doesn’t understand regrets, their origin, their cessation, or the practice that leads to their cessation. And so their regrets grow. They’re not freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from suffering, I say.

A learned noble disciple does understand regrets, their origin, their cessation, and the practice that leads to their cessation. And so their regrets cease. They’re freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re freed from suffering, I say. Knowing and seeing this, a learned noble disciple does not answer: ‘A realized one still exists after death’ … ‘A realized one neither still exists nor no longer exists after death.’ Knowing and seeing this, a learned noble disciple does not declare the undeclared points. Knowing and seeing this, a learned noble disciple doesn’t shake, tremble, quake, or get nervous regarding the undeclared points. This is the cause, this is the reason why a learned noble disciple has no doubts regarding the undeclared points.”

AN 7.55 Places People Are Reborn Purisagatisutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you seven places people are reborn, and complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” the mendicants replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what are the seven places people are reborn?

Take a mendicant who practices like this: ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. It will not be, and it will not be mine. I am giving up what exists, what has come to be.’ They gain equanimity. They’re not attached to life, or to creating a new life. And they see with right wisdom that there is a peaceful state beyond. But they haven’t completely realized that state. They haven’t totally given up the underlying tendencies of conceit, desire for continued existence, and ignorance. With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next. Suppose you struck an iron pot that had been heated all day. Any spark that flew off would be extinguished. In the same way, a mendicant who practices like this … With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next.

Take a mendicant who practices like this: ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. It will not be, and it will not be mine. I am giving up what exists, what has come to be.’ They gain equanimity. They’re not attached to life, or to creating a new life. And they see with right wisdom that there is a peaceful state beyond. But they haven’t totally realized that state. They haven’t completely given up the underlying tendencies of conceit, desire for continued existence, and ignorance. With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next. Suppose you struck an iron pot that had been heated all day. Any spark that flew off and floated away would be extinguished. In the same way, a mendicant who practices like this … With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next.

Take a mendicant who practices like this: ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. …’ With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next. Suppose you struck an iron pot that had been heated all day. Any spark that flew off and floated away would be extinguished before landing. In the same way, a mendicant who practices like this … With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next.

Take a mendicant who practices like this: ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. …’ With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished upon landing. Suppose you struck an iron pot that had been heated all day. Any spark that flew off and floated away would be extinguished upon landing. In the same way, a mendicant who practices like this … ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. …’ With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished upon landing.

Take a mendicant who practices like this: ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. …’ With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished without extra effort. Suppose you struck an iron pot that had been heated all day. Any spark that flew off and floated away would fall on a little heap of grass or twigs. There it would ignite a fire and produce smoke. But the fire would consume the grass or twigs and become extinguished due to not being fed. In the same way, a mendicant who practices like this … ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. …’ With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished without extra effort.

Take a mendicant who practices like this: ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. …’ With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished with extra effort. Suppose you struck an iron pot that had been heated all day. Any spark that flew off and floated away would fall on a large heap of grass or twigs. There it would ignite a fire and produce smoke. But the fire would consume the grass or twigs and become extinguished due to not being fed. In the same way, a mendicant who practices like this … ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. …’ With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished with extra effort.

Take a mendicant who practices like this: ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. It will not be, and it will not be mine. I am giving up what exists, what has come to be.’ They gain equanimity. They’re not attached to life, or to creating a new life. And they see with right wisdom that there is a peaceful state beyond. But they haven’t totally realized that state. They haven’t completely given up the underlying tendencies of conceit, desire for continued existence, and ignorance. With the ending of the five lower fetters they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm. Suppose you struck an iron pot that had been heated all day. Any spark that flew off and floated away would fall on a big heap of grass or twigs. There it would ignite a fire and produce smoke. And after consuming the grass and twigs, the fire would burn up plants and trees until it reached a green field, a roadside, a cliff’s edge, a body of water, or cleared parkland, where it would be extinguished due to not being fed. In the same way, a mendicant who practices like this … ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. …’ With the ending of the five lower fetters they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm. These are the seven places people are reborn.

And what is complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping? Take a mendicant who practices like this: ‘It might not be, and it might not be mine. It will not be, and it will not be mine. I am giving up what exists, what has come to be.’ They gain equanimity. They’re not attached to life, or to creating a new life. And they see with right wisdom that there is a peaceful state beyond. And they have totally realized that state. They’ve completely given up the underlying tendencies of conceit, desire for continued existence, and ignorance. They’ve realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. This is called complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping.

These are the seven places people are reborn, and complete extinguishment with no fuel for grasping.”

AN 7.56 Tissa the Divinity Tissabrahmāsutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain.

Then, late at night, two glorious deities, lighting up the entire Vulture’s Peak, went up to the Buddha, bowed, and stood to one side. One deity said to him, “Sir, these nuns are freed!”

The other deity said to him, “Sir, these nuns are well freed with no residue!”

This is what those deities said, and the Teacher concurred. Then those deities, knowing that the Teacher concurred, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on their right, before vanishing right there.

Then, when the night had passed, the Buddha told the mendicants all that had happened.

Now at that time Venerable Mahāmoggallāna was sitting not far from the Buddha. He thought, “Which gods know whether a person has remainder or not?”

Now, at that time a monk named Tissa had recently passed away and been reborn in a realm of divinity. There they knew that Tissa the Divinity was very mighty and powerful.

And then Venerable Mahāmoggallāna, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, vanished from the Vulture’s Peak and reappeared in that realm of divinity.

Tissa saw Moggallāna coming off in the distance, and said to him, “Come, my good Moggallāna! Welcome, my good Moggallāna! It’s been a long time since you took the opportunity to come here. Sit, my good Moggallāna, here, a seat is ready.”

Moggallāna sat down on the seat spread out. Then Tissa bowed to Moggallāna and sat to one side.

Moggallāna said to him, “Which gods know whether a person has remainder or not?”

“The gods of the Divinity’s host know this.”

“But do all of them know this?”

“No, my good Moggallāna, not all of them.

Those gods of the Divinity’s host who are content with the lifespan of the Divinity, with the beauty, happiness, glory, and sovereignty of the Divinity, and who don’t truly understand any escape beyond: they don’t know this. But those gods of the Divinity’s host who are not content with the lifespan of the Divinity, with the beauty, happiness, glory, and sovereignty of the Divinity, and who do truly understand any escape beyond: they do know this.

Take a mendicant who is freed both ways. The gods know of them: ‘This venerable is freed both ways. As long as their body remains they will be seen by gods and humans. But when their body breaks up gods and humans will see them no more.’ This too is how those gods know whether a person has remainder or not.

Take a mendicant who is freed by wisdom. The gods know of them: ‘This venerable is freed by wisdom. As long as their body remains they will be seen by gods and humans. But when their body breaks up gods and humans will see them no more.’ This too is how those gods know whether a person has remainder or not.

Take a mendicant who is a direct witness. The gods know of them: ‘This venerable is a direct witness. Hopefully this venerable will frequent appropriate lodgings, associate with good friends, and control their faculties. Then they might realize the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life, and live having achieved with their own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.’ This too is how those gods know whether a person has remainder or not.

Take a mendicant who is attained to view. … freed by faith … a follower of teachings. The gods know of them: ‘This venerable is a follower of teachings. Hopefully this venerable will frequent appropriate lodgings, associate with good friends, and control their faculties. Then they might realize the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life, and live having achieved with their own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.’ This too is how those gods know whether a person has remainder or not.”

Moggallāna approved and agreed with what Tissa the Divinity said. Then, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, he vanished from the realm of divinity and reappeared on the Vulture’s Peak. Then Mahāmoggallāna went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“But Moggallāna, Tissa the Divinity didn’t teach the seventh individual, the signless meditator.”

“Now is the time, Blessed One! Now is the time, Holy One! May the Buddha teach the seventh individual, the signless meditator. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, Moggallāna, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” Mahāmoggallāna replied. The Buddha said this:

“Moggallāna, take the case of a mendicant who, not focusing on any signs, enters and remains in the signless immersion of the heart. The gods know of them: ‘This venerable, not focusing on any signs, enters and remains in the signless immersion of the heart. Hopefully this venerable will frequent appropriate lodgings, associate with good friends, and control their faculties. Then they might realize the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life, and live having achieved with their own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.’ This too is how those gods know whether a person has remainder or not.”

AN 7.57 General Sīha Sīhasenāpatisutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof. Then General Sīha went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, can you point out a fruit of giving that’s apparent in the present life?”

“Well then, Sīha, I’ll ask you about this in return, and you can answer as you like. What do you think, Sīha? Consider two people. One is faithless, stingy, miserly, and abusive. One is a faithful donor who loves charity. Which do you think the perfected ones will show sympathy for first?”

“Why would the perfected ones first show sympathy for the person who is faithless, stingy, miserly, and abusive? They’d show sympathy first for the faithful donor who loves charity.”

“Which do you think the perfected ones will first approach?” “They’d first approach the faithful donor who loves charity.”

“Which do you think the perfected ones will receive alms from first?” “They’d receive alms first from the faithful donor who loves charity.”

“Which do you think the perfected ones will teach the Dhamma to first?” “They’d first teach the Dhamma to the faithful donor who loves charity.”

“Which do you think would get a good reputation?” “The faithful donor who loves charity would get a good reputation.”

“Which do you think would enter any kind of assembly bold and self-assured, whether it’s an assembly of aristocrats, brahmins, householders, or ascetics?”

“How could the person who is faithless, stingy, miserly, and abusive enter any kind of assembly bold and self-assured, whether it’s an assembly of aristocrats, brahmins, householders, or ascetics? The faithful donor who loves charity would enter any kind of assembly bold and self-assured, whether it’s an assembly of aristocrats, brahmins, householders, or ascetics.”

“When their body breaks up, after death, which do you think would be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm?”

“Why would the person who is faithless, stingy, miserly, and abusive be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm? The faithful donor who loves charity would, when their body breaks up, after death, be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

When it comes to these fruits of giving that are apparent in the present life, I don’t rely on faith in the Buddha, for I know them too. I’m a giver, a donor, and the perfected ones show sympathy for me first. I’m a giver, and the perfected ones approach me first. I’m a giver, and the perfected ones receive alms from me first. I’m a giver, and the perfected ones teach me Dhamma first. I’m a giver, and I have this good reputation: ‘General Sīha gives, serves, and attends on the Saṅgha.’ I’m a giver, I enter any kind of assembly bold and self-assured, whether it’s an assembly of aristocrats, brahmins, householders, or ascetics. When it comes to these fruits of giving that are apparent in the present life, I don’t rely on faith in the Buddha, for I know them too. But when the Buddha says: ‘When a giver’s body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’ I don’t know this, so I rely on faith in the Buddha.”

“That’s so true, Sīha! That’s so true! When a giver’s body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.”

AN 7.58 Nothing to Hide Arakkheyyasutta

“Mendicants, there are four areas where the Realized One has nothing to hide, and three ways he is irreproachable. What are the four areas where the Realized One has nothing to hide?

His bodily behavior is pure. So the Realized One has no bodily misconduct to hide, thinking: ‘Don’t let others find this out about me!’

His verbal behavior is pure. So the Realized One has no verbal misconduct to hide, thinking: ‘Don’t let others find this out about me!’

His mental behavior is pure. So the Realized One has no mental misconduct to hide, thinking: ‘Don’t let others find this out about me!’

His livelihood is pure. So the Realized One has no wrong livelihood to hide, thinking: ‘Don’t let others find this out about me!’

These are the four areas where the Realized One has nothing to hide.

What are the three ways the Realized One is irreproachable?

The Realized One has explained the teaching well. I see no reason for anyone—whether ascetic, brahmin, god, Māra, or the Divinity, or anyone else in the world—to legitimately scold me, saying: ‘For such reasons you haven’t explained the teaching well.’ Since I see no such reason, I live secure, fearless, and self-assured.

I have clearly described the practice that leads to extinguishment for my disciples. Practicing in accordance with this, my disciples realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. I see no reason for anyone—whether ascetic, brahmin, god, Māra, or the Divinity, or anyone else in the world—to legitimately scold me, saying: ‘For such reasons you haven’t clearly described the practice that leads to extinguishment for your disciples.’ Since I see no such reason, I live secure, fearless, and self-assured.

Many hundreds in my assembly of disciples have realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. I see no reason for anyone—whether ascetic, brahmin, god, Māra, or the Divinity, or anyone else in the world—to legitimately scold me, saying: ‘For such reasons you don’t have many hundreds of disciples in your following who have realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and who live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.’ Since I see no such reason, I live secure, fearless, and self-assured.

These are the three ways the Realized One is irreproachable.

These are the four areas where the Realized One has nothing to hide, and the three ways he is irreproachable.”

AN 7.59 With Kimbila Kimilasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Kimbilā in the Freshwater Mangrove Wood. Then Venerable Kimbila went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“What is the cause, sir, what is the reason why the true teaching does not last long after the final quenching of the Realized One?”

“Kimbila, it’s when the monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen lack respect and reverence for the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, immersion, diligence, and hospitality after the final quenching of the Realized One. This is the cause, this is the reason why the true teaching does not last long after the final quenching of the Realized One.”

“What is the cause, sir, what is the reason why the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One?”

“Kimbila, it’s when the monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen maintain respect and reverence for the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, immersion, diligence, and hospitality after the final quenching of the Realized One. This is the cause, this is the reason why the true teaching does last long after the final quenching of the Realized One.”

AN 7.60 Seven Qualities Sattadhammasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities soon realizes the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. They live having achieved with their own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness. What seven? It’s when a mendicant is faithful, ethical, learned, secluded, energetic, mindful, and wise. A mendicant with these seven qualities soon realizes the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. They live having achieved with their own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.”

AN 7.61 Nodding Off Pacalāyamānasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Bhaggas at Crocodile’s Bellow, in the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood.

Now at that time, in the land of the Magadhans near Kallavāḷamutta Village, Venerable Mahāmoggallāna was nodding off while meditating. The Buddha saw him with his clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman. Then, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, he vanished from the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood in the land of the Bhaggas and reappeared in front of Mahāmoggallāna near Kallavāḷamutta Village in the land of the Magadhans.

He sat down on the seat spread out and said to Mahāmoggallāna, “Are you nodding off, Moggallāna? Are you nodding off?”

“Yes, sir.”

“So, Moggallāna, don’t focus on or cultivate the perception that you were meditating on when you fell drowsy. It’s possible that you’ll give up drowsiness in this way.

But what if that doesn’t work? Then think about and consider the teaching as you’ve learned and memorized it, examining it with your mind. It’s possible that you’ll give up drowsiness in this way.

But what if that doesn’t work? Then rehearse in detail the teaching as you’ve learned and memorized it. It’s possible that you’ll give up drowsiness in this way.

But what if that doesn’t work? Then pinch your ears and rub your limbs. It’s possible that you’ll give up drowsiness in this way.

But what if that doesn’t work? Then get up from your seat, flush your eyes with water, look around in every direction, and look up at the stars and constellations. It’s possible that you’ll give up drowsiness in this way.

But what if that doesn’t work? Then apply your mind to the perception of light, focusing on the perception of day: as by day, so by night; as by night, so by day. And so, with an open and unenveloped heart, develop a mind that’s full of radiance. It’s possible that you’ll give up drowsiness in this way.

But what if that doesn’t work? Then walk mindfully, focusing on the perception of before and behind, your faculties directed inwards and your mind not scattered outside. It’s possible that you’ll give up drowsiness in this way.

But what if that doesn’t work? Then lie down in the lion’s posture—on the right side, placing one foot on top of the other—mindful and aware, and focused on the time of getting up. When you wake, you should get up quickly, thinking: ‘I will not live indulging in the pleasures of sleeping, lying down, and drowsing.’ That’s how you should train.

So you should train like this: ‘I will not approach families with my head swollen with vanity.’ That’s how you should train. What happens if a mendicant approaches families with a head swollen with vanity? Well, families have business to attend to, so people might not notice when a mendicant arrives. In that case the mendicant thinks: ‘Who on earth has turned this family against me? It seems they don’t like me any more.’ And so, because they don’t get anything they feel dismayed. Being dismayed, they become restless. Being restless, they lose restraint. And without restraint the mind is far from immersion.

So you should train like this: ‘I won’t get into arguments.’ That’s how you should train. When there’s an argument, you can expect there’ll be lots of talking. When there’s lots of talking, people become restless. Being restless, they lose restraint. And without restraint the mind is far from immersion. Moggallāna, I don’t praise all kinds of closeness. Nor do I criticize all kinds of closeness. I don’t praise closeness with laypeople and renunciates. I do praise closeness with those lodgings that are quiet and still, far from the madding crowd, remote from human settlements, and fit for retreat.”

When he said this, Venerable Moggallāna asked the Buddha, “Sir, how do you briefly define a mendicant who is freed through the ending of craving, who has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal, and is best among gods and humans?”

“Take a mendicant who has heard: ‘Nothing is worth insisting on.’ When a mendicant has heard that nothing is worth insisting on, they directly know all things. Directly knowing all things, they completely understand all things. Completely understanding all things, when they experience any kind of feeling—pleasant, unpleasant, or neutral—they meditate observing impermanence, dispassion, cessation, and letting go in those feelings. Meditating in this way, they don’t grasp at anything in the world. Not grasping, they’re not anxious. Not being anxious, they personally become extinguished.

They understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’ That’s how I briefly define a mendicant who is freed through the ending of craving, who has reached the ultimate end, the ultimate sanctuary from the yoke, the ultimate spiritual life, the ultimate goal, and is best among gods and humans.”

AN 7.62 Don’t Fear Good Deeds Mettasutta

“Mendicants, don’t fear good deeds. For ‘good deeds’ is a term for happiness. I recall undergoing for a long time the likable, desirable, and agreeable results of good deeds performed over a long time. I developed a mind of love for seven years. As a result, for seven eons of the cosmos contracting and expanding I didn’t return to this world again. As the cosmos contracted I went to the realm of sublime luminosity. As it expanded I was reborn in an empty mansion of divinity.

There I was the Divinity, the Great Divinity, the vanquisher, the unvanquished, the universal seer, the wielder of power. I was Sakka, lord of gods, thirty-six times. Many hundreds of times I was a king, a wheel-turning monarch, a just and principled king. My dominion extended to all four sides, I achieved stability in the country, and I possessed the seven treasures. These were my seven treasures: the wheel, the elephant, the horse, the jewel, the woman, the householder, and the commander as the seventh treasure. I had over a thousand sons who were valiant and heroic, crushing the armies of my enemies. After conquering this land girt by sea, I reigned by principle, without rod or sword.

See the result of good deeds,
of skillful deeds, for one seeking happiness.
I developed a mind of love
for seven years, mendicants.
For seven eons of expansion and contraction
I didn’t return to this world again.

As the world contracted
I went to the realm of sublime luminosity.
And when it expanded
I went to an empty mansion of divinity.

Seven times I was a Great Divinity,
and at that time I was the wielder of power.
Thirty-six times I was lord of gods,
acting as ruler of the gods.

Then I was king, a wheel-turning monarch,
lord of the Black Plum Tree Land.
An anointed aristocrat,
I was sovereign of all humans.

Without rod or sword,
I conquered this land.
Through non-violent action
I guided it justly.

After ruling this vast territory
by means of principle,
I was born in a rich family,
affluent and wealthy.

It was replete with all sense pleasures,
and the seven treasures.
This was well taught by the Buddhas,
who bring the world together.

This is the cause of greatness
by which one is called a lord of the land.
I was a majestic king,
with lots of property and assets;

successful and glorious,
lord of the Black Plum Tree Land.
Who would not be inspired by this,
even someone of dark birth.

Therefore someone who desires self-knowledge,
and aspires to greatness themselves,
should respect the true teaching,
remembering the instructions of the Buddhas.”

AN 7.63 Kinds of Wives Bhariyāsutta

Then the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of the householder Anāthapiṇḍika, where he sat down on the seat spread out.

Now at that time people in Anāthapiṇḍika’s home were making a colossal racket. Then the householder Anāthapiṇḍika went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him, “Householder, what’s with the people making that colossal racket in your home? You’d think it was fishermen hauling in a catch!”

“Sir, that’s my daughter-in-law Sujātā. She’s been brought here from a wealthy family. She doesn’t obey her mother-in-law or father-in-law or her husband. And she does not honor, respect, esteem, and venerate the Buddha.”

Then the Buddha addressed Sujātā, saying, “Come, Sujātā.”

“Yes, sir,” she replied. She went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to her:

“Sujātā, a man can have seven kinds of wife. What seven? A wife like a killer, a wife like a thief, a wife like a lord, a wife like a mother, a wife like a sister, a wife like a comrade, and a wife like a bondservant. These are the kinds of wife that a man can have. Which one of these are you?”

“Sir, I don’t understand the detailed meaning of what the Buddha has said in brief. Please teach me this matter so I can understand the detailed meaning.”

“Well then, Sujātā, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” she replied. The Buddha said this:

“With a mind full of hate and no kindness,
lusting for others, looking down on her husband,
she longs to murder him who paid the price for her.
A man’s wife of this sort
is called a wife and a killer.

A woman’s husband earns his wealth
by focusing on a profession, trade, or farming.
And even if it’s only a little, she wants to take it.
A man’s wife of this sort
is called a wife and a thief.

She’s an idle glutton who doesn’t want to work.
Her words are harsh, fierce, and rude.
He works hard, but she lives as his master.
A man’s wife of this sort
is called a wife and a lord.

She’s always caring and kind,
looking after her husband like a mother her child.
She keeps the wealth that he has earned secure.
A man’s wife of this sort
is called a wife and a mother.

She respects her husband
as a younger sister respects her elder.
Conscientious, she does what her husband says.
A man’s wife of this sort
is called a wife and a sister.

She’s delighted to see him,
like one reunited with a long-lost comrade.
She’s of good pedigree, virtuous, and devoted.
A man’s wife of this sort
is called a wife and a comrade.

She has no anger when threatened with violence by the rod.
Without hate or anger,
she endures her husband and does what he says.
A man’s wife of this sort
is called a wife and a bondservant.

The kinds of wives here called
killer, thief, and lord;
immoral, harsh, and lacking regard for others,
when their body breaks up they set course for hell.

But the kinds of wives here called
mother, sister, comrade, and bondservant;
steadfast in their own morality, restrained for a long time,
when their body breaks up they set course for a good place.

Sujātā, these are the seven kinds of wife that a man can have. Which one of these are you?”

“Sir, from this day forth may the Buddha remember me as a wife like a bondservant.”

AN 7.64 Irritable Kodhanasutta

“Mendicants, these seven things that please and assist an enemy happen to an irritable woman or man. What seven?

Firstly, an enemy wishes for an enemy: ‘If only they’d become ugly!’ Why is that? Because an enemy doesn’t like to have a beautiful enemy. An irritable individual, overcome and overwhelmed by anger, is ugly, even though they’re nicely bathed and anointed, with hair and beard dressed, and wearing white clothes. This is the first thing that pleases and assists an enemy which happens to an irritable woman or man.

Furthermore, an enemy wishes for an enemy: ‘If only they’d sleep badly!’ Why is that? Because an enemy doesn’t like to have an enemy who sleeps at ease. An irritable individual, overcome and overwhelmed by anger, sleeps badly, even though they sleep on a couch spread with woolen covers—shag-piled, pure white, or embroidered with flowers—and spread with a fine deer hide, with a canopy above and red pillows at both ends. This is the second thing …

Furthermore, an enemy wishes for an enemy: ‘If only their needs are not amply satisfied!’ Why is that? Because an enemy doesn’t like to have an enemy whose needs are amply satisfied. When an irritable individual, overcome and overwhelmed by anger, gets what they don’t need they think, ‘I’ve got what I need.’ When they get what they need they think, ‘I’ve got what I don’t need.’ When an angry person gets these things that are the exact opposite of what they need, it’s for their lasting harm and suffering. This is the third thing …

Furthermore, an enemy wishes for an enemy: ‘If only they weren’t wealthy!’ Why is that? Because an enemy doesn’t like to have an enemy who is wealthy. When an individual is irritable, overcome and overwhelmed by anger, the rulers seize the legitimate wealth they’ve earned by their efforts, built up with their own hands, gathered by the sweat of their brow. This is the fourth thing …

Furthermore, an enemy wishes for an enemy: ‘If only they weren’t famous!’ Why is that? Because an enemy doesn’t like to have a famous enemy. When an individual is irritable, overcome and overwhelmed by anger, any fame they have acquired by diligence falls to dust. This is the fifth thing …

Furthermore, an enemy wishes for an enemy: ‘If only they had no friends!’ Why is that? Because an enemy doesn’t like to have an enemy with friends. When an individual is irritable, overcome and overwhelmed by anger, their friends and colleagues, relatives and kin avoid them from afar. This is the sixth thing …

Furthermore, an enemy wishes for an enemy: ‘If only, when their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell!’ Why is that? Because an enemy doesn’t like to have an enemy who goes to a good place. When an individual is irritable, overcome and overwhelmed by anger, they do bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. This is the seventh thing that pleases and assists an enemy which happens to an irritable woman or man.

These are the seven things that please and assist an enemy which happen to an irritable woman or man.

An irritable person is ugly
and they sleep badly.
When they get what they need,
they take it to be what they don’t need.

An angry person
kills with body or speech;
overcome with anger,
they lose their wealth.

Mad with anger,
they fall into disgrace.
Family, friends, and loved ones
avoid an irritable person.

Anger creates harm;
anger upsets the mind.
That person doesn’t recognize
the danger that arises within.

An angry person doesn’t know the good.
An angry person doesn’t see the truth.
When a person is beset by anger,
only blind darkness is left.

An angry person destroys with ease
what was hard to build.
Afterwards, when the anger is spent,
they’re tormented as if burnt by fire.

Their look betrays their sulkiness
like a fire’s smoky plume.
And when their anger flares up,
they make others angry.

They have no conscience or prudence,
nor any respectful speech.
One overcome by anger
has no island refuge anywhere.

The deeds that torment a man
are far from those that are good.
I’ll explain them now;
listen to this, for it is the truth.

An angry person slays their father;
their mother, too, they slay.
An angry person slays a saint;
a normal person, too, they slay.

A man is raised by his mother,
who shows him the world.
But an angry ordinary person slays
even that good woman who gave him life.

Like oneself, those sentient beings
hold themselves most dear.
But when angered, they kill themselves in different ways,
distraught in many respects.

Some kill themselves with swords,
some, distraught, take poison.
Some hang themselves with rope,
or fling themselves down a mountain gorge.

When they commit deeds of baby-killing,
and killing themselves,
they don’t realize what they do,
for anger leads to their downfall.

The snare of death in the form of anger
lies hidden in the heart.
You should cut it out by self-control,
by wisdom, energy, and right ideas.

An astute person should cut out
this unskillful thing.
And they’d train in the teaching in just the same way,
not yielding to sulkiness.

Free of anger, free of despair,
free of greed, with no more longing,
tamed, having given up anger,
the undefiled are fully extinguished.”

The Great Chapter

AN 7.65 Conscience and Prudence Hirīottappasutta

“Mendicants, when there is no conscience and prudence, one who lacks conscience and prudence has destroyed a vital condition for sense restraint. When there is no sense restraint, one who lacks sense restraint has destroyed a vital condition for ethical conduct. When there is no ethical conduct, one who lacks ethics has destroyed a vital condition for right immersion. When there is no right immersion, one who lacks right immersion has destroyed a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is no true knowledge and vision, one who lacks true knowledge and vision has destroyed a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is no disillusionment and dispassion, one who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that lacked branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would not grow to fullness.

In the same way, when there is no conscience and prudence, a person who lacks conscience and prudence has destroyed a vital condition for sense restraint. When there is no sense restraint, one who lacks sense restraint has destroyed a vital condition for ethical conduct. When there is no ethical conduct, one who lacks ethics has destroyed a vital condition for right immersion. When there is no right immersion, one who lacks right immersion has destroyed a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is no true knowledge and vision, one who lacks true knowledge and vision has destroyed a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is no disillusionment and dispassion, one who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

When there is conscience and prudence, a person who has fulfilled conscience and prudence has fulfilled a vital condition for sense restraint. When there is sense restraint, one who has fulfilled sense restraint has fulfilled a vital condition for ethical conduct. When there is ethical conduct, one who has fulfilled ethical conduct has fulfilled a vital condition for right immersion. When there is right immersion, one who has fulfilled right immersion has fulfilled a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is true knowledge and vision, one who has fulfilled true knowledge and vision has fulfilled a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is disillusionment and dispassion, one who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that was complete with branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would grow to fullness.

In the same way, when there is conscience and prudence, one who has fulfilled conscience and prudence has fulfilled a vital condition for sense restraint. … One who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.”

AN 7.66 The Seven Suns Sattasūriyasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī in Ambapālī’s Mango Grove. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, conditions are impermanent. Conditions are unstable. Conditions are unreliable. This is quite enough for you to become disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding all conditions.

Sineru, the king of mountains, is 84,000 leagues long and 84,000 leagues wide. It sinks 84,000 leagues below the ocean and rises 84,000 leagues above it. There comes a time when, after a very long period has passed—many years, many hundreds, many thousands, many hundreds of thousands of years—the heavens fail to rain. When this happens, the plants and seeds, the herbs, grass, and big trees wither away and dry up, and are no more. So impermanent are conditions, so unstable, so unreliable. This is quite enough for you to become disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding all conditions.

There comes a time when, after a very long period has passed, a second sun appears. When this happens, the streams and pools wither away and dry up, and are no more. So impermanent are conditions …

There comes a time when, after a very long period has passed, a third sun appears. When this happens, the great rivers—the Ganges, Yamunā, Aciravatī, Sarabhū, and Mahī—wither away and dry up, and are no more. So impermanent are conditions …

There comes a time when, after a very long period has passed, a fourth sun appears. When this happens, the great lakes from which the rivers originate—the Anotattā, Sīhapapātā, Rathakārā, Kaṇṇamuṇḍā, Kuṇālā, Chaddantā, and Mandākinī—wither away and dry up, and are no more. So impermanent are conditions …

There comes a time when, after a very long period has passed, a fifth sun appears. When this happens, the water in the ocean sinks by a hundred leagues. It sinks by two, three, four, five, six, or even seven hundred leagues. The water that remains in the ocean is only seven palm trees deep. It’s six, five, four, three, two, or even one palm tree deep. The water that remains in the ocean is only seven fathoms deep. It’s six, five, four, three, two, one or even half a fathom deep. It’s waist high, knee high, or even ankle high. It’s like in autumn, when the heavens rain heavily and water remains here and there in the cows’ hoofprints. In the same way, water in the ocean remains here and there in puddles like cows’ hoofprints. When the fifth sun appears there’s not even enough water left in the great ocean for the tip of the toe. So impermanent are conditions …

There comes a time when, after a very long period has passed, a sixth sun appears. When this happens, this great earth and Sineru the king of mountains smoke and smolder and give off fumes. It’s like when a potter’s kiln is first kindled, and it smokes and smolders and gives off fumes. In the same way, this great earth and Sineru the king of mountains smoke and smolder and give off fumes. So impermanent are conditions …

There comes a time when, after a very long period has passed, a seventh sun appears. When this happens, this great earth and Sineru the king of mountains erupt in one burning mass of fire. And as they blaze and burn the flames are swept by the wind as far as the realm of divinity. Sineru the king of mountains blazes and burns, crumbling as it’s overcome by the great fire. And meanwhile, mountain peaks a hundred leagues high, or two, three, four, or five hundred leagues high disintegrate as they burn. And when the great earth and Sineru the king of mountains blaze and burn, no soot or ash is found. It’s like when ghee or oil blaze and burn, and neither ashes nor soot are found. In the same way, when the great earth and Sineru the king of mountains blaze and burn, no soot or ash is found. So impermanent are conditions, so unstable are conditions, so unreliable are conditions. This is quite enough for you to become disillusioned, dispassionate, and freed regarding all conditions.

Mendicants, who would ever think or believe that this earth and Sineru, king of mountains, will burn and crumble and be no more, except one who has seen the truth?

Once upon a time, there was a teacher named Sunetta. He was a religious founder and was free of desire for sensual pleasures. He had many hundreds of disciples. He taught them a Dhamma for rebirth in the company of Divinity. Those who totally understood Sunetta’s teachings were—when their body broke up, after death—reborn in a good place, the company of Divinity. Of those who didn’t totally understand Sunetta’s teachings, some—when their body broke up, after death—were reborn in the company of the gods who control what is created by others. Some were reborn in the company of the gods who love to create, some with the joyful gods, some with the gods of Yama, some with the gods of the thirty-three, and some with the gods of the four great kings. Some were reborn in the company of well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders.

Then the teacher Sunetta thought: ‘It’s not proper for me to be reborn in the next life in exactly the same place as my disciples. Why don’t I further develop love?’

Then Sunetta developed love for seven years. Having done so he did not return to this world for seven eons of cosmic expansion and contraction. As the cosmos contracted he went to the realm of sublime luminosity. As it expanded he was reborn in an empty mansion of divinity. There he was the Divinity, the Great Divinity, the vanquisher, the unvanquished, the universal seer, the wielder of power. He was Sakka, lord of gods, thirty-six times. Many hundreds of times he was a king, a wheel-turning monarch, a just and principled king. His dominion extended to all four sides, he achieved stability in the country, and he possessed the seven treasures. He had over a thousand sons who were valiant and heroic, crushing the armies of his enemies. After conquering this land girt by sea, he reigned by principle, without rod or sword. Yet even though Sunetta lived so long, he was not free from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. He was not free from suffering, I say.

Why is that? Because of not understanding and not penetrating four things. What four? Noble ethics, immersion, wisdom, and freedom. These noble ethics, immersion, wisdom, and freedom have been understood and penetrated. Craving for continued existence has been cut off; the leash to existence is ended; now there’ll be no more future lives.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“Ethics, immersion, and wisdom,
and the supreme freedom:
these things have been understood
by Gotama the renowned.

And so the Buddha, having insight,
explained this teaching to the mendicants.
The Teacher has made an end of suffering;
seeing clearly, he is quenched.”

AN 7.67 The Simile of the Citadel Nagaropamasutta

“Mendicants, when a king’s frontier citadel is well provided with seven essentials and gets four kinds of sustenance when needed, without trouble or difficulty, it is then called a king’s frontier citadel that cannot be overrun by external foes and enemies.

With what seven essentials is a citadel well provided?

Firstly, a citadel has a pillar with deep foundations, firmly embedded, imperturbable and unshakable. This is the first essential with which a king’s frontier citadel is well provided, to defend those within and repel those outside.

Furthermore, a citadel has a moat that is deep and wide. This is the second essential …

Furthermore, a citadel has a patrol path that is high and wide. This is the third essential …

Furthermore, a citadel has stores of many weapons, both projectile and hand-held. This is the fourth essential …

Furthermore, many kinds of armed forces reside in a citadel, such as elephant marshals, cavalry, charioteers, archers, bannermen, adjutants, food servers, warrior-chiefs, princes, chargers, great warriors, heroes, leather-clad soldiers, and sons of bondservants. This is the fifth essential …

Furthermore, a citadel has a gatekeeper who is astute, competent, and intelligent. He keeps strangers out and lets known people in. This is the sixth essential …

Furthermore, a citadel has a wall that’s high and wide, covered with plaster. This is the seventh essential with which a king’s frontier citadel is well provided, to defend those within and repel those outside.

With these seven essentials a citadel is well provided.

What are the four kinds of sustenance it gets when needed, without trouble or difficulty?

Firstly, a king’s frontier citadel has much hay, wood, and water stored up for the enjoyment, relief, and comfort of those within and to repel those outside.

Furthermore, a king’s frontier citadel has much rice and barley stored up for those within.

Furthermore, a king’s frontier citadel has much food such as sesame, green gram, and black gram stored up for those within.

Furthermore, a king’s frontier citadel has much medicine—ghee, butter, oil, honey, molasses, and salt—stored up for the enjoyment, relief, and comfort of those within and to repel those outside.

These are the four kinds of sustenance it gets when needed, without trouble or difficulty.

When a king’s frontier citadel is well provided with seven essentials and gets four kinds of sustenance when needed, without trouble or difficulty, it is then called a king’s frontier citadel that cannot be overrun by external foes and enemies. In the same way, when a noble disciple has seven good qualities, and they get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty, they are then called a noble disciple who cannot be overrun by Māra, who cannot be overrun by the Wicked One. What are the seven good qualities that they possess?

Just as a king’s frontier citadel has a pillar with deep foundations, firmly embedded, imperturbable and unshakable, to defend those within and repel those outside, in the same way a noble disciple has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ A noble disciple with faith as their pillar gives up the unskillful and develops the skillful, they give up the blameworthy and develop the blameless, and they keep themselves pure. This is the first good quality they have.

Just as a citadel has a moat that is deep and wide, in the same way a noble disciple has a conscience. They’re conscientious about bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind, and conscientious about having any bad, unskillful qualities. A noble disciple with a conscience as their moat gives up the unskillful and develops the skillful, they give up the blameworthy and develop the blameless, and they keep themselves pure. This is the second good quality they have.

Just as a citadel has a patrol path that is high and wide, in the same way a noble disciple is prudent. They’re prudent when it comes to bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind, and prudent when it comes to acquiring any bad, unskillful qualities. A noble disciple with prudence as their patrol path gives up the unskillful and develops the skillful, they give up the blameworthy and develop the blameless, and they keep themselves pure. This is the third good quality they have.

Just as a citadel has stores of many weapons, both projectile and hand-held, in the same way a noble disciple is very learned. They remember and keep what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, reciting them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. A noble disciple with learning as their weapon gives up the unskillful and develops the skillful, they give up the blameworthy and develop the blameless, and they keep themselves pure. This is the fourth good quality they have.

Just as many kinds of armed forces reside in a citadel … in the same way a noble disciple is energetic. They live with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They are strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. A noble disciple with energy as their armed forces gives up the unskillful and develops the skillful, they give up the blameworthy and develop the blameless, and they keep themselves pure. This is the fifth good quality they have.

Just as a citadel has a gatekeeper who is astute, competent, and intelligent, who keeps strangers out and lets known people in, in the same way a noble disciple is mindful. They have utmost mindfulness and alertness, and can remember and recall what was said and done long ago. A noble disciple with mindfulness as their gatekeeper gives up the unskillful and develops the skillful, they give up the blameworthy and develop the blameless, and they keep themselves pure. This is the sixth good quality they have.

Just as a citadel has a wall that’s high and wide, covered with plaster, to defend those within and repel those outside, in the same way a noble disciple is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. A noble disciple with wisdom as their wall gives up the unskillful and develops the skillful, they give up the blameworthy and develop the blameless, and they keep themselves pure. This is the seventh good quality they have. These are the seven good qualities that they possess.

And what are the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—that they get when they want, without trouble or difficulty? Just as a king’s frontier citadel has much hay, wood, and water stored up for the enjoyment, relief, and comfort of those within and to repel those outside, in the same way a noble disciple, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. This is for their own enjoyment, relief, and comfort, and for alighting upon extinguishment.

Just as a king’s frontier citadel has much rice and barley stored up, in the same way, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, a noble disciple enters and remains in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected. This is for their own enjoyment, relief, and comfort, and for alighting upon extinguishment.

Just as a king’s frontier citadel has much food such as sesame, green gram, and black gram stored up, in the same way with the fading away of rapture, a noble disciple enters and remains in the third absorption, where they meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.’ This is for their own enjoyment, relief, and comfort, and for alighting upon extinguishment.

Just as a king’s frontier citadel has much medicine—ghee, butter, oil, honey, molasses, and salt—stored up for the enjoyment, relief, and comfort of those within and to repel those outside, in the same way, with the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, a noble disciple enters and remains in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness. This is for their own enjoyment, relief, and comfort, and for alighting upon extinguishment. These are the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—which they get when they want, without trouble or difficulty.

When a noble disciple has seven good qualities, and they get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty, they are then called a noble disciple who cannot be overrun by Māra, who cannot be overrun by the Wicked One.”

AN 7.68 One Who Knows the Teachings Dhammaññūsutta

“A mendicant with seven qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What seven? It’s when a mendicant knows the teachings, knows the meaning, has self-knowledge, knows moderation, knows the right time, knows assemblies, and knows individuals high and low.

And how is a mendicant one who knows the teachings? It’s when a mendicant knows the teachings: statements, mixed prose & verse, discussions, verses, inspired exclamations, legends, stories of past lives, amazing stories, and elaborations. If a mendicant did not know these teachings, they would not be called ‘one who knows the teachings’. But because they do know these teachings, they are called ‘one who knows the teachings’. Such is the one who knows the teachings.

And how are they one who knows the meaning? It’s when a mendicant knows the meaning of this or that statement: ‘This is what that statement means; that is what this statement means.’ If a mendicant did not know the meaning of this or that statement, they would not be called ‘one who knows the meaning’. But because they do know the meaning of this or that statement, they are called ‘one who knows the meaning’. Such is the one who knows the teachings and the one who knows the meaning.

And how are they one who has self-knowledge? It’s when a mendicant has self-knowledge: ‘This is the extent of my faith, ethics, learning, generosity, wisdom, and eloquence.’ If a mendicant did not have self-knowledge, they would not be called ‘one who has self-knowledge’. But because they do have self-knowledge, they are called ‘one who has self-knowledge’. Such is the one who knows the teachings, the one who knows the meaning, and the one who has self-knowledge.

And how are they one who knows moderation? It’s when a mendicant knows moderation when receiving robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. If a mendicant did not know moderation, they would not be called ‘one who knows moderation’. But because they do know moderation, they are called ‘one who knows moderation’. Such is the one who knows the teachings, the one who knows the meaning, the one who has self-knowledge, and the one who knows moderation.

And how are they one who knows the right time? It’s when a mendicant knows the right time: ‘This is the time for recitation; this is the time for questioning; this is the time for meditation; this is the time for retreat.’ If a mendicant did not know the right time, they would not be called ‘one who knows the right time’. But because they do know the right time, they are called ‘one who knows the right time’. Such is the one who knows the teachings, the one who knows the meaning, the one who has self-knowledge, the one who knows moderation, and the one who knows the right time.

And how are they one who knows assemblies? It’s when a mendicant knows assemblies: ‘This is an assembly of aristocrats, of brahmins, of householders, or of ascetics. This one should be approached in this way. This is how to stand, to act, to sit, to speak, or to stay silent when there.’ If a mendicant did not know assemblies, they would not be called ‘one who knows assemblies’. But because they do know assemblies, they are called ‘one who knows assemblies’. Such is the one who knows the teachings, the one who knows the meaning, the one who has self-knowledge, the one who knows moderation, the one who knows the right time, and the one who knows assemblies.

And how are they one who knows individuals high and low? It’s when a mendicant understands individuals in terms of pairs. Two individuals: one likes to see the noble ones, one does not. The individual who doesn’t like to see the noble ones is reprehensible in that respect. The individual who does like to see the noble ones is praiseworthy in that respect.

Two individuals like to see the noble ones: one likes to hear the true teaching, one does not. The individual who doesn’t like to hear the true teaching is reprehensible in that respect. The individual who does like to hear the true teaching is praiseworthy in that respect.

Two individuals like to hear the true teaching: one actively listens to the teaching, one does not. The individual who doesn’t actively listen to the teaching is reprehensible in that respect. The individual who does actively listen to the teaching is praiseworthy in that respect.

Two individuals actively listen to the teaching: one remembers the teaching they’ve heard, one does not. The individual who doesn’t remember the teaching they’ve heard is reprehensible in that respect. The individual who does remember the teaching they’ve heard is praiseworthy in that respect.

Two individuals remember the teaching they’ve heard: one examines the meaning of the teachings they have remembered, one does not. The individual who does not examine the meaning of the teachings they have remembered is reprehensible in that respect. The individual who does examine the meaning of the teachings they have remembered is praiseworthy in that respect.

Two individuals examine the meaning of the teachings they have remembered: one understands the meaning and the teaching and practicesin line with the teaching, one understands the meaning and the teaching but does not practice in line with the teaching. The individual who understands the meaning and the teaching but does not practice in line with the principle of the teaching is reprehensible in that respect. The individual who understands the meaning and the teaching and practices in line with the principle of the teaching is praiseworthy in that respect.

Two individuals understand the meaning and the teaching and practice in line with the teaching: one practices to benefit themselves but not others, and one practices to benefit both themselves and others. The individual who practices to benefit themselves but not others is reprehensible in that respect. The individual who practices to benefit both themselves and others is praiseworthy in that respect.

That’s how a mendicant understands individuals in terms of pairs.

That’s how a mendicant is one who knows individuals high and low. A mendicant with these seven qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 7.69 The Shady Orchid Tree Pāricchattakasutta

“Mendicants, when the leaves on the Shady Orchid Tree belonging to the gods of the thirty-three turn brown, the gods are elated. They think: ‘Now the leaves on the Shady Orchid Tree have turned brown! It won’t be long until they fall.’

When the leaves have fallen, the gods are elated. They think: ‘Now the leaves on the Shady Orchid Tree have fallen. It won’t be long until its foliage starts to regrow.’

When the foliage starts to regrow, the gods are elated. They think: ‘Now the foliage of the Shady Orchid Tree has started to regrow. It won’t be long until it’s ready to grow flowers and leaves separately.’

When it’s ready to grow flowers and leaves separately, the gods are elated. They think: ‘Now the Shady Orchid Tree is ready to grow flowers and leaves separately. It won’t be long until buds start to form.’

When the buds start to form, the gods are elated. They think: ‘Now the buds of the Shady Orchid Tree have started to form. It won’t be long until the buds burst.’

When the buds have burst, the gods are elated. They think: ‘Now the buds of the Shady Orchid Tree have burst. It won’t be long until it fully blossoms.’

When the Shady Orchid Tree of the gods of the thirty-three has fully blossomed, the gods are elated. For four heavenly months they amused themselves at the root of the tree, supplied and provided with the five kinds of sensual stimulation. When the Shady Orchid Tree has fully blossomed, its radiance spreads for fifty leagues, while its fragrance wafts for a hundred leagues. Such is the majesty of the Shady Orchid Tree.

In the same way, when a noble disciple plans to go forth from the lay life to homelessness, they’re like the Shady Orchid Tree when its leaves turn brown.

When a noble disciple shaves off their hair and beard, dresses in ocher robes, and goes forth from the lay life to homelessness, they’re like the Shady Orchid Tree when its leaves fall.

When a noble disciple, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected, they’re like the Shady Orchid Tree when its foliage starts to regrow.

When, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, a noble disciple enters and remains in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected, they’re like the Shady Orchid Tree when it’s ready to grow flowers and leaves separately.

When, with the fading away of rapture, a noble disciple enters and remains in the third absorption, where they meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss’, they’re like the Shady Orchid Tree when its buds start to form.

When, with the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, a noble disciple enters and remains in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness, they’re like the Shady Orchid Tree when its buds burst.

When a noble disciple realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements, they’re like the Shady Orchid Tree when it fully blossoms.

At that time the earth gods raise the cry: ‘This venerable named so-and-so, from such-and-such village or town, the protégé of the venerable named so-and-so, went forth from the lay life to homelessness. They’ve realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.’

Hearing the cry of the earth gods, the gods of the four great kings … the gods of the thirty-three … the gods of Yama … the joyful gods … the gods who love to create … the gods who control what is created by others … the gods of the Divinity’s host raise the cry: ‘This venerable named so-and-so, from such-and-such village or town, the protégé of the venerable named so-and-so, went forth from the lay life to homelessness. They’ve realized the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.’ And so at that moment, that hour, the cry soars up to the realm of divinity. Such is the majesty of a mendicant who has ended the defilements.”

AN 7.70 Honor Sakkaccasutta

Then as Venerable Sāriputta was in private retreat this thought came to his mind, “What should a mendicant honor and respect and rely on, to give up the unskillful and develop the skillful?”

Then he thought, “A mendicant should honor and respect and rely on the Teacher … the teaching … the Saṅgha … the training … immersion … diligence … A mendicant should honor and respect and rely on hospitality, to give up the unskillful and develop the skillful.”

Then he thought, “These qualities are pure and bright in me. Why don’t I go and tell them to the Buddha? Then these qualities will not only be purified in me, but will be better known as purified. Suppose a man were to acquire a gold ingot, pure and bright. They’d think, ‘My gold ingot is pure and bright. Why don’t I take it to show the smiths? Then it will not only be purified, but will be better known as purified.’ In the same way, these qualities are pure and bright in me. Why don’t I go and tell them to the Buddha? Then these qualities will not only be purified in me, but will be better known as purified.”

Then in the late afternoon, Sāriputta came out of retreat and went to the Buddha. He bowed, sat down to one side, and told the Buddha of his thoughts while on retreat.

“Good, good, Sāriputta! A mendicant should honor and respect and rely on the Teacher, to give up the unskillful and develop the skillful. A mendicant should honor and respect and rely on the teaching … the Saṅgha … the training … immersion … diligence … A mendicant should honor and respect and rely on hospitality, to give up the unskillful and develop the skillful.”

When he said this, Venerable Sāriputta said to the Buddha:

“Sir, this is how I understand the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement. It is quite impossible for a mendicant who doesn’t respect the Teacher to respect the teaching. A mendicant who disrespects the Teacher disrespects the teaching.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who doesn’t respect the Teacher and the teaching to respect the Saṅgha. A mendicant who disrespects the Teacher and the teaching disrespects the Saṅgha.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who doesn’t respect the Teacher, the teaching, and the Saṅgha to respect the training. A mendicant who disrespects the Teacher, the teaching, and the Saṅgha disrespects the training.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who doesn’t respect the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, and the training to respect immersion. A mendicant who disrespects the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, and the training disrespects immersion.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who doesn’t respect the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, and immersion to respect diligence. A mendicant who disrespects the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, and immersion disrespects diligence.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who doesn’t respect the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, immersion, and diligence to respect hospitality. A mendicant who disrespects the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, immersion, and diligence disrespects hospitality.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who does respect the Teacher to disrespect the teaching. …

A mendicant who respects the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, immersion, and diligence respects hospitality.

It’s quite possible for a mendicant who respects the Teacher to respect the teaching. …

A mendicant who respects the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, immersion, and diligence respects hospitality.

That’s how I understand the detailed meaning of the Buddha’s brief statement.”

“Good, good, Sāriputta! It’s good that you understand the detailed meaning of what I’ve said in brief like this.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who doesn’t respect the Teacher to respect the teaching. …

A mendicant who disrespects the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, immersion, and diligence disrespects hospitality.

It is quite impossible for a mendicant who does respect the Teacher to disrespect the teaching. …

A mendicant who respects the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, immersion, and diligence respects hospitality.

It’s quite possible for a mendicant who does respect the Teacher to respect the teaching. …

A mendicant who respects the Teacher, the teaching, the Saṅgha, the training, immersion, and diligence respects hospitality.

This is how to see the detailed meaning of what I said in brief.”

AN 7.71 Committed to Development Bhāvanāsutta

“Mendicants, when a mendicant is not committed to development, they might wish: ‘If only my mind were freed from the defilements by not grasping!’ Even so, their mind is not freed from defilements by not grasping. Why is that? You should say: ‘It’s because they’re undeveloped.’ Undeveloped in what? The four kinds of mindfulness meditation, the four right efforts, the four bases of psychic power, the five faculties, the five powers, the seven awakening factors, and the noble eightfold path.

Suppose there was a chicken with eight or ten or twelve eggs. But she had not properly sat on them to keep them warm and incubated. Even if that chicken might wish: ‘If only my chicks could break out of the eggshell with their claws and beak and hatch safely!’ Still they can’t break out and hatch safely. Why is that? Because she has not properly sat on them to keep them warm and incubated.

In the same way, when a mendicant is not committed to development, they might wish: ‘If only my mind were freed from the defilements by not grasping!’ Even so, their mind is not freed from defilements by not grasping. Why is that? You should say: ‘It’s because they’re undeveloped.’ Undeveloped in what? The four kinds of mindfulness meditation, the four right efforts, the four bases of psychic power, the five faculties, the five powers, the seven awakening factors, and the noble eightfold path.

When a mendicant is committed to development, they might not wish: ‘If only my mind were freed from the defilements by not grasping!’ Even so, their mind is freed from defilements by not grasping. Why is that? You should say: ‘It’s because they are developed.’ Developed in what? The four kinds of mindfulness meditation, the four right efforts, the four bases of psychic power, the five faculties, the five powers, the seven awakening factors, and the noble eightfold path.

Suppose there was a chicken with eight or ten or twelve eggs. And she properly sat on them to keep them warm and incubated. Even if that chicken doesn’t wish: ‘If only my chicks could break out of the eggshell with their claws and beak and hatch safely!’ Still they can break out and hatch safely. Why is that? Because she properly sat on them to keep them warm and incubated.

In the same way, when a mendicant is committed to development, they might not wish: ‘If only my mind were freed from the defilements by not grasping!’ Even so, their mind is freed from defilements by not grasping. Why is that? You should say: ‘It’s because they are developed.’ Developed in what? The four kinds of mindfulness meditation, the four right efforts, the four bases of psychic power, the five faculties, the five powers, the seven awakening factors, and the noble eightfold path.

Suppose a mason or their apprentice sees the marks of his fingers and thumb on the handle of his adze. They don’t know how much of the handle was worn away today, how much yesterday, and how much previously. They just know what has been worn away. In the same way, when a mendicant is committed to development, they don’t know how much of the defilements were worn away today, how much yesterday, and how much previously. They just know what has been worn away.

Suppose there was a sea-faring ship bound together with ropes. For six months they deteriorated in the water. Then in the cold season it was hauled up on dry land, where the ropes were weathered by wind and sun. When the monsoon clouds soaked it with rain, the ropes would readily collapse and rot away. In the same way, when a mendicant is committed to development their fetters readily collapse and rot away.”

AN 7.72 The Simile of the Great Mass of Fire Aggikkhandhopamasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was wandering in the land of the Kosalans together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants.

While walking along the road, at a certain spot he saw a great mass of fire burning, blazing, and glowing. Seeing this he left the road, sat at the root of a tree on a seat spread out, and addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, do you see that great mass of fire burning, blazing, and glowing?”

“Yes, sir.”

“What do you think, mendicants? Which is better—to sit or lie down embracing that great mass of fire? Or to sit or lie down embracing a girl of the aristocrats or brahmins or householders with soft and tender hands and feet?”

“Sir, it would be much better to sit or lie down embracing a girl of the aristocrats or brahmins or householders with soft and tender hands and feet. For it would be painful to sit or lie down embracing that great mass of fire.”

“I declare this to you, mendicants, I announce this to you! It would be better for that unethical man—of bad qualities, filthy, with suspicious behavior, underhand, no true ascetic or spiritual practitioner, though claiming to be one, rotten inside, festering, and depraved—to sit or lie down embracing that great mass of fire. Why is that? Because that might result in death or deadly pain. But when his body breaks up, after death, it would not cause him to be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

But when such an unethical man sits or lies down embracing a girl of the aristocrats or brahmins or householders with soft and tender hands and feet, that brings him lasting harm and suffering. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

What do you think, mendicants? Which is better—to have a strong man twist a strong horse-hair rope around both shins and tighten it so that it cuts through your outer skin, your inner skin, your flesh, sinews, and bones, until it reaches your marrow and keeps pressing? Or to consent to well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders bowing down to you?”

“Sir, it would be much better to consent to well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders bowing down. For it would be painful to have a strong man twist a strong horse-hair rope around your shins and tighten it so that it cut through the outer skin until it reached the marrow and kept pressing.”

“I declare this to you, mendicants, I announce this to you! It would be better for that unethical man to have a strong man twist a strong horse-hair rope around both shins and tighten it until it reached the marrow and kept pressing. Why is that? Because that might result in death or deadly pain. But when his body breaks up, after death, it would not cause him to be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. But when such an unethical man consents to well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders bowing down, that brings him lasting harm and suffering. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

What do you think, mendicants? Which is better—to have a strong man stab you in the chest with a sharp, oiled sword? Or to consent to well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders revering you with cupped palms?”

“Sir, it would be much better to consent to well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders revering you with cupped palms. For it would be painful to have a strong man stab you in the chest with a sharp, oiled sword.”

“I declare this to you, mendicants, I announce this to you! It would be better for that unethical man to have a strong man stab him in the chest with a sharp, oiled sword. Why is that? Because that might result in death or deadly pain. But when his body breaks up, after death, it would not cause him to be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. But when such an unethical man consents to well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders revering him with cupped palms, that brings him lasting harm and suffering. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

What do you think, mendicants? Which is better—to have a strong man wrap you up in a red-hot sheet of iron, burning, blazing, and glowing? Or to enjoy the use of a robe given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders?”

“Sir, it would be much better to enjoy the use of a robe given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders. For it would be painful to have a strong man wrap you up in a red-hot sheet of iron, burning, blazing, and glowing.”

“I declare this to you, mendicants, I announce this to you! It would be better for that unethical man to have a strong man wrap him up in a red-hot sheet of iron, burning, blazing, and glowing. Why is that? Because that might result in death or deadly pain. But when his body breaks up, after death, it would not cause him to be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. But when such an unethical man enjoys the use of a robe given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders, that brings him lasting harm and suffering. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

What do you think, mendicants? Which is better—to have a strong man force your mouth open with a hot iron spike and shove in a red-hot copper ball, burning, blazing, and glowing, that burns your lips, mouth, tongue, throat, and stomach before coming out below dragging your entrails? Or to enjoy almsfood given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders?”

“Sir, it would be much better to enjoy almsfood given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders. For it would be painful to have a strong man force your mouth open with a hot iron spike and shove in a red-hot copper ball, burning, blazing, and glowing, that burns your lips, mouth, tongue, throat, and stomach before coming out below dragging your entrails.”

“I declare this to you, mendicants, I announce this to you! It would be better for that unethical man to have a strong man force his mouth open with a hot iron spike and shove in a red-hot copper ball, burning, blazing, and glowing, that burns his lips, mouth, tongue, throat, and stomach before coming out below with his entrails. Why is that? Because that might result in death or deadly pain. But when his body breaks up, after death, it would not cause him to be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. But when such an unethical man enjoys almsfood given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders, that brings him lasting harm and suffering. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

What do you think, mendicants? Which is better—to have a strong man grab you by the head or shoulders and make you sit or lie down on red-hot iron bed or seat? Or to enjoy the use of beds and chairs given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders?”

“Sir, it would be much better to enjoy the use of beds and chairs given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders. For it would be painful to have a strong man grab you by the head or shoulders and make you sit or lie down on a red-hot iron bed or seat.”

“I declare this to you, mendicants, I announce this to you! It would be better for that unethical man to have a strong man grab him by the head or shoulders and make him sit or lie down on a red-hot iron bed or seat. Why is that? Because that might result in death or deadly pain. But when his body breaks up, after death, it would not cause him to be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. But when such an unethical man enjoys the use of beds and seats given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders, that brings him lasting harm and suffering. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

What do you think, mendicants? Which is better—to have a strong man grab you, turn you upside down, and shove you in a red-hot copper pot, burning, blazing, and glowing, where you’re seared in boiling scum, and swept up and down and round and round. Or to enjoy the use of dwellings given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders?”

“Sir, it would be much better to enjoy the use of dwellings given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders. For it would be painful to have a strong man grab you, turn you upside down, and shove you in a red-hot copper pot, burning, blazing, and glowing, where you’re seared in boiling scum, and swept up and down and round and round.”

“I declare this to you, mendicants, I announce this to you! It would be better for that unethical man to have a strong man grab him, turn him upside down, and shove him in a red-hot copper pot, burning, blazing, and glowing, where he’s seared in boiling scum, and swept up and down and round and round. Why is that? Because that might result in death or deadly pain. But when his body breaks up, after death, it would not cause him to be reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. But when such an unethical man enjoys the use of dwellings given in faith by well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders, that brings him lasting harm and suffering. When his body breaks up, after death, he’s reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell.

So you should train like this: ‘The services of those whose robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick we enjoy shall be very fruitful and beneficial for them. And our going forth will not be barren, but will be fruitful and fertile.’ That’s how you should train. Considering what is good for yourself, mendicants, is quite enough for you to persist with diligence. Considering what is good for others is quite enough for you to persist with diligence. Considering what is good for both is quite enough for you to persist with diligence.”

That is what the Buddha said. And while this discourse was being spoken, sixty monks spewed hot blood from their mouths. Sixty mendicants resigned the training and returned to a lesser life, saying:

“It’s too hard, Blessed One! It’s just too hard!” And sixty monks were freed from defilements by not grasping.

AN 7.73 About Sunetta Sunettasutta

“Once upon a time, mendicants, there was a teacher named Sunetta. He was a religious founder and was free of desire for sensual pleasures. He had many hundreds of disciples. He taught them a Dhamma for rebirth in the company of Divinity. Those lacking confidence in Sunetta were—when their body broke up, after death—reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. Those full of confidence in Sunetta were—when their body broke up, after death—reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

Once upon a time, there was a teacher named Mūgapakkha … Aranemi … Kuddālaka … Hatthipāla … Jotipāla … Araka. He was a religious founder and was free of desire for sensual pleasures. He had many hundreds of disciples. He taught them a Dhamma for rebirth in the company of Divinity. Those lacking confidence in Araka were—when their body broke up, after death—reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. Those full of confidence in Araka were—when their body broke up, after death—reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.

What do you think, mendicants? If someone with malicious intent were to abuse and insult these seven teachers with their hundreds of followers, would they not brim with much wickedness?”

“Yes, sir.”

“They would indeed. But someone who abuses and insults a single individual accomplished in view with malicious intent brims even more with wickedness. Why is that? I say that any injury done by those outside of the Buddhist community does not compare with what is done to one’s own spiritual companions.

So you should train like this: ‘We will have no malicious intent for our spiritual companions.’ That’s how you should train.”

AN 7.74 About Araka Arakasutta

“Once upon a time, mendicants, there was a teacher named Araka. He was a religious founder and was free of desire for sensual pleasures. He had many hundreds of disciples, and he taught them like this: ‘Brahmins, life as a human is short, brief, and fleeting, full of suffering and distress. Be thoughtful and wake up! Do what’s good and lead the spiritual life, for no one born can escape death.

It’s like a drop of dew on a grass tip. When the sun comes up it vanishes right away and doesn’t last long. In the same way, life as a human is like a dewdrop. It’s brief and fleeting, full of suffering and distress. Be thoughtful and wake up! Do what’s good and lead the spiritual life, for no one born can escape death.

It’s like when the heavens rain heavily. The bubbles vanish right away and don’t last long. In the same way, life as a human is like a bubble. …

It’s like a line drawn in water. It vanishes right away and doesn’t last long. In the same way, life as a human is like a line drawn in water. …

It’s like a mountain river traveling far, flowing fast, carrying all before it. It doesn’t turn back—not for a moment, a second, an hour—but runs, rolls, and flows on. In the same way, life as a human is like a mountain river. …

It’s like a strong man who has formed a glob of spit on the tip of his tongue. He could easily spit it out. In the same way, life as a human is like a glob of spit. …

Suppose there was an iron cauldron that had been heated all day. If you tossed a scrap of meat in, it would vanish right away and not last long. In the same way, life as a human is like a scrap of meat. …

It’s like a cow being led to the slaughterhouse. With every step she comes closer to the slaughter, closer to death. In the same way, life as a human is like a cow being slaughtered. It’s brief and fleeting, full of suffering and distress. Be thoughtful and wake up! Do what’s good and lead the spiritual life, for no one born can escape death.’

Now, mendicants, at that time human beings had a lifespan of 60,000 years. Girls could be married at 500 years of age. And human beings only had six afflictions: cold, heat, hunger, thirst, and the need to defecate and urinate. But even though humans were so long-lived with so few afflictions, Araka still taught in this way: ‘Life as a human is short, brief, and fleeting, full of suffering and distress. Be thoughtful and wake up! Do what’s good and lead the spiritual life, for no one born can escape death.’

These days it’d be right to say: ‘Life as a human is short, brief, and fleeting, full of suffering and distress. Be thoughtful and wake up! Do what’s good and lead the spiritual life, for no one born can escape death.’ For these days a long life is a hundred years or a little more. Living for a hundred years, there are just three hundred seasons, a hundred each of the winter, summer, and rains. Living for three hundred seasons, there are just twelve hundred months, four hundred in each of the winter, summer, and rains. Living for twelve hundred months, there are just twenty-four hundred fortnights, eight hundred in each of the winter, summer, and rains. Living for 2,400 fortnights, there are just 36,000 days, 12,000 in each of the summer, winter, and rains. Living for 36,000 days, you just eat 72,000 meals, 24,000 in each of the summer, winter, and rains, including when you’re suckling at the breast, and when you’re prevented from eating.

Things that prevent you from eating include anger, pain, sickness, sabbath, or being unable to get food. So mendicants, for a human being with a hundred years lifespan I have counted the lifespan, the limit of the lifespan, the seasons, the years, the months, the fortnights, the nights, the days, the meals, and the things that prevent them from eating. Out of sympathy, I’ve done what a teacher should do who wants what’s best for their disciples. Here are these roots of trees, and here are these empty huts. Practice absorption, mendicants! Don’t be negligent! Don’t regret it later! This is my instruction to you.”

The Chapter on a Great Sacrifice

AN 7.44 Planes of Consciousness Sattaviññāṇaṭṭhitisutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven planes of consciousness. What seven?

There are sentient beings that are diverse in body and diverse in perception, such as human beings, some gods, and some beings in the underworld. This is the first plane of consciousness.

There are sentient beings that are diverse in body and unified in perception, such as the gods reborn in the Divinity’s host through the first absorption. This is the second plane of consciousness.

There are sentient beings that are unified in body and diverse in perception, such as the gods of sublime luminosity. This is the third plane of consciousness.

There are sentient beings that are unified in body and unified in perception, such as the gods of universal beauty. This is the fourth plane of consciousness.

There are sentient beings that have gone totally beyond perceptions of form. With the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, they have been reborn in the dimension of infinite space. This is the fifth plane of consciousness.

There are sentient beings that have gone totally beyond the dimension of infinite space. Aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, they have been reborn in the dimension of infinite consciousness. This is the sixth plane of consciousness.

There are sentient beings that have gone totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness. Aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, they have been reborn in the dimension of nothingness. This is the seventh plane of consciousness.

These are the seven planes of consciousness.”

AN 7.45 Prerequisites for Immersion Samādhiparikkhārasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven prerequisites for immersion. What seven? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, and right mindfulness. Unification of mind with these seven factors as prerequisites is what is called noble right immersion ‘with its vital conditions’ and also ‘with its prerequisites’.”

AN 7.46 Fires (1st) Paṭhamaaggisutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven fires. What seven? The fires of greed, hate, delusion. The fire of those worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods. A householder’s fire. The fire of those worthy of a religious donation. And a wood fire. These are the seven fires.”

AN 7.47 Fires (2nd) Dutiyaaggisutta

Now at that time the brahmin Uggatasarīra had prepared a large sacrifice. Bulls, bullocks, heifers, goats and rams—five hundred of each—had been led to the post for the sacrifice.

Then the brahmin Uggatasarīra went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha, “Worthy Gotama, I have heard that kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post is very fruitful and beneficial.”

“I’ve also heard this, brahmin.”

For a second time … and third time Uggatasarīra said to the Buddha, “Worthy Gotama, I have heard that kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post is very fruitful and beneficial.”

“I’ve also heard this, brahmin.”

“Then the worthy Gotama and I are in total agreement in this matter.”

When he said this, Venerable Ānanda said to Uggatasarīra, “Brahmin, you shouldn’t ask the Buddha in this way. You should ask in this way: ‘Sir, I want to kindle the sacrificial fire and raise the sacrificial post. May the Buddha please advise and instruct me. It will be for my lasting welfare and happiness.’”

Then Uggatasarīra said to the Buddha, “Worthy Gotama, I want to kindle the sacrificial fire and raise the sacrificial post. May the worthy Gotama please advise and instruct me. It will be for my lasting welfare and happiness.”

“Even before kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post, one raises three unskillful knives which ripen and result in suffering. What three? The knives of the body, speech, and mind. Even before kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post one gives rise to the thought: ‘May this many bulls, bullocks, heifers, goats, and rams be slaughtered for the sacrifice!’ Thinking, ‘May I make goodness’, one makes wickedness. Thinking, ‘May I do good’, one does bad. Thinking, ‘May I seek the path to a good rebirth’, one seeks the path to a bad rebirth. Even before kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post one raises this first unskillful mental knife which ripens and results in suffering.

Furthermore, even before kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post, one says such things as: ‘May this many bulls, bullocks, heifers, goats, and rams be slaughtered for the sacrifice!’ Thinking, ‘May I make goodness’, one makes wickedness. Thinking, ‘May I do good’, one does bad. Thinking, ‘May I seek the path to a good rebirth’, one seeks the path to a bad rebirth. Even before kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post one raises this second unskillful verbal knife which ripens and results in suffering.

Furthermore, even before kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post one first personally undertakes preparations for the sacrificial slaughter of bulls, bullocks, heifers, goats, and rams. Thinking, ‘May I make goodness’, one makes wickedness. Thinking, ‘May I do good’, one does bad. Thinking, ‘May I seek the path to a good rebirth’, one seeks the path to a bad rebirth. Even before kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post, one raises this third unskillful bodily knife which ripens and results in suffering. Even before kindling the sacrificial fire and raising the sacrificial post, one raises these three unskillful knives which ripen and result in suffering.

Brahmin, these three fires should be given up and shunned, not cultivated. What three? The fires of greed, hate, and delusion.

And why should the fire of greed be given up and shunned, not cultivated? A greedy person does bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. That’s why the fire of greed should be given up and shunned, not cultivated.

And why should the fire of hate be given up and shunned, not cultivated? A hateful person does bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. That’s why the fire of hate should be given up and shunned, not cultivated.

And why should the fire of delusion be given up and shunned, not cultivated? A deluded person does bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. That’s why the fire of delusion should be given up and shunned, not cultivated. These three fires should be given up and shunned, not cultivated.

Brahmin, you should properly and happily take care of three fires, honoring, respecting, esteeming, and venerating them. What three? The fire of those worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods. The fire of a householder. And the fire of those worthy of a religious donation.

And what is the fire of those worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods? Your mother and father are called the fire of those worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods. Why is that? Since it is from them that you’ve been incubated and produced. So you should properly and happily take care of this fire, honoring, respecting, esteeming, and venerating it.

And what is the fire of a householder? Your children, partners, bondservants, servants, and workers are called a householder’s fire. So you should properly and happily take care of this fire, honoring, respecting, esteeming, and venerating it.

And what is the fire of those worthy of a religious donation? The ascetics and brahmins who refrain from intoxication and negligence, are settled in patience and gentleness, and who tame, calm, and extinguish themselves are called the fire of those worthy of a religious donation. So you should properly and happily take care of this fire, honoring, respecting, esteeming, and venerating it. You should properly and happily take care of these three fires, honoring, respecting, esteeming, and venerating them.

But the wood fire, brahmin, should, from time to time, be fanned, watched over with equanimity, extinguished, or put aside.”

When he said this, the brahmin Uggatasarīra said to the Buddha, “Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life. Worthy Gotama, I now set free these five hundred bulls, five hundred bullocks, five hundred heifers, five hundred goats, and five hundred rams. I give them life! May they eat grass and drink cool water and enjoy a cool breeze!”

AN 7.48 Perceptions in Brief Paṭhamasaññāsutta

“Mendicants, these seven perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination.

What seven? The perceptions of ugliness, death, repulsiveness of food, dissatisfaction with the whole world, impermanence, suffering in impermanence, and not-self in suffering. These seven perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination.”

AN 7.49 Perceptions in Detail Dutiyasaññāsutta

“Mendicants, these seven perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination. What seven? The perceptions of ugliness, death, repulsiveness of food, dissatisfaction with the whole world, impermanence, suffering in impermanence, and not-self in suffering. These seven perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. They have freedom from death as their objective and culmination.

‘When the perception of ugliness is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? When a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of ugliness, their mind draws back from sexual intercourse. They shrink away, turn aside, and don’t get drawn into it. And either equanimity or revulsion become stabilized. It’s like a chicken’s feather or a scrap of sinew thrown in a fire. It shrivels up, shrinks, rolls up, and doesn’t stretch out. In the same way, when a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of ugliness, their mind draws back from sexual intercourse. …

If a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of ugliness, but their mind is drawn to sexual intercourse, and not repulsed, they should know: ‘My perception of ugliness is undeveloped. I don’t have any distinction higher than before. I haven’t attained a fruit of development.’ In this way they are aware of the situation. But if a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of ugliness, their mind draws back from sexual intercourse … they should know: ‘My perception of ugliness is well developed. I have realized a distinction higher than before. I have attained a fruit of development.’ In this way they are aware of the situation. ‘When the perception of ugliness is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘When the perception of death is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? When a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of death, their mind draws back from desire to be reborn. … That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘When the perception of the repulsiveness of food is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? When a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of the repulsiveness of food, their mind draws back from craving for tastes. … That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘When the perception of dissatisfaction with the whole world is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? When a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of dissatisfaction with the whole world, their mind draws back from the world’s shiny things. … That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘When the perception of impermanence is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? When a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of impermanence, their mind draws back from possessions, honor, and popularity. … That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘When the perception of suffering in impermanence is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? When a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of suffering in impermanence, they establish a keen perception of the danger of sloth, laziness, slackness, negligence, lack of commitment, and failure to review, like a killer with a drawn sword. … That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘When the perception of not-self in suffering is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? When a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of not-self in suffering, their heart is rid of I-making, mine-making, and conceit for this conscious body and externally for all signs. It has gone beyond discrimination, and is peaceful and well freed.

If a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of not-self in suffering, but their heart is not rid of I-making, mine-making, and conceit for this conscious body and externally for all signs; nor has it gone beyond discrimination, and is not peaceful or well freed, they should know: ‘My perception of not-self in suffering is undeveloped. I don’t have any distinction higher than before. I haven’t attained a fruit of development.’ In this way they are aware of the situation.

But if a mendicant often meditates with a mind reinforced with the perception of not-self in suffering, and their heart is rid of I-making, mine-making, and conceit for this conscious body and externally for all signs; and it has gone beyond discrimination, and is peaceful and well freed, they should know: ‘My perception of not-self in suffering is well developed. I have realized a distinction higher than before. I have attained a fruit of development.’ In this way they are aware of the situation. ‘When the perception of not-self in suffering is developed and cultivated it’s very fruitful and beneficial. It has freedom from death as its objective and culmination.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

These seven perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. Their objective and culmination is freedom from death.”

AN 7.50 Sex Methunasutta

Then the brahmin Jānussoṇi went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha, “Does Worthy Gotama claim to be chaste?”

“Brahmin, if anyone should be rightly said to live the chaste life intact, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, full and pure, it’s me.”

“But what, Worthy Gotama, is a break, taint, stain, or mar in chastity?”

“Firstly, an ascetic or brahmin who claims to be perfectly chaste does not mutually engage in sex with a lady. However, they consent to being anointed, massaged, bathed, and rubbed by a lady. They enjoy it and like it and find it rewarding. This is a break, taint, stain, or mar in chastity. This is called one who lives the chaste life impurely, yoked by the yoke of sex. They’re not freed from rebirth, old age, death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from suffering, I say.

Furthermore, an ascetic or brahmin who claims to be perfectly chaste does not mutually engage in sex with a lady. Nor do they consent to massage and bathing. However, they giggle and play and have fun with ladies. …

they gaze into a lady’s eyes. …

they listen through a wall or rampart to the sound of ladies laughing or chatting or singing or crying. …

they recall when they used to laugh, chat, and have fun with ladies. …

they see a householder or their child amusing themselves, supplied and provided with the five kinds of sensual stimulation. …

They don’t see a householder or their child amusing themselves, supplied and provided with the five kinds of sensual stimulation. However, they live the chaste life wishing to be reborn in one of the orders of gods. They think: ‘By this precept or observance or fervent austerity or spiritual practice, may I become one of the gods!’ They enjoy it and like it and find it rewarding. This is a break, taint, stain, or mar in chastity. This is called one who lives the chaste life impurely, yoked by the yoke of sex. They’re not free from rebirth, old age, death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not free from suffering, I say.

As long as I saw that these seven sexual yokes—or even one of them—had not been given up in me, I didn’t announce my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

But when I saw that these seven sexual yokes—every one of them—had been given up in me, I announced my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans. Knowledge and vision arose in me: ‘My freedom is unshakable; this is my last rebirth; now there’ll be no more future lives.’”

When he said this, the brahmin Jānussoṇi said to the Buddha, “Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! … From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 7.51 Yoking and Unyoking Saṁyogasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you an exposition of the teaching on yoking and unyoking. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak. … And what is the exposition of the teaching on yoking and unyoking?

A woman focuses on her own femininity: her feminine moves, feminine appearance, feminine ways, feminine desires, feminine voice, and feminine adornment. She’s stimulated by this and takes pleasure in it. So she focuses on the masculinity of others: masculine moves, masculine appearance, masculine ways, masculine desires, masculine voice, and masculine adornment. She’s stimulated by this and takes pleasure in it. So she desires to yoke herself to another. And she desires the pleasure and happiness that comes from such yoking. Sentient beings who relish their femininity are yoked to men. This is how a woman does not transcend her femininity.

A man focuses on his own masculinity: his masculine moves, masculine appearance, masculine ways, masculine desires, masculine voice, and masculine adornment. He’s stimulated by this and takes pleasure in it. So he focuses on the femininity of others: feminine moves, feminine appearance, feminine ways, feminine desires, feminine voice, and feminine adornment. He’s stimulated by this and takes pleasure in it. So he desires to yoke himself to another. And he desires the pleasure and happiness that comes from such yoking. Sentient beings who relish their masculinity are yoked to women. This is how a man does not transcend his masculinity. This is how yoking comes about.

And how does unyoking come about? A woman doesn’t focus on her own femininity: her feminine moves, feminine appearance, feminine ways, feminine desires, feminine voice, and feminine adornment. She isn’t stimulated by this and takes no pleasure in it. So she doesn’t focus on the masculinity of others: masculine moves, masculine appearance, masculine ways, masculine desires, masculine voice, and masculine adornment. She isn’t stimulated by this and takes no pleasure in it. So she doesn’t desire to yoke herself to another. Nor does she desire the pleasure and happiness that comes from such yoking. Sentient beings who do not relish their femininity are not yoked to men. This is how a woman transcends her femininity.

A man doesn’t focus on his own masculinity: masculine moves, masculine appearance, masculine ways, masculine desires, masculine voice, and masculine adornment. He isn’t stimulated by this and takes no pleasure in it. So he doesn’t focus on the femininity of others: feminine moves, feminine appearance, feminine ways, feminine desires, feminine voice, and feminine adornment. He isn’t stimulated by this and takes no pleasure in it. So he doesn’t desire to yoke himself to another. Nor does he desire the pleasure and happiness that comes from such yoking. Sentient beings who do not relish their masculinity are not yoked to women. This is how a man transcends his masculinity. This is how unyoking comes about. This is the exposition of the teaching on yoking and unyoking.”

AN 7.52 A Very Fruitful Gift Dānamahapphalasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Campā on the banks of the Gaggarā Lotus Pond.

Then several lay followers of Campā went to Venerable Sāriputta, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, it’s been a long time since we’ve heard a Dhamma talk from the Buddha. It would be good if we got to hear a Dhamma talk from the Buddha.”

“Well then, reverends, come on the next sabbath day. Hopefully you’ll get to hear a Dhamma talk from the Buddha.”

“Yes, sir” they replied. Then they rose from their seats, bowed to Sāriputta, and respectfully circled him before leaving.

Then on the next sabbath the lay followers of Campā went to Venerable Sāriputta, bowed, and stood to one side. Then they went together with Sāriputta to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. Sāriputta said to the Buddha:

“Sir, could it be that someone gives a gift and it is not very fruitful or beneficial, while someone else gives exactly the same gift and it is very fruitful and beneficial?”

“Indeed it could, Sāriputta.”

“Sir, what is the cause, what is the reason for this?”

“Sāriputta, take the case of a someone who gives a gift as an investment, their mind tied to it, expecting to keep it, thinking ‘I’ll enjoy this in my next life.’ They give to ascetics or brahmins such things as food, drink, clothing, vehicles; garlands, fragrance, and makeup; and bed, house, and lighting. What do you think, Sāriputta, don’t some people give gifts in this way?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Sāriputta, someone who gives a gift as an investment, when their body breaks up, after death, is reborn in the company of the gods of the four great kings. When that deed, success, glory, and sovereignty is spent they return to this place.

Next, take the case of a someone who gives a gift not as an investment, their mind not tied to it, not expecting to keep it, and not thinking, ‘I’ll enjoy this in my next life.’ But they give a gift thinking, ‘It’s good to give.’ …

They give a gift thinking, ‘Giving was practiced by my father and my father’s father. It would not be right for me to abandon this family custom.’ …

They give a gift thinking, ‘I cook, they don’t. It wouldn’t be right for me to not give to them.’ …

They give a gift thinking, ‘The ancient brahmin seers were Aṭṭhaka, Vāmaka, Vāmadeva, Vessāmitta, Yamadaggi, Aṅgīrasa, Bhāradvāja, Vāseṭṭha, Kassapa, and Bhagu. Just as they performed great sacrifices, I will share a gift.’ …

They give a gift thinking, ‘When giving this gift my mind becomes clear, and I become happy and joyful.’ …

They don’t give a gift thinking, ‘When giving this gift my mind becomes clear, and I become happy and joyful.’ But they give a gift thinking, ‘This is an adornment and requisite for the mind.’ They give to ascetics or brahmins such things as food, drink, clothing, vehicles; garlands, fragrance, and makeup; and bed, house, and lighting. What do you think, Sāriputta, don’t some people give gifts in this way?”

“Yes, sir.”

“Sāriputta, someone who gives gifts, not for any other reason, but thinking, ‘This is an adornment and requisite for the mind’, when their body breaks up, after death, is reborn among the gods of the Divinity’s host. When that deed, success, glory, and sovereignty is spent they are a non-returner; they do not return to this place.

This is the cause, this is the reason why someone gives a gift and it is not very fruitful or beneficial, while someone else gives exactly the same gift and it is very fruitful and beneficial.”

AN 7.53 Nanda’s Mother Nandamātāsutta

So I have heard. At one time the venerables Sāriputta and Mahāmoggallāna were wandering in the Southern Hills together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants. Now at that time the laywoman Veḷukaṇṭakī, Nanda’s mother, rose at the crack of dawn and recited the verses of “The Way to the Far Shore”.

And at that time the great king Vessavaṇa was on his way from the north to the south on some business. He heard Nanda’s Mother reciting, and stood waiting for her to finish.

Then when her recital was over she fell silent. Then, knowing she had finished, Vessavaṇa applauded, saying, “Good, sister! Good, sister!”

“But who might you be, dearest?”

“Sister, I am your brother Vessavaṇa, the great king.”

“Good, dearest! Then may my recital of the teaching be my offering to you as my guest.”

“Good, sister! And let this also be your offering to me as your guest. Tomorrow, the mendicant Saṅgha headed by Sāriputta and Moggallāna will arrive at Veḷukaṇṭa before breakfast. When you’ve served the Saṅgha, please dedicate the religious donation to me. Then that will also be your offering to me as your guest.”

And when the night had passed the lay woman Nanda’s Mother had delicious fresh and cooked foods prepared in her own home. Then the Saṅgha of mendicants headed by Sāriputta and Moggallāna arrived at Veḷukaṇṭa. Then Nanda’s Mother addressed a man, “Please, my man, go to the monastery and announce the time to the Saṅgha, saying: ‘Sirs, it’s time. The meal is ready in the home of the lady Nanda’s Mother.’”

“Yes, ma’am,” that man replied, and he did as she said.

And then the Saṅgha of mendicants headed by Sāriputta and Moggallāna robed up in the morning and, taking their bowls and robes, went to the home of Nanda’s Mother, where they sat on the seats spread out. Then Nanda’s Mother served and satisfied them with her own hands with delicious fresh and cooked foods.

When Sāriputta had eaten and washed his hand and bowl, Nanda’s Mother sat down to one side. Sāriputta said to her, “Nanda’s Mother, who told you that the Saṅgha of mendicants was about to arrive?”

“Sir, last night I rose at the crack of dawn and recited the verses of ‘The Way to the Far Shore’, and then I fell silent. Then the great king Vessavaṇa, knowing I had finished, applauded me, ‘Good, sister! Good, sister!’

I asked: ‘But who might you be, dearest?’

‘Sister, I am your brother Vessavaṇa, the great king.’

‘Good, dearest! Then may my recital of the teaching be my offering to you as my guest.’

‘Good, sister! And let this also be your offering to me as your guest. Tomorrow, the mendicant Saṅgha headed by Sāriputta and Moggallāna will arrive at Veḷukaṇṭa before breakfast. When you’ve served the Saṅgha, please dedicate the religious donation to me. Then that will also be your offering to me as your guest.’

And so, sir, may the merit and the flourishing of merit of this gift be for the happiness of the great king Vessavaṇa.”

“It’s incredible, Nanda’s Mother, it’s amazing that you converse face to face with a mighty and illustrious godling like the great king Vessavaṇa.”

“Sir, this is not my only incredible and amazing quality; there is another. I had an only son named Nanda who I loved dearly. The rulers forcibly abducted him on some pretext and had him executed. But I can’t recall getting upset when my boy was under arrest or being arrested, imprisoned or being put in prison, killed or being killed.”

“It’s incredible, Nanda’s Mother, it’s amazing that you purify even the arising of a thought.”

“Sir, this is not my only incredible and amazing quality; there is another. When my husband passed away he was reborn in one of the realms of spirits. He revealed to me his previous incarnation. But I can’t recall getting upset on that account.”

“It’s incredible, Nanda’s Mother, it’s amazing that you purify even the arising of a thought.”

“Sir, this is not my only incredible and amazing quality; there is another. Ever since we were both young, and I was given in marriage to my husband, I can’t recall betraying him even in thought, still less in deed.”

“It’s incredible, Nanda’s Mother, it’s amazing that you purify even the arising of a thought.”

“Sir, this is not my only incredible and amazing quality; there is another. Ever since I declared myself a lay follower, I can’t recall deliberately breaking any precept.”

“It’s incredible, Nanda’s Mother, it’s amazing!”

“Sir, this is not my only incredible and amazing quality; there is another. Whenever I want, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, I enter and remain in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, I enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected. And with the fading away of rapture, I enter and remain in the third absorption, where I meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.’ With the giving up of pleasure and pain, and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, I enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness.”

“It’s incredible, Nanda’s Mother, it’s amazing!”

“Sir, this is not my only incredible and amazing quality; there is another. Of the five lower fetters taught by the Buddha, I don’t see any that I haven’t given up.”

“It’s incredible, Nanda’s Mother, it’s amazing!”

Then Venerable Sāriputta educated, encouraged, fired up, and inspired Nanda’s Mother with a Dhamma talk, after which he rose from his seat and left.

The First Fifty

The Chapter on Wealth

AN 7.1 Pleasing (1st) Paṭhamapiyasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities is disliked and disapproved by their spiritual companions, not respected or admired. What seven? It’s when a mendicant desires material things, honor, and status. They lack conscience and prudence. They have corrupt wishes and wrong view. A mendicant with these seven qualities is disliked and disapproved by their spiritual companions, not respected or admired.

A mendicant with seven qualities is liked and approved by their spiritual companions, respected and admired. What seven? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t desire material things, honor, and status. They have conscience and prudence. They have few desires and right view. A mendicant with these seven qualities is liked and approved by their spiritual companions, respected and admired.”

AN 7.2 Pleasing (2nd) Dutiyapiyasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities is disliked and disapproved by their spiritual companions, not respected or admired. What seven? It’s when a mendicant desires material things, honor, and status. They lack conscience and prudence. They’re jealous and stingy. A mendicant with these seven qualities is disliked and disapproved by their spiritual companions, not respected or admired.

A mendicant with seven qualities is liked and approved by their spiritual companions, respected and admired. What seven? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t desire material things, honor, and status. They have conscience and prudence. They’re not jealous or stingy. A mendicant with these seven qualities is liked and approved by their spiritual companions, respected and admired.”

AN 7.3 Powers in Brief Saṁkhittabalasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. … “Mendicants, there are these seven powers. What seven? The powers of faith, energy, conscience, prudence, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom. These are the seven powers.

The powers are faith and energy,
conscience and prudence,
mindfulness and immersion,
and wisdom as the seventh power.
Empowered by these,
an astute mendicant lives happily.

They should examine the teaching rationally,
discerning the meaning with wisdom.
The liberation of their heart
is like a lamp going out.”

AN 7.4 Powers in Detail Vitthatabalasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven powers. What seven? The powers of faith, energy, conscience, prudence, mindfulness, immersion, and wisdom.

And what is the power of faith? It’s when a noble disciple has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ This is called the power of faith.

And what is the power of energy? It’s when a noble disciple lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They’re strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. This is called the power of energy.

And what is the power of conscience? It’s when a noble disciple has a conscience. They’re conscientious about bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind, and conscientious about acquiring any bad, unskillful qualities. This is called the power of conscience.

And what is the power of prudence? It’s when a noble disciple is prudent. They’re prudent when it comes to bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind, and prudent when it comes to the acquiring of any bad, unskillful qualities. This is called the power of prudence.

And what is the power of mindfulness? It’s when a noble disciple is mindful. They have utmost mindfulness and alertness, and can remember and recall what was said and done long ago. This is called the power of mindfulness.

And what is the power of immersion? It’s when a noble disciple, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. … With the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, they enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness. This is called the power of immersion.

And what is the power of wisdom? It’s when a noble disciple is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is called the power of wisdom.

These are the seven powers.

The powers are faith and energy,
conscience and prudence,
mindfulness and immersion,
and wisdom as the seventh power.
Empowered by these,
an astute mendicant lives happily.

They should examine the teaching rationally,
discerning the meaning with wisdom.
The liberation of their heart
is like a lamp going out.”

AN 7.5 Wealth in Brief Saṁkhittadhanasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven kinds of wealth. What seven? The wealth of faith, ethics, conscience, prudence, learning, generosity, and wisdom. These are the seven kinds of wealth.

Faith and ethical conduct are kinds of wealth,
as are conscience and prudence,
learning and generosity,
and wisdom is the seventh kind of wealth.

When a woman or man
has these kinds of wealth,
they’re said to be prosperous,
their life is not in vain.

So let the wise devote themselves
to faith, ethical behavior,
confidence, and insight into the teaching,
remembering the instructions of the Buddhas.”

AN 7.6 Wealth in Detail Vitthatadhanasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven kinds of wealth. What seven? The wealth of faith, ethics, conscience, prudence, learning, generosity, and wisdom.

And what is the wealth of faith? It’s when a noble disciple has faith in the Realized One’s awakening … This is called the wealth of faith.

And what is the wealth of ethical conduct? It’s when a noble disciple doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, use speech that’s false, backbiting, harsh, or nonsensical, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. This is called the wealth of ethical conduct.

And what is the wealth of conscience? It’s when a noble disciple has a conscience. They’re conscientious about bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind, and conscientious about having any bad, unskillful qualities. This is called the wealth of conscience.

And what is the wealth of prudence? It’s when a noble disciple is prudent. They’re prudent when it comes to bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind, and prudent when it comes to the acquiring of any bad, unskillful qualities. This is called the wealth of prudence.

And what is the wealth of learning? It’s when a noble disciple is very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. This is called the wealth of learning.

And what is the wealth of generosity? It’s when a noble disciple lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. This is called the wealth of generosity.

And what is the wealth of wisdom? It’s when a noble disciple is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is called the wealth of wisdom.

These are the seven kinds of wealth.

Faith and ethical conduct are kinds of wealth,
as are conscience and prudence,
learning and generosity,
and wisdom is the seventh kind of wealth.

When a woman or man
has these kinds of wealth,
they’re said to be prosperous,
their life is not in vain.

So let the wise devote themselves
to faith, ethical behavior,
confidence, and insight into the teaching,
remembering the instructions of the Buddhas.”

AN 7.7 With Ugga Uggasutta

Then Ugga the government chief minister went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! Migāra of Rohaṇa is so rich, so very wealthy.”

“But Ugga, how rich is he?”

“He has a hundred thousand gold coins, not to mention the silver coins!”

“Well, Ugga, that is wealth, I can’t deny it. But fire, water, rulers, thieves, and unloved heirs all take a share of that wealth. There are these seven kinds of wealth that they can’t take a share of. What seven? The wealth of faith, ethics, conscience, prudence, learning, generosity, and wisdom. There are these seven kinds of wealth that fire, water, rulers, thieves, and unloved heirs can’t take a share of.

Faith and ethical conduct are kinds of wealth,
as are conscience and prudence,
learning and generosity,
and wisdom is the seventh kind of wealth.

When a woman or man
has these kinds of wealth,
they’re really rich in the world,
invincible among gods and humans.

So let the wise devote themselves
to faith, ethical behavior,
confidence, and insight into the teaching,
remembering the instructions of the Buddhas.”

AN 7.8 Fetters Saṁyojanasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven fetters. What seven? The fetters of attraction, aversion, views, doubt, conceit, desire for continued existence, and ignorance. These are the seven fetters.”

AN 7.9 Giving Up Pahānasutta

“Mendicants, the spiritual life is lived to give up and cut out these seven fetters. What seven? The fetters of attraction, aversion, views, doubt, conceit, desire to be reborn, and ignorance. The spiritual life is lived to give up and cut out these seven fetters. When a mendicant has given up the fetters of attraction, repulsion, views, doubt, conceit, desire to be reborn, and ignorance—cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so they are unable to arise in the future—they’re called a mendicant who has cut off craving, cast off the fetters, and by rightly comprehending conceit has made an end of suffering.”

AN 7.10 Stinginess Macchariyasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven fetters. What seven? The fetters of attraction, aversion, views, doubt, conceit, jealousy, and stinginess. These are the seven fetters.”

Abbreviated Texts Beginning With Greed

AN 7.615 Untitled Discourse on Greed (1st) ~

“Mendicants, for insight into greed, seven things should be developed. What seven? The awakening factor of mindfulness … the awakening factor of equanimity. These seven things should be developed for insight into greed.”

AN 7.616 Untitled Discourse on Greed (2nd) ~

“Mendicants, for insight into greed, seven things should be developed. What seven? The perception of impermanence, the perception of not-self, the perception of ugliness, the perception of drawbacks, the perception of giving up, the perception of fading away, and the perception of cessation. These seven things should be developed for insight into greed.”

AN 7.617 Untitled Discourse on Greed (3rd) ~

“Mendicants, for insight into greed, seven things should be developed. What seven? The perceptions of ugliness, death, repulsiveness of food, dissatisfaction with the whole world, impermanence, suffering in impermanence, and not-self in suffering. These seven things should be developed for insight into greed.”

AN 7.618–644 Untitled Discourses on Greed ~

“For the complete understanding of greed … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … For the letting go of greed, these seven things should be developed.”

AN 7.645–1124 Untitled Discourses on Hate, Etc. ~

“For insight into hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … jealousy … stinginess … deceitfulness … deviousness … obstinacy … aggression … conceit … arrogance … vanity …

For insight into negligence … complete understanding … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … For the letting go of negligence these seven things should be developed.”

That is what the Buddha said. Satisfied, the mendicants approved what the Buddha said.

The Book of the Sevens is finished.

The Chapter on the Vajji Seven

AN 7.21 At Sārandada Sārandadasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Sārandada Shrine. Then several Licchavis went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and the Buddha said to these Licchavis:

“Licchavis, I will teach you these seven principles that prevent decline. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what are the seven principles that prevent decline? As long as the Vajjis meet frequently and have many meetings, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the Vajjis meet in harmony, leave in harmony, and carry on their business in harmony, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the Vajjis don’t make new decrees or abolish existing decrees, but proceed having undertaken the ancient Vajjian principles as they have been decreed, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the Vajjis honor, respect, esteem, and venerate Vajjian elders, and think them worth listening to, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the Vajjis don’t forcibly abduct the women or girls of the clans and make them live with them, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the Vajjis honor, respect, esteem, and venerate the Vajjian shrines, whether inner or outer, not neglecting the proper spirit-offerings that were given and made in the past, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the Vajjis organize proper protection, shelter, and security for perfected ones, so that more perfected ones might come to the realm and those already here may live in comfort, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as these seven principles that prevent decline last among the Vajjis, and as long as the Vajjis are seen following them, they can expect growth, not decline.”

AN 7.22 With Vassakāra Vassakārasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain.

Now at that time King Ajātasattu of Magadha, son of the princess of Videha, wanted to invade the Vajjis. He said: “I shall wipe out these Vajjis, so mighty and powerful! I shall destroy them, and lay ruin and devastation upon them!”

And then King Ajātasattu addressed Vassakāra the brahmin, a chief minister of Magadha, “Please, brahmin, go to the Buddha, and in my name bow with your head to his feet. Ask him if he is healthy and well, nimble, strong, and living comfortably. And then say: ‘Sir, King Ajātasattu of Magadha, son of the princess of Videha, wants to invade the Vajjis. He said: “I shall wipe out these Vajjis, so mighty and powerful! I shall destroy them, and lay ruin and devastation upon them!”’ Remember well how the Buddha answers and tell it to me. For Realized Ones say nothing that is not so.”

“Yes, worthy sir,” Vassakāra replied. He went to the Buddha and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, King Ajātasattu bows with his head to your feet. He asks if you are healthy and well, nimble, strong, and living comfortably. King Ajātasattu wants to invade the Vajjis. He said: ‘I shall wipe out these Vajjis, so mighty and powerful! I shall destroy them, and lay ruin and devastation upon them!’”

Now at that time Venerable Ānanda was standing behind the Buddha fanning him. Then the Buddha said to him: “Ānanda, have you heard that the Vajjis meet frequently and have many meetings?”

“I have heard that, sir.”

“As long as the Vajjis meet frequently and have many meetings, they can expect growth, not decline.

Ānanda, have you heard that the Vajjis meet in harmony, leave in harmony, and carry on their business in harmony?”

“I have heard that, sir.”

“As long as the Vajjis meet in harmony, leave in harmony, and carry on their business in harmony, they can expect growth, not decline.

Ānanda, have you heard that the Vajjis don’t make new decrees or abolish existing decrees, but proceed having undertaken the ancient Vajjian principles as they have been decreed?”

“I have heard that, sir.”

“As long as the Vajjis don’t make new decrees or abolish existing decrees, but proceed having undertaken the ancient Vajjian principles as they have been decreed, they can expect growth, not decline.

Ānanda, have you heard that the Vajjis honor, respect, esteem, and venerate Vajjian elders, and think them worth listening to?”

“I have heard that, sir.”

“As long as the Vajjis honor, respect, esteem, and venerate Vajjian elders, and think them worth listening to, they can expect growth, not decline.

Ānanda, have you heard that the Vajjis don’t forcibly abduct the women or girls of the clans and make them live with them?”

“I have heard that, sir.”

“As long as the Vajjis don’t forcibly abduct the women or girls of the clans and make them live with them, they can expect growth, not decline.

Ānanda, have you heard that the Vajjis honor, respect, esteem, and venerate the Vajjian shrines, whether inner or outer, not neglecting the proper spirit-offerings that were given and made in the past?”

“I have heard that, sir.”

“As long as the Vajjis honor, respect, esteem, and venerate the Vajjian shrines, whether inner or outer, not neglecting the proper spirit-offerings that were given and made in the past, they can expect growth, not decline.

Ānanda, have you heard that the Vajjis organize proper protection, shelter, and security for perfected ones, so that more perfected ones might come to the realm and those already here may live in comfort?”

“I have heard that, sir.”

“As long as the Vajjis organize proper protection, shelter, and security for perfected ones, so that more perfected ones might come to the realm and those already here may live in comfort, they can expect growth, not decline.”

Then the Buddha said to Vassakāra:

“Brahmin, this one time I was staying near Vesālī at the Sārandada Shrine. There I taught the Vajjis these principles that prevent decline. As long as these seven principles that prevent decline last among the Vajjis, and as long as the Vajjis are seen following them, they can expect growth, not decline.”

When the Buddha had spoken, Vassakāra said to him: “Worthy Gotama, if the Vajjis follow even a single one of these principles they can expect growth, not decline. How much more so all seven! King Ajātasattu cannot defeat the Vajjis in war, unless by bribery or by sowing dissension. Well, now, worthy Gotama, I must go. I have many duties, and much to do.”

“Please, brahmin, go at your convenience.” Then Vassakāra the brahmin, having approved and agreed with what the Buddha said, rose from his seat and left.

AN 7.23 Non-Decline for Mendicants (1st) Paṭhamasattakasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, I will teach you these seven principles that prevent decline. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“What are the seven principles that prevent decline? As long as the mendicants meet frequently and have many meetings, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the mendicants meet in harmony, leave in harmony, and carry on their business in harmony, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the mendicants don’t make new decrees or abolish existing decrees, but proceed having undertaken the training rules as they have been decreed, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the mendicants honor, respect, esteem, and venerate the senior mendicants—of long standing, long gone forth, fathers and leaders of the Saṅgha—and think them worth listening to, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the mendicants don’t fall under the sway of arisen craving for future lives, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the mendicants take care to live in wilderness lodgings, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as the mendicants individually establish mindfulness, so that more good-hearted spiritual companions might come, and those that have already come may live comfortably, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as these seven principles that prevent decline last among the mendicants, and as long as the mendicants are seen following them, they can expect growth, not decline.”

AN 7.24 Non-Decline for Mendicants (2nd) Dutiyasattakasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you seven principles that prevent decline. Listen and apply your mind well … And what are the seven principles that prevent decline?

As long as the mendicants don’t relish work, loving it and liking to relish it, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as they don’t enjoy talk … sleep … company … they don’t have corrupt wishes, falling under the sway of corrupt wishes … they don’t have bad friends, companions, and associates … they don’t stop half-way after achieving some trifling distinction, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as these seven principles that prevent decline last among the mendicants, and as long as the mendicants are seen following them, they can expect growth, not decline.”

AN 7.25 Non-Decline for Mendicants (3rd) Tatiyasattakasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you seven principles that prevent decline. Listen and apply your mind well … And what are the seven principles that prevent decline? As long as the mendicants are faithful … conscientious … prudent … learned … energetic … mindful … wise, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as these seven principles that prevent decline last among the mendicants, and as long as the mendicants are seen following them, they can expect growth, not decline.”

AN 7.26 Awakening Factors Bojjhaṅgasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you seven principles that prevent decline. Listen and apply your mind well … And what are the seven principles that prevent decline? As long as the mendicants develop the awakening factor of mindfulness … investigation of principles … energy … rapture … tranquility … immersion … equanimity, they can expect growth, not decline.

As long as these seven principles that prevent decline last among the mendicants, and as long as the mendicants are seen following them, they can expect growth, not decline.”

AN 7.27 Perceptions Saññāsutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you seven principles that prevent decline. Listen and apply your mind well … And what are the seven principles that prevent decline? As long as the mendicants develop the perception of impermanence …

not-self … ugliness … drawbacks … giving up … fading away … cessation, they can expect growth, not decline. As long as these seven principles that prevent decline last among the mendicants, and as long as the mendicants are seen following them, they can expect growth, not decline.”

AN 7.28 Non-decline for a Mendicant Trainee Paṭhamaparihānisutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“These seven things lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee. What seven? They relish work, talk, sleep, and company. They don’t guard the sense doors and they eat too much. And when there is Saṅgha business to be carried out, they don’t reflect: ‘There are senior mendicants in the Saṅgha of long standing, long gone forth, responsible. They’ll be known for taking care of this.’ So they get involved in that. These seven things lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.

These seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee. What seven? They don’t relish work, talk, sleep, and company. They guard the sense doors and don’t eat too much. And when there is Saṅgha business to be carried out, they reflect: ‘There are senior mendicants in the Saṅgha of long standing, long gone forth, responsible. They’ll be known for taking care of this.’ So they don’t get involved in that. These seven things don’t lead to the decline of a mendicant trainee.”

AN 7.29 Non-decline for a Lay Follower Dutiyaparihānisutta

“These seven things lead to the decline of a lay follower. What seven? They miss out on seeing the mendicants. They neglect listening to the true teaching. They don’t train in higher ethical conduct. They’re very suspicious about mendicants, whether senior, junior, or middle. They listen to the teaching with a hostile, fault-finding mind. They seek outside of the Buddhist community for those worthy of religious donations. And they serve them first. These seven things lead to the decline of a lay follower.

These seven things don’t lead to the decline of a lay follower. What seven? They don’t miss out on seeing the mendicants. They don’t neglect listening to the true teaching. They train in higher ethical conduct. They’re very confident about mendicants, whether senior, junior, or middle. They don’t listen to the teaching with a hostile, fault-finding mind. They don’t seek outside of the Buddhist community for those worthy of religious donations. And they serve the Buddhist community first. These seven things don’t lead to the decline of a lay follower.”

That is what the Buddha said. Then the Holy One, the Teacher, went on to say:

“A lay follower misses out on seeing
those who are evolved
and listening to the teachings of the Noble One.
They don’t train in higher ethical conduct,

and their suspicion about mendicants
just grows and grows.
They want to listen to the true teaching
with a fault-finding mind.

They seek outside the Buddhist community
for someone else worthy of religious donations,
and that lay follower
serves them first.

These seven principles leading to decline
have been well taught.
A lay follower who practices them
falls away from the true teaching.

A lay follower doesn’t miss out on seeing
those who are evolved
and listening to the teachings of the Noble One.
They train in higher ethical conduct,

and their confidence in mendicants
just grows and grows.
They want to listen to the true teaching
without a fault-finding mind.

They don’t seek outside the Buddhist community
for someone else worthy of religious donations,
and that lay follower
serves the Buddhist community first.

These seven principles that prevent decline
have been well taught.
A lay follower who practices them
doesn’t fall away from the true teaching.”

AN 7.30 Failures for a Lay Follower Vipattisutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven failures for a lay follower …

There are these seven accomplishments for a lay follower …”

AN 7.31 Downfalls for a Lay Follower Parābhavasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven downfalls for a lay follower … There are these seven successes for a lay follower. What seven?

They don’t miss out on seeing the mendicants.

They don’t neglect listening to the true teaching.

They train in higher ethical conduct.

They’re very confident about mendicants, whether senior, junior, or middle.

They don’t listen to the teaching with a hostile, fault-finding mind.

They don’t seek outside of the Buddhist community for those worthy of religious donations.

And they serve the Buddhist community first.

These are the seven successes for a lay follower.

A lay follower misses out on seeing
those who are evolved
and listening to the teachings of the Noble One.
They don’t train in higher ethical conduct,

and their suspicion about mendicants
just grows and grows.
They want to listen to the true teaching
with a fault-finding mind.

They seek outside the Buddhist community
for someone else worthy of religious donations,
and that lay follower
serves them first.

These seven principles leading to decline
have been well taught.
A lay follower who practices these
falls away from the true teaching.

A lay follower doesn’t miss out on seeing
those who are evolved
and listening to the teachings of the Noble One.
They train in higher ethical conduct,

and their confidence in mendicants
just grows and grows.
They want to listen to the true teaching
without a fault-finding mind.

They don’t seek outside the Buddhist community
for someone else worthy of religious donations,
and that lay follower
serves the Buddhist community first.

These seven principles that prevent decline
have been well taught.
A lay follower who practices them
doesn’t fall away from the true teaching.”

The Chapter on the Monastic Law

AN 7.75 An Expert in the Monastic Law (1st) Paṭhamavinayadharasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities is an expert in the monastic law. What seven? They know what is an offense. They know what is not an offense. They know what is a light offense. They know what is a serious offense. They’re ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these seven qualities is an expert in the monastic law.”

AN 7.76 An Expert in the Monastic Law (2nd) Dutiyavinayadharasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities is an expert in the monastic law. What seven? They know what is an offense. They know what is not an offense. They know what is a light offense. They know what is a heavy offense. Both monastic codes have been passed down to them in detail, well analyzed, well mastered, well evaluated in both the rules and accompanying material. They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these seven qualities is an expert in the monastic law.”

AN 7.77 An Expert in the Monastic Law (3rd) Tatiyavinayadharasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities is an expert in the monastic law. What seven? They know what is an offense. They know what is not an offense. They know what is a light offense. They know what is a heavy offense. They’re firm and unfaltering in the training. They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these seven qualities is an expert in the monastic law.”

AN 7.78 An Expert in the Monastic Law (4th) Catutthavinayadharasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities is an expert in the monastic law. What seven? They know what is an offense. They know what is not an offense. They know what is a light offense. They know what is a heavy offense. They recollect their many kinds of past lives, with features and details. With clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, they understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these seven qualities is an expert in the monastic law.”

AN 7.79 Shines as an Expert in the Monastic Law (1st) Paṭhamavinayadharasobhanasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities shines as an expert in the monastic law. What seven? They know what is an offense. They know what is not an offense. They know what is a light offense. They know what is a heavy offense. They’re ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places; seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in the present life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these seven qualities shines as an expert in the monastic law.”

AN 7.80 Shines as an Expert in the Monastic Law (2nd) Dutiyavinayadharasobhanasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities shines as an expert in the monastic law. What seven? They know what is an offense. They know what is not an offense. They know what is a light offense. They know what is a heavy offense. Both monastic codes have been passed down to them in detail, well analyzed, well mastered, well evaluated in both the rules and accompanying material. They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in the present life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these seven qualities shines as an expert in the monastic law.”

AN 7.81 Shines as an Expert in the Monastic Law (3rd) Tatiyavinayadharasobhanasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities shines as an expert in the monastic law. What seven? They know what is an offense. They know what is not an offense. They know what is a light offense. They know what is a serious offense. They’re firm and unfaltering in the training. They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in the present life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these seven qualities shines as an expert in the monastic law.”

AN 7.82 Shines as an Expert in the Monastic Law (4th) Catutthavinayadharasobhanasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with seven qualities shines as an expert in the monastic law. What seven? They know what is an offense. They know what is not an offense. They know what is a light offense. They know what is a heavy offense. They recollect their many kinds of past lives, with features and details. With clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, they understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds. They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. A mendicant with these seven qualities shines as an expert in the monastic law.”

AN 7.83 The Teacher’s Instructions Satthusāsanasutta

Then Venerable Upāli went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief. When I’ve heard it, I’ll live alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute.”

“Upāli, you might know that certain things don’t lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. Categorically, you should remember these things as not the teaching, not the training, and not the Teacher’s instructions. You might know that certain things do lead solely to disillusionment, dispassion, cessation, peace, insight, awakening, and extinguishment. Categorically, you should remember these things as the teaching, the training, and the Teacher’s instructions.”

AN 7.84 The Settling of Disciplinary Issues Adhikaraṇasamathasutta

“Mendicants, there are these seven principles for settling any disciplinary issues that might arise. What seven? Resolution face-to-face to be applied. Resolution through recollection to be granted. Resolution because of past insanity to be granted. Acting according to what has been admitted. Majority decision. Further penalty. Covering over as if with grass. These are the seven principles for settling any disciplinary issues that might arise.”

The Chapter on Earthquakes

AN 8.61 Desire Icchāsutta

“Mendicants, these eight individuals are found in the world. What eight?

First, when a mendicant stays secluded, living independently, a desire arises for material things. They try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. But material things don’t come to them. And so they sorrow and wail and lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion because they don’t get those material things. This is called a mendicant who lives desiring material things. They try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. But when they do not acquire material things, they sorrow and lament. They’ve fallen from the true teaching.

Next, when a mendicant stays secluded, living independently, a desire arises for material things. They try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. And material things do come to them. And so they become indulgent and fall into negligence regarding those material things. This is called a mendicant who lives desiring material things. They try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. And when they acquire material things, they become intoxicated and negligent. They’ve fallen from the true teaching.

Next, when a mendicant stays secluded, living independently, a desire arises for material things. They don’t try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. And material things don’t come to them. And so they sorrow and wail and lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion because they don’t get those material things. This is called a mendicant who lives desiring material things. They don’t try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. And when they do not acquire material things, they sorrow and lament. They’ve fallen from the true teaching.

Next, when a mendicant stays secluded, living independently, a desire arises for material things. They don’t try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. But material things do come to them. And so they become indulgent and fall into negligence regarding those material things. This is called a mendicant who lives desiring material things. They don’t try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. But when they acquire material things, they become intoxicated and negligent. They’ve fallen from the true teaching.

Next, when a mendicant stays secluded, living independently, a desire arises for material things. They try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. But material things don’t come to them. But they don’t sorrow and wail and lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion because they don’t get those material things. This is called a mendicant who lives desiring material things. They try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. But when they do not acquire material things, they don’t sorrow and lament. They haven’t fallen from the true teaching.

Next, when a mendicant stays secluded, living independently, a desire arises for material things. They try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. And material things do come to them. But they don’t become indulgent and fall into negligence regarding those material things. This is called a mendicant who lives desiring material things. They try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. But when they acquire material things, they don’t become intoxicated and negligent. They haven’t fallen from the true teaching.

Next, when a mendicant stays secluded, living independently, a desire arises for material things. They don’t try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. And material things don’t come to them. But they don’t sorrow and wail and lament, beating their breast and falling into confusion because they don’t get those material things. This is called a mendicant who lives desiring material things. They don’t try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. And when they do not acquire material things, they don’t sorrow and lament. They haven’t fallen from the true teaching.

Next, when a mendicant stays secluded, living independently, a desire arises for material things. They don’t try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. But material things do come to them. But they don’t become indulgent and fall into negligence regarding those material things. This is called a mendicant who lives desiring material things. They don’t try hard, strive, and make an effort to get them. And when they acquire material things, they don’t become intoxicated and negligent. They haven’t fallen from the true teaching.

These are the eight individuals found in the world.”

AN 8.62 Good Enough Alaṁsutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with six qualities is good enough for themselves and others. What six? A mendicant is quick-witted when it comes to skillful teachings. They readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard. They examine the meaning of teachings they’ve memorized. Understanding the meaning and the teaching, they practice in line with the teaching. They’re a good speaker who enunciates well. Their voice is polished, clear, articulate, and expresses the meaning. They educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these six qualities is good enough for themselves and others.

A mendicant with five qualities is good enough for themselves and others. What five? A mendicant is not quick-witted when it comes to skillful teachings. They readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard. They examine the meaning of teachings they’ve memorized. Understanding the meaning and the teaching, they practice in line with the teaching. They’re a good speaker. Their voice is polished, clear, articulate, and expresses the meaning. They educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these five qualities is good enough for themselves and others.

A mendicant with four qualities is good enough for themselves but not for others. What four? A mendicant is quick-witted when it comes to skillful teachings. They readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard. They examine the meaning of teachings they’ve memorized. Understanding the meaning and the teaching, they practice in line with the teaching. But they’re not a good speaker and do not enunciate well. Their voice isn’t polished, clear, articulate, and doesn’t express the meaning. They don’t educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these four qualities is good enough for themselves but not for others.

A mendicant with four qualities is good enough for others but not for themselves. What four? A mendicant is quick-witted when it comes to skillful teachings. They readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard. But they don’t examine the meaning of teachings they’ve memorized. Not understanding the meaning and the teaching, they don’t practice in line with the teaching. They’re a good speaker who enunciates well. Their voice is polished, clear, articulate, and expresses the meaning. They educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these four qualities is good enough for others but not for themselves.

A mendicant with three qualities is good enough for themselves but not for others. What three? A mendicant is not quick-witted when it comes to skillful teachings. They readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard. They examine the meaning of teachings they’ve memorized. Understanding the meaning and the teaching, they practice in line with the teaching. But they’re not a good speaker and do not enunciate well. Their voice isn’t polished, clear, articulate, and doesn’t express the meaning. They don’t educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these three qualities is good enough for themselves but not for others.

A mendicant with three qualities is good enough for others but not for themselves. What three? A mendicant is not quick-witted when it comes to skillful teachings. They readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard. But they don’t examine the meaning of teachings they’ve memorized. Not understanding the meaning and the teaching, they don’t practice in line with the teaching. They’re a good speaker. Their voice is polished, clear, articulate, and expresses the meaning. They educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these three qualities is good enough for others but not for themselves.

A mendicant with two qualities is good enough for themselves but not for others. What two? A mendicant is not quick-witted when it comes to skillful teachings. And they don’t readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard. But they examine the meaning of teachings they have memorized. Understanding the meaning and the teaching, they practice in line with the teaching. They’re not a good speaker. Their voice isn’t polished, clear, articulate, and doesn’t express the meaning. They don’t educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these two qualities is good enough for themselves but not for others.

A mendicant with two qualities is good enough for others but not for themselves. What two? A mendicant is not quick-witted when it comes to skillful teachings. And they don’t readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard. Nor do they examine the meaning of teachings they’ve memorized. Not understanding the meaning and the teaching, they don’t practice in line with the teaching. But they’re a good speaker who enunciates well. Their voice is polished, clear, articulate, and expresses the meaning. They educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these two qualities is good enough for others but not for themselves.”

AN 8.63 A Teaching in Brief Saṁkhittasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief. When I’ve heard it, I’ll live alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute.”

“This is exactly how some futile people ask me for something. But when the teaching has been explained they think only of following me around.”

“Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief! May the Holy One teach me the Dhamma in brief! Hopefully I can understand the meaning of what the Buddha says! Hopefully I can be an heir of the Buddha’s teaching!”

“Well then, mendicant, you should train like this: ‘My mind will be steady and well settled internally. And bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen will not occupy my mind.’ That’s how you should train.

When your mind is steady and well settled internally, and bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen don’t occupy your mind, then you should train like this: ‘I will develop the heart’s release by love. I’ll cultivate it, make it my vehicle and my basis, keep it up, consolidate it, and properly implement it.’ That’s how you should train.

When this immersion is developed and cultivated in this way, you should develop it while placing the mind and keeping it connected. You should develop it without placing the mind, merely keeping it connected. You should develop it without placing the mind or keeping it connected. You should develop it with rapture. You should develop it without rapture. You should develop it with pleasure. You should develop it with equanimity.

When this immersion is well developed in this way, you should train like this: ‘I will develop the heart’s release by compassion …’ … ‘I will develop the heart’s release by rejoicing …’ … ‘I will develop the heart’s release by equanimity. I’ll cultivate it, make it my vehicle and my basis, keep it up, consolidate it, and properly implement it.’ That’s how you should train.

When this immersion is well developed in this way, you should develop it while placing the mind and keeping it connected. You should develop it without placing the mind, merely keeping it connected. You should develop it without placing the mind or keeping it connected. You should develop it with rapture. You should develop it without rapture. You should develop it with pleasure. You should develop it with equanimity.

When this immersion is well developed in this way, you should train like this: ‘I’ll meditate observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.’ That’s how you should train.

When this immersion is developed and cultivated in this way, you should develop it while placing the mind and keeping it connected. You should develop it without placing the mind, merely keeping it connected. You should develop it without placing the mind or keeping it connected. You should develop it with rapture. You should develop it without rapture. You should develop it with pleasure. You should develop it with equanimity.

When this immersion is well developed in this way, you should train like this: ‘I’ll meditate on an aspect of feelings …’ … ‘I’ll meditate on an aspect of the mind …’ … ‘I’ll meditate on an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world.’ That’s how you should train.

When this immersion is developed and cultivated in this way, you should develop it while placing the mind and keeping it connected. You should develop it without placing the mind, merely keeping it connected. You should develop it without placing the mind or keeping it connected. You should develop it with rapture. You should develop it without rapture. You should develop it with pleasure. You should develop it with equanimity.

When this immersion is well developed in this way, wherever you walk, you’ll walk comfortably. Wherever you stand, you’ll stand comfortably. Wherever you sit, you’ll sit comfortably. Wherever you lie down, you’ll lie down comfortably.”

When that mendicant had been given this advice by the Buddha, he rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

Then that mendicant, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And that mendicant became one of the perfected.

AN 8.64 At Gayā Head Gayāsīsasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Gayā on Gayā Head. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, before my awakening—when I was still not awake but intent on awakening—I perceived light but did not see forms.

Then it occurred to me, ‘What if I were to both perceive light and see forms? Then my knowledge and vision would become even more purified.’

So after some time, living diligent, keen, and resolute, I perceived light and saw forms. But I didn’t associate with those deities, converse, or engage in discussion.

Then it occurred to me, ‘What if I were to perceive light and see forms; and associate with those deities, converse, and engage in discussion? Then my knowledge and vision would become even more purified.’

So after some time … I perceived light and saw forms. And I associated with those deities, conversed, and engaged in discussion. But I didn’t know which orders of gods those deities came from.

Then it occurred to me, ‘What if I were to perceive light and see forms; and associate with those deities, converse, and engage in discussion; and find out which orders of gods those deities come from? Then my knowledge and vision would become even more purified.’

So after some time … I perceived light and saw forms. And I associated with those deities … And I found out which orders of gods those deities came from. But I didn’t know what deeds caused those deities to be reborn there after passing away from here.

So after some time … I found out what deeds caused those deities to be reborn there after passing away from here. But I didn’t know what deeds caused those deities to have such food and such an experience of pleasure and pain.

So after some time … I found out what deeds caused those deities to have such food and such an experience of pleasure and pain. But I didn’t know that these deities have a lifespan of such a length.

So after some time … I found out that these deities have a lifespan of such a length. But I didn’t know whether or not I had previously lived together with those deities.

Then it occurred to me, ‘What if I were to perceive light and see forms; and associate with those deities, converse, and engage in discussion; and find out which orders of gods those deities come from; and what deeds caused those deities to be reborn there after passing away from here; and what deeds caused those deities to have such food and such an experience of pleasure and pain; and that these deities have a lifespan of such a length; and whether or not I have previously lived together with those deities? Then my knowledge and vision would become even more purified.’

So after some time … I found out whether or not I have previously lived together with those deities.

As long as my knowledge and vision about the deities was not fully purified in these eight rounds, I didn’t announce my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

But when my knowledge and vision about the deities was fully purified in these eight rounds, I announced my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans. Knowledge and vision arose in me: ‘My freedom is unshakable; this is my last rebirth; now there’ll be no more future lives.’”

AN 8.65 Dimensions of Mastery Abhibhāyatanasutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight dimensions of mastery. What eight?

Perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, limited, both pretty and ugly. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the first dimension of mastery.

Perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, limitless, both pretty and ugly. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the second dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, limited, both pretty and ugly. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the third dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, limitless, both pretty and ugly. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the fourth dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, blue, with blue color and blue appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the fifth dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, yellow, with yellow color and yellow appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the sixth dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, red, with red color and red appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the seventh dimension of mastery.

Not perceiving form internally, someone sees forms externally, white, with white color and white appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ This is the eighth dimension of mastery.

These are the eight dimensions of mastery.”

AN 8.66 Liberations Vimokkhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight liberations. What eight? Having physical form, they see forms. This is the first liberation.

Not perceiving form internally, they see forms externally. This is the second liberation.

They’re focused only on beauty. This is the third liberation.

Going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite space. This is the fourth liberation.

Going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite consciousness. This is the fifth liberation.

Going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, they enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness. This is the sixth liberation.

Going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, they enter and remain in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. This is the seventh liberation.

Going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, they enter and remain in the cessation of perception and feeling. This is the eighth liberation.

These are the eight liberations.”

AN 8.67 Ignoble Expressions Anariyavohārasutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight ignoble expressions. What eight? Saying you’ve seen, heard, thought, or known something, but you haven’t. And saying you haven’t seen, heard, thought, or known something, but you have. These are the eight ignoble expressions.”

AN 8.68 Noble Expressions Ariyavohārasutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight noble expressions. What eight? Saying you haven’t seen, heard, thought, or known something, and you haven’t. And saying you’ve seen, heard, thought, or known something, and you have. These are the eight noble expressions.”

AN 8.69 Assemblies Parisāsutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight assemblies. What eight? The assemblies of aristocrats, brahmins, householders, and ascetics. An assembly of the gods of the four great kings. An assembly of the gods of the thirty-three. An assembly of Māras. An assembly of divinities.

I recall having approached an assembly of hundreds of aristocrats. There I used to sit with them, converse, and engage in discussion. And my appearance and voice became just like theirs. I educated, encouraged, fired up, and inspired them with a Dhamma talk. But when I spoke they didn’t know: ‘Who is this that speaks? Is it a god or a human?’ And when my Dhamma talk was finished I vanished. But when I vanished they didn’t know: ‘Who was that who vanished? Was it a god or a human?’

I recall having approached an assembly of hundreds of brahmins … householders … ascetics … the gods of the four great kings … the gods of the thirty-three … Māras … divinities. There too I used to sit with them, converse, and engage in discussion. And my appearance and voice became just like theirs. I educated, encouraged, fired up, and inspired them with a Dhamma talk. But when I spoke they didn’t know: ‘Who is this that speaks? Is it a god or a human?’ And when my Dhamma talk was finished I vanished. But when I vanished they didn’t know: ‘Who was that who vanished? Was it a god or a human?’ These are the eight assemblies.”

AN 8.70 Earthquakes Bhūmicālasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof.

Then the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Vesālī for alms. Then, after the meal, on his return from almsround, he addressed Venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, get your sitting cloth. Let’s go to the Cāpāla Shrine for the day’s meditation.”

“Yes, sir,” replied Ānanda. Taking his sitting cloth he followed behind the Buddha.

Then the Buddha went up to the Cāpāla Shrine, where he sat down on the seat spread out. When he was seated he said to Venerable Ānanda:

“Ānanda, Vesālī is lovely. And the Udena, Gotamaka, Seven Maidens, Many Sons, Sārandada, and Cāpāla Shrines are all lovely. Whoever has developed and cultivated the four bases of psychic power—made them a vehicle and a basis, kept them up, consolidated them, and properly implemented them—may, if they wish, live for the proper lifespan or what’s left of it. The Realized One has developed and cultivated the four bases of psychic power, made them a vehicle and a basis, kept them up, consolidated them, and properly implemented them. If he wished, the Realized One could live for the proper lifespan or what’s left of it.”

But Ānanda didn’t get it, even though the Buddha dropped such an obvious hint, such a clear sign. He didn’t beg the Buddha, “Sir, may the Blessed One please remain for the proper lifespan! May the Holy One please remain for the proper lifespan! That would be for the welfare and happiness of the people, out of sympathy for the world, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.” For his mind was as if possessed by Māra.

For a second time …

And for a third time, the Buddha said to him:

“Ānanda, Vesālī is lovely. And the Udena, Gotamaka, Seven Maidens, Many Sons, Sārandada, and Cāpāla Shrines are all lovely. Whoever has developed and cultivated the four bases of psychic power—made them a vehicle and a basis, kept them up, consolidated them, and properly implemented them—may, if they wish, live for the proper lifespan or what’s left of it. The Realized One has developed and cultivated the four bases of psychic power, made them a vehicle and a basis, kept them up, consolidated them, and properly implemented them. If he wished, the Realized One could live for the proper lifespan or what’s left of it.”

But Ānanda didn’t get it, even though the Buddha dropped such an obvious hint, such a clear sign. He didn’t beg the Buddha, “Sir, may the Blessed One please remain for the proper lifespan! May the Holy One please remain for the proper lifespan! That would be for the welfare and happiness of the people, out of sympathy for the world, for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of gods and humans.” For his mind was as if possessed by Māra.

Then the Buddha said to Venerable Ānanda, “Go now, Ānanda, at your convenience.”

“Yes, sir,” replied Ānanda. He rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before sitting at the root of a tree close by.

And then, not long after Ānanda had left, Māra the Wicked said to the Buddha:

“Sir, may the Blessed One now be fully extinguished! May the Holy One now be fully extinguished! Now is the time for the full extinguishment of the Buddha.

Sir, you once made this statement: ‘Wicked One, I shall not be fully extinguished until I have monk disciples who are competent, educated, assured, learned, have memorized the teachings, and practice in line with the principle of the teaching; not until they practice appropriately, living in line with the teaching; not until they’ve learned their denomination, and explain, teach, assert, establish, clarify, analyze, and reveal; not until they can legitimately and completely refute the doctrines of others that come up, and teach with a demonstrable basis.’ Today you do have such monk disciples.

May the Blessed One now be fully extinguished! May the Holy One now be fully extinguished! Now is the time for the full extinguishment of the Buddha.

Sir, you once made this statement: ‘Wicked One, I shall not be fully extinguished until I have nun disciples who are competent, educated, self-assured, learned …’ …

‘Wicked One, I shall not be fully extinguished until I have layman disciples who are competent, educated, self-assured, learned …’ …

‘Wicked One, I shall not be fully extinguished until I have laywoman disciples who are competent, educated, self-assured, learned …’ … Today you do have such laywoman disciples.

Sir, may the Blessed One now be fully extinguished! May the Holy One be fully extinguished! Now is the time for the full extinguishment of the Buddha. Sir, you once made this statement:

‘Wicked One, I shall not be fully extinguished until my spiritual path is successful and prosperous, extensive, popular, widespread, and fully revealed among gods and humans.’ Today your spiritual path is successful and prosperous, extensive, popular, widespread, and fully revealed among gods and humans.

Sir, may the Blessed One now be fully extinguished! May the Holy One be fully extinguished! Now is the time for the full extinguishment of the Buddha.”

“Relax, Wicked One. The full extinguishment of the Realized One will be soon. Three months from now the Realized One will be fully extinguished.”

So at the Cāpāla Shrine the Buddha, mindful and aware, surrendered the life force. When he did so there was a great earthquake, awe-inspiring and hair-raising, and thunder cracked the sky. Then, understanding this matter, on that occasion the Buddha expressed this heartfelt sentiment:

“Comparing the incomparable with the creation of prolonged life,
the sage surrendered the life force.
Happy inside, serene,
he shattered self-creation like a suit of armor.”

Then Venerable Ānanda thought, “That was a really big earthquake! That was really a very big earthquake; awe-inspiring and hair-raising, and thunder cracked the sky! What’s the cause, what’s the reason for a great earthquake?”

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, that was a really big earthquake! That was really a very big earthquake; awe-inspiring and hair-raising, and thunder cracked the sky! What’s the cause, what’s the reason for a great earthquake?”

“Ānanda, there are these eight causes and reasons for a great earthquake. What eight?

This great earth is established on water, the water is established on air, and the air stands in space. At a time when a great wind blows, it stirs the water, and the water stirs the earth. This is the first cause and reason for a great earthquake.

Furthermore, there is an ascetic or brahmin with psychic power who has achieved mastery of the mind, or a god who is mighty and powerful. They’ve developed a limited perception of earth and a limitless perception of water. They make the earth shake and rock and tremble. This is the second cause and reason for a great earthquake.

Furthermore, when the being intent on awakening passes away from the host of joyful gods, he’s conceived in his mother’s womb, mindful and aware. Then the earth shakes and rocks and trembles. This is the third cause and reason for a great earthquake.

Furthermore, when the being intent on awakening comes out of his mother’s womb mindful and aware, the earth shakes and rocks and trembles. This is the fourth cause and reason for a great earthquake.

Furthermore, when the Realized One awakens to the supreme perfect awakening, the earth shakes and rocks and trembles. This is the fifth cause and reason for a great earthquake.

Furthermore, when the Realized One rolls forth the supreme Wheel of Dhamma, the earth shakes and rocks and trembles. This is the sixth cause and reason for a great earthquake.

Furthermore, when the Realized One, mindful and aware, surrenders the life force, the earth shakes and rocks and trembles. This is the seventh cause and reason for a great earthquake.

Furthermore, when the Realized One becomes fully extinguished in the element of extinguishment with no residue, the earth shakes and rocks and trembles. This is the eighth cause and reason for a great earthquake.

These are the eight causes and reasons for a great earthquake.”

The Chapter on Giving

AN 8.31 Giving (1st) Paṭhamadānasutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight gifts. What eight? Someone might give a gift after insulting the recipient. Or they give out of fear. Or they give thinking, ‘They gave to me.’ Or they give thinking, ‘They’ll give to me.’ Or they give thinking, ‘It’s good to give.’ Or they give thinking, ‘I cook, they don’t. It wouldn’t be right for me to not give to them.’ Or they give thinking, ‘By giving this gift I’ll get a good reputation.’ Or they give thinking, ‘This is an adornment and requisite for the mind.’ These are the eight gifts.”

AN 8.32 Giving (2nd) Dutiyadānasutta

“Faith, conscience, and skillful giving
are qualities true persons follow.
For this, they say, is the path of the gods,
which leads to the heavenly realm.”

AN 8.33 Reasons to Give Dānavatthusutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight grounds for giving. What eight? Someone might give a gift out of favoritism or hostility or stupidity or cowardice. Or they give thinking, ‘Giving was practiced by my father and my father’s father. It would not be right for me to abandon this traditional family custom.’ Or they give thinking, ‘After I’ve given this gift, when my body breaks up, after death, I’ll be reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’ Or they give thinking, ‘When giving this gift my mind becomes clear, and I become happy and joyful.’ Or they give a gift thinking, ‘This is an adornment and requisite for the mind.’ These are the eight grounds for giving.”

AN 8.34 A Field Khettasutta

“Mendicants, when a field has eight factors a seed sown in it is not very fruitful or rewarding or productive. What eight factors does it have? It’s when a field has mounds and ditches. It has stones and gravel. It’s salty. It doesn’t have deep furrows. And it’s not equipped with water inlets, water outlets, irrigation channels, and boundaries. When a field has these eight factors a seed sown in it is not fruitful or rewarding or productive.

In the same way, when an ascetic or brahmin has eight factors a gift given to them is not very fruitful or beneficial or brilliant or bountiful. What eight factors do they have? It’s when an ascetic or brahmin has wrong view, wrong purpose, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong mindfulness, and wrong immersion. When an ascetic or brahmin has these eight factors a gift given to them is not very fruitful or beneficial or brilliant or bountiful.

When a field has eight factors a seed sown in it is very fruitful and rewarding and productive. What eight factors does it have? It’s when a field doesn’t have mounds and ditches. It doesn’t have stones and gravel. It’s not salty. It has deep furrows. And it’s equipped with water inlets, water outlets, irrigation channels, and boundaries. When a field has these eight factors a seed sown in it is very fruitful and rewarding and productive.

In the same way, when an ascetic or brahmin has eight factors a gift given to them is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful. What eight factors do they have? It’s when an ascetic or brahmin has right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. When an ascetic or brahmin has these eight factors a gift given to them is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful.

When the field is excellent,
and the seed sown in it is excellent,
and the rainfall is excellent,
the crop of grain will be excellent.

The absence of crop loss is excellent,
its growth is excellent,
its maturation is excellent,
and its fruit is excellent.

So too, when you give excellent food
to those of excellent ethics,
it leads to many excellences,
for what you did was excellent.

So if a person wants excellence,
let them excel in this.
You should frequent those with excellent wisdom,
so that your own excellence will flourish.

Excelling in knowledge and conduct,
and having excellence of mind,
you perform excellent deeds,
and gain excellent benefits.

Truly knowing the world,
and having attained excellence of view,
one who excels in mind proceeds,
relying on excellence in the path.

Shaking off all stains,
and attaining the excellence of extinguishment,
you’re freed from all sufferings:
this is complete excellence.”

AN 8.35 Rebirth by Giving Dānūpapattisutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight rebirths by giving. What eight?

First, someone gives to ascetics or brahmins such things as food, drink, clothing, vehicles; garlands, fragrance, and makeup; and bed, house, and lighting. Whatever they give they expect back. They see a well-to-do aristocrat or brahmin or householder amusing themselves, supplied and provided with the five kinds of sensual stimulation. It occurs to them: ‘If only, when my body breaks up, after death, I would be reborn in the company of well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders!’ They settle on that thought, stabilize it, and develop it. As they’ve settled for less and not developed further, their thought leads to rebirth there. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of well-to-do aristocrats or brahmins or householders. But I say that this is only for those of ethical conduct, not for the unethical. The heart’s wish of an ethical person succeeds because of their purity.

Next, someone gives to ascetics or brahmins … Whatever they give they expect back. And they’ve heard: ‘The gods of the four great kings are long-lived, beautiful, and very happy.’ It occurs to them: ‘If only, when my body breaks up, after death, I would be reborn in the company of the gods of the four great kings!’ … When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods of the four great kings. But I say that this is only for those of ethical conduct, not for the unethical. The heart’s wish of an ethical person succeeds because of their purity.

Next, someone gives to ascetics or brahmins … Whatever they give they expect back. And they’ve heard: ‘The gods of the thirty-three …’

‘The gods of Yama …’

‘The joyful gods …’

‘The gods who love to create …’

‘The gods who control what is created by others are long-lived, beautiful, and very happy.’ It occurs to them: ‘If only, when my body breaks up, after death, I would be reborn in the company of the gods who control what is created by others!’ They settle on that thought, stabilize it, and develop it. As they’ve settled for less and not developed further, their thought leads to rebirth there. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods who control what is created by others. But I say that this is only for those of ethical conduct, not for the unethical. The heart’s wish of an ethical person succeeds because of their purity.

Next, someone gives to ascetics or brahmins such things as food, drink, clothing, vehicles; garlands, fragrance, and makeup; and bed, house, and lighting. Whatever they give they expect back. And they’ve heard: ‘The gods of the Divinity’s host are long-lived, beautiful, and very happy.’ It occurs to them: ‘If only, when my body breaks up, after death, I would be reborn in the company of the gods of the Divinity’s host!’ They settle on that thought, stabilize it, and develop it. As they’ve settled for less and not developed further, their thought leads to rebirth there. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods of the Divinity’s host. But I say that this is only for those of ethical conduct, not for the unethical. And for those free of desire, not those with desire. The heart’s wish of an ethical person succeeds because of their freedom from desire.

These are the eight rebirths by giving.”

AN 8.36 Grounds for Making Merit Puññakiriyavatthusutta

“Mendicants, there are these three grounds for making merit. What three? Giving, ethical conduct, and meditation are all grounds for making merit.

First, someone has practiced a little giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit, but they haven’t got as far as meditation as a ground for making merit. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn among disadvantaged humans.

Next, someone has practiced a moderate amount of giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit, but they haven’t got as far as meditation as a ground for making merit. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn among well-off humans.

Next, someone has practiced to an extraordinary degree giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit, but they haven’t got as far as meditation as a ground for making merit. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods of the four great kings. There, the four great kings themselves have practiced giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit to a greater degree than the other gods. So they surpass them in ten respects: heavenly lifespan, beauty, happiness, glory, sovereignty, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches.

Next, someone has practiced to an extraordinary degree giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit, but they haven’t got as far as meditation as a ground for making merit. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods of the thirty-three. There, Sakka, lord of gods, has practiced giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit to a greater degree than the other gods. So he surpasses them in ten respects …

Next, someone has practiced to an extraordinary degree giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit, but they haven’t got as far as meditation as a ground for making merit. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods of Yama. There, the godling Suyāma has practiced giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit to a greater degree than the other gods. So he surpasses them in ten respects …

Next, someone has practiced to an extraordinary degree giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit, but they haven’t got as far as meditation as a ground for making merit. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the joyful gods. There, the godling Santusita has practiced giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit to a greater degree than the other gods. So he surpasses them in ten respects …

Next, someone has practiced to an extraordinary degree giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit, but they haven’t got as far as meditation as a ground for making merit. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods who love to create. There, the godling Sunimmita has practiced giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit to a greater degree than the other gods. So he surpasses them in ten respects …

Next, someone has practiced to an extraordinary degree giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit, but they haven’t got as far as meditation as a ground for making merit. When their body breaks up, after death, they’re reborn in the company of the gods who control what is created by others. There, the godling Vasavattī has practiced giving and ethical conduct as grounds for making merit to a greater degree than the other gods. So he surpasses them in ten respects: heavenly lifespan, beauty, happiness, glory, sovereignty, sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches.

These are the three grounds for making merit.”

AN 8.37 Gifts of a True Person Sappurisadānasutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight gifts of a true person. What eight? Their gift is pure, good quality, timely, appropriate, intelligent, and regular. While giving their heart is confident, and afterwards they’re uplifted. These are the eight gifts of a true person.

He gives pure, good quality, and timely gifts
of appropriate food and drinks
regularly to spiritual practitioners
who are fertile fields of merit.

They never regret
giving away many things of the flesh.
Discerning people praise
giving such gifts.

An intelligent person sacrifices like this,
faithful, with a mind of letting go.
Such an astute person is reborn
in a happy, pleasing world.”

AN 8.38 A True Person Sappurisasutta

“Mendicants, a true person is born in a family for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of the people. For the benefit, welfare, and happiness of mother and father; children and partners; bondservants, workers, and staff; friends and colleagues; departed ancestors; the king; the deities; and ascetics and brahmins.

It’s like a great rain cloud, which nourishes all the crops for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of the people. In the same way, a true person is born in a family for the benefit, welfare, and happiness of the people. …

A wise person living at home
benefits many people.
Neither by day or at night do they neglect
their mother, father, and ancestors.
They venerate them in accord with the teaching,
remembering what they have done.

One of settled faith and good nature
venerates the homeless renunciates,
the mendicant spiritual practitioners,
knowing their good-hearted qualities.

Good for the king, good for the gods,
and good for relatives and comrades.

In fact, they’re good for everyone,
well grounded in the true teaching.
Rid of the stain of stinginess,
they’ll enjoy a world of grace.”

AN 8.39 Overflowing Merit Abhisandasutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness. They nurture happiness and are conducive to heaven, ripening in happiness and leading to heaven. They lead to what is likable, desirable, agreeable, to welfare and happiness. What eight?

Firstly, a noble disciple has gone for refuge to the Buddha. This is the first kind of overflowing merit …

Furthermore, a noble disciple has gone for refuge to the teaching. This is the second kind of overflowing merit …

Furthermore, a noble disciple has gone for refuge to the Saṅgha. This is the third kind of overflowing merit …

Mendicants, these five gifts are great, primordial, long-standing, customary, and traditional. They are uncorrupted, as they have been since the beginning. They’re not being corrupted now nor will they be. Sensible ascetics and brahmins don’t look down on them. What five?

Firstly, a noble disciple gives up killing living creatures. By so doing they give to countless sentient beings the gift of freedom from fear, enmity, and ill will. And they themselves also enjoy unlimited freedom from fear, enmity, and ill will. This is the first gift that is a great offering, primordial, long-standing, customary, and traditional. It is uncorrupted, as it has been since the beginning. It’s not being corrupted now nor will it be. Sensible ascetics and brahmins don’t look down on it. This is the fourth kind of overflowing merit …

Furthermore, a noble disciple gives up stealing. … This is the fifth kind of overflowing merit …

Furthermore, a noble disciple gives up sexual misconduct. … This is the sixth kind of overflowing merit …

Furthermore, a noble disciple gives up lying. … This is the seventh kind of overflowing merit …

Furthermore, a noble disciple gives up intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. By so doing they give to countless sentient beings the gift of freedom from fear, enmity, and ill will. And they themselves also enjoy unlimited freedom from fear, enmity, and ill will. This is the fifth gift that is a great offering, primordial, long-standing, customary, and traditional. It is uncorrupted, as it has been since the beginning. It’s not being corrupted now nor will it be. Sensible ascetics and brahmins don’t look down on it. This is the eighth kind of overflowing merit …

These are the eight kinds of overflowing merit, overflowing goodness. They nurture happiness and are conducive to heaven, ripening in happiness and leading to heaven. They lead to what is likable, desirable, agreeable, to welfare and happiness.”

AN 8.40 The Results of Misconduct Duccaritavipākasutta

“Mendicants, the killing of living creatures, when cultivated, developed, and practiced, leads to hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. The minimum result it leads to for a human being is a short lifespan.

Stealing, when cultivated, developed, and practiced, leads to hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. The minimum result it leads to for a human being is loss of wealth.

Sexual misconduct, when cultivated, developed, and practiced, leads to hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. The minimum result it leads to for a human being is rivalry and enmity.

Lying, when cultivated, developed, and practiced, leads to hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. The minimum result it leads to for a human being is false accusations.

Backbiting, when cultivated, developed, and practiced, leads to hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. The minimum result it leads to for a human being is being divided against friends.

Harsh speech, when cultivated, developed, and practiced, leads to hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. The minimum result it leads to for a human being is hearing disagreeable things.

Talking nonsense, when cultivated, developed, and practiced, leads to hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. The minimum result it leads to for a human being is that no one takes what you say seriously.

Drinking beer and wine, when cultivated, developed, and practiced, leads to hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. The minimum result it leads to for a human being is madness.”

The Second Fifty

The Chapter on Gotamī

AN 8.51 With Gotamī Gotamīsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Then Mahāpajāpati Gotamī went up to the Buddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, please let ladies gain the going forth from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

“Enough, Gotamī. Don’t endorse the going forth for ladies from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

For a second time …

For a third time, Mahāpajāpati Gotamī said to the Buddha:

“Sir, please let ladies gain the going forth from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

“Enough, Gotamī. Don’t endorse the going forth for ladies from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

Then Mahāpajāpati Gotamī thought, “The Buddha does not permit ladies to go forth.” Miserable and sad, weeping, with a tearful face, she bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on her right, before leaving.

When the Buddha had stayed in Kapilavatthu as long as he pleased, he set out for Vesālī. Traveling stage by stage, he arrived at Vesālī, where he stayed at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof. Then Mahāpajāpati Gotamī had her hair shaved, and dressed in ocher robes. Together with several Sakyan ladies she set out for Vesālī. Traveling stage by stage, she arrived at Vesālī and went to the Great Wood, the hall with the peaked roof. Then Mahāpajāpati Gotamī stood crying outside the gate, her feet swollen, her limbs covered with dust, miserable and sad, with tearful face.

Venerable Ānanda saw her standing there, and said to her, “Gotamī, why do you stand crying outside the gate, your feet swollen, your limbs covered with dust, miserable and sad, with tearful face?”

“Honorable Ānanda, it’s because the Buddha does not permit ladies to go forth in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

“Well then, Gotamī, wait here an hour while I ask the Buddha to grant the going forth for ladies.”

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, Mahāpajāpati Gotamī is standing crying outside the gate, her feet swollen, her limbs covered with dust, miserable and sad, with tearful face. She says that it’s because the Buddha does not permit ladies to go forth. Sir, please let ladies gain the going forth from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

“Enough, Ānanda. Don’t endorse the going forth for ladies from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

For a second time …

For a third time, Ānanda said to the Buddha:

“Sir, please let ladies gain the going forth from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

“Enough, Ānanda. Don’t endorse the going forth for ladies from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

Then Venerable Ānanda thought, “The Buddha does not permit ladies to go forth. Why don’t I try another approach?”

Then Venerable Ānanda said to the Buddha, “Sir, is a lady able to realize the fruits of stream-entry, once-return, non-return, and perfection once she has gone forth?”

“She is able, Ānanda.”

“If a lady is able to realize the fruits of stream-entry, once-return, non-return, and perfection once she has gone forth. Sir, Mahāpajāpati has been very helpful to the Buddha. As his aunt, she raised him, nurtured him, and gave him her milk. When the Buddha’s birth mother passed away, she nurtured him at her own breast. Sir, please let ladies gain the going forth from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One.”

“Ānanda, if Mahāpajāpati Gotamī accepts these eight principles of respect, that will be her ordination.

A nun, even if she has been ordained for a hundred years, should bow down to a monk who was ordained that very day. She should rise up for him, greet him with cupped palms, and observe proper etiquette toward him. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts.

A nun should not commence the rainy season residence in a monastery without monks. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts.

Each fortnight the nuns should expect two things from the community of monks: the date of the sabbath, and visiting for advice. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts.

After completing the rainy season residence the nuns should invite admonition from the communities of both monks and nuns in regard to anything that was seen, heard, or suspected. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts.

A nun who has committed a grave offense should undergo penance in the communities of both monks and nuns for a fortnight. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts.

A trainee nun who has trained in the six rules for two years should seek ordination from the communities of both monks and nuns. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts.

A nun should not abuse or insult a monk in any way. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts.

From this day forth it is forbidden for nuns to criticize monks, but it is not forbidden for monks to criticize nuns. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts.

If Mahāpajāpati Gotamī accepts these eight principles of respect, that will be her ordination.”

Then Ānanda, having learned these eight principles of respect from the Buddha himself, went to Mahāpajāpati Gotamī and said:

“Gotamī, if you accept eight principles of respect, that will be your ordination.

A nun, even if she has been ordained for a hundred years, should bow down to a monk who was ordained that very day. She should rise up for him, greet him with cupped palms, and observe proper etiquette toward him. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts. …

From this day forth it is forbidden for nuns to criticize monks, but it is not forbidden for monks to criticize nuns. This principle should be honored, respected, esteemed, and venerated, and not transgressed so long as life lasts. If you accept these eight principles of respect, that will be your ordination.”

“Ānanda, suppose there was a woman or man who was young, youthful, and fond of adornments, and had bathed their head. After getting a garland of lotuses, jasmine, or liana flowers, they would take them in both hands and place them on the crown of the head. In the same way, sir, I accept these eight principles of respect as not to be transgressed so long as life lasts.”

Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, Mahāpajāpati Gotamī has accepted the eight principles of respect as not to be transgressed so long as life lasts.”

“Ānanda, if ladies had not gained the going forth from the lay life to homelessness in the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One, the spiritual life would have lasted long. The true teaching would have remained for a thousand years. But since they have gained the going forth, now the spiritual life will not last long. The true teaching will remain only five hundred years.

It’s like those families with many women and few men. They’re easy prey for bandits and grain-jar thieves. In the same way, the spiritual life does not last long in a teaching and training where ladies gain the going forth.

It’s like a field full of rice. Once the disease called ‘white bones’ attacks, it doesn’t last long. In the same way, the spiritual life does not last long in a teaching and training where ladies gain the going forth.

It’s like a field full of sugarcane. Once the disease called ‘red rot’ attacks, it doesn’t last long. In the same way, the spiritual life does not last long in a teaching and training where ladies gain the going forth.

As a man might build a dyke around a large lake as a precaution against the water overflowing, in the same way as a precaution I’ve prescribed the eight principles of respect as not to be transgressed so long as life lasts.”

AN 8.52 An Adviser for Nuns Ovādasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof. Then Venerable Ānanda went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, how many qualities should a monk have to be deemed an adviser for nuns?”

“Ānanda, a monk with eight qualities may be deemed an adviser for nuns. What eight?

Firstly, a monk is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken.

They’re learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s totally full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, reciting them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically.

Both monastic codes have been passed down to them in detail, well analyzed, well mastered, well evaluated in both the rules and accompanying material.

They’re a good speaker who enunciates well. Their voice is polished, clear, articulate, and expresses the meaning.

They’re able to educate, encourage, fire up, and inspire the community of nuns.

They’re liked and agreeable to most of the nuns.

They have never previously sexually harassed any woman wearing the ocher robe who has gone forth in the Buddha’s name.

They have been ordained for twenty years or more.

A monk with these eight qualities may be deemed an adviser for nuns.”

AN 8.53 Brief Advice to Gotamī Saṁkhittasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof. Then Mahāpajāpati Gotamī went up to the Buddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, may the Buddha please teach me Dhamma in brief. When I’ve heard it, I’ll live alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute.”

“Gotamī, you might know that certain things lead to passion, not dispassion; to yoking, not to unyoking; to accumulation, not dispersal; to more desires, not fewer; to lack of contentment, not contentment; to crowding, not seclusion; to laziness, not energy; to being burdensome, not being unburdensome. Categorically, you should remember these things as not the teaching, not the training, and not the Teacher’s instructions.

You might know that certain things lead to dispassion, not passion; to unyoking, not to yoking; to dispersal, not accumulation; to fewer desires, not more; to contentment, not lack of contentment; to seclusion, not crowding; to energy, not laziness; to being unburdensome, not being burdensome. Categorically, you should remember these things as the teaching, the training, and the Teacher’s instructions.”

AN 8.54 With Dīghajāṇu Dīghajāṇusutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Koliyans, where they have a town named Kakkarapatta. Then Dīghajāṇu the Koliyan went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, we are laypeople who enjoy sensual pleasures and living at home with our children. We use sandalwood imported from Kāsi, we wear garlands, fragrance, and makeup, and we accept gold and currency. May the Buddha please teach us the Dhamma in a way that leads to our welfare and happiness in this life and lives to come.”

“Byagghapajja, these four things lead to the welfare and happiness of a gentleman in this life. What four?

Accomplishment in initiative, protection, good friendship, and balanced finances. And what is accomplishment in initiative? It’s when a gentleman earns a living by means such as farming, trade, raising cattle, archery, government service, or one of the professions. He understands how to go about these things in order to complete and organize the work. This is called accomplishment in initiative.

And what is accomplishment in protection? It’s when a gentleman owns legitimate wealth that he has earned by his own efforts and initiative, built up with his own hands, gathered by the sweat of the brow. He ensures it is guarded and protected, thinking: ‘How can I prevent my wealth from being taken by rulers or bandits, consumed by fire, swept away by flood, or taken by unloved heirs?’ This is called accomplishment in protection.

And what is accomplishment in good friendship? It’s when a gentleman resides in a town or village. And in that place there are householders or their children who may be young or old, but are mature in conduct, accomplished in faith, ethics, generosity, and wisdom. He associates with them, converses and engages in discussion. And he emulates the same kind of accomplishment in faith, ethics, generosity, and wisdom. This is called accomplishment in good friendship.

And what is accomplishment in balanced finances? It’s when a gentleman, knowing his income and expenditure, balances his finances, being neither too extravagant nor too frugal. He thinks, ‘In this way my income will exceed my expenditure, not the reverse.’ It’s like an appraiser or their apprentice who, holding up the scales, knows that it’s low by this much or high by this much. In the same way, a gentleman, knowing his income and expenditure, balances his finances, being neither too extravagant nor too frugal. He thinks, ‘In this way my income will exceed my expenditure, not the reverse.’ If a gentleman has little income but an opulent life, there’ll be some who say: ‘This gentleman eats their wealth like a fig-eater!’ If a gentleman has a large income but a spartan life, there’ll be some who say: ‘This gentleman is starving themselves to death!’ But a gentleman, knowing his income and expenditure, leads a balanced life, neither too extravagant nor too frugal, thinking, ‘In this way my income will exceed my expenditure, not the reverse.’ This is called accomplishment in balanced finances.

There are four drains on wealth that has been gathered in this way. Womanizing, drinking, gambling, and having bad friends, companions, and associates. Suppose there was a large reservoir with four inlets and four drains. And someone was to open up the drains and close off the inlets, and the heavens don’t provide enough rain. You’d expect that large reservoir to dwindle, not expand. In the same way, there are four drains on wealth that has been gathered in this way. Womanizing, drinking, gambling, and having bad friends, companions, and associates.

There are four inlets for wealth that has been gathered in this way. Not womanizing, drinking, or gambling, and having good friends, companions, and associates. Suppose there was a large reservoir with four inlets and four drains. And someone was to open up the inlets and close off the drains, and the heavens provide plenty of rain. You’d expect that large reservoir to expand, not dwindle. In the same way, there are four inlets for wealth that has been gathered in this way. Not womanizing, drinking, or gambling, and having good friends, companions, and associates.

These are the four things that lead to the welfare and happiness of a gentleman in this life.

These four things lead to the welfare and happiness of a gentleman in lives to come. What four? Accomplishment in faith, ethics, generosity, and wisdom.

And what is accomplishment in faith? It’s when a gentleman has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ This is called accomplishment in faith.

And what is accomplishment in ethics? It’s when a gentleman doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. This is called accomplishment in ethics.

And what is accomplishment in generosity? It’s when a gentleman lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. This is called accomplishment in generosity.

And what is accomplishment in wisdom? It’s when a gentleman is wise. He has the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is called accomplishment in wisdom.

These are the four things that lead to the welfare and happiness of a gentleman in lives to come.

They’re enterprising in the workplace,
diligent in managing things,
they balance their finances,
and preserve their wealth.

Faithful, accomplished in ethics,
bountiful, rid of stinginess,
they always purify the path
to well-being in lives to come.

And so these eight qualities
of a faithful householder of discernment
are declared by the one who is truly named
to lead to happiness in both spheres,

welfare and benefit in this life,
and happiness in lives to come.
This is how, for a householder,
merit grows by generosity.”

AN 8.55 With Ujjaya Ujjayasutta

Then Ujjaya the brahmin went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, we wish to travel abroad. May the Buddha please teach us the Dhamma in a way that leads to our welfare and happiness in this life and lives to come.”

“Brahmin, these four things lead to the welfare and happiness of a gentleman in this life. What four? Accomplishment in initiative, protection, good friendship, and balanced finances.

And what is accomplishment in initiative? It’s when a gentleman earns a living by means such as farming, trade, raising cattle, archery, government service, or one of the professions. He understands how to go about these things in order to complete and organize the work. This is called accomplishment in initiative.

And what is accomplishment in protection? It’s when a gentleman owns legitimate wealth that he has earned by his own efforts and initiative, built up with his own hands, gathered by the sweat of the brow. He ensures it is guarded and protected, thinking: ‘How can I prevent my wealth from being taken by rulers or bandits, consumed by fire, swept away by flood, or taken by unloved heirs?’ This is called accomplishment in protection.

And what is accomplishment in good friendship? It’s when a gentleman resides in a town or village. And in that place there are householders or their children who may be young or old, but are mature in conduct, accomplished in faith, ethics, generosity, and wisdom. He associates with them, converses and engages in discussion. And he emulates the same kind of accomplishment in faith, ethics, generosity, and wisdom. This is called accomplishment in good friendship.

And what is accomplishment in balanced finances? It’s when a gentleman, knowing his income and expenditure, balances his finances, being neither too extravagant nor too frugal. He thinks, ‘In this way my income will exceed my expenditure, not the reverse.’ It’s like an appraiser or their apprentice who, holding up the scales, knows that it’s low by this much or high by this much. In the same way, a gentleman, knowing his income and expenditure, balances his finances, being neither too extravagant nor too frugal. He thinks, ‘In this way my income will exceed my expenditure, not the reverse.’ If a gentleman has little income but an opulent life, there’ll be some who say: ‘This gentleman eats their wealth like a fig-eater!’ If a gentleman has a large income but a spartan life, there’ll be some who say: ‘This gentleman is starving themselves to death!’ But a gentleman, knowing his income and expenditure, leads a balanced life, neither too extravagant nor too frugal, thinking, ‘In this way my income will exceed my expenditure, not the reverse.’ This is called accomplishment in balanced finances.

There are four drains on wealth that has been gathered in this way. Womanizing, drinking, gambling, and having bad friends, companions, and associates. Suppose there was a large reservoir with four inlets and four drains. And someone was to open up the drains and close off the inlets, and the heavens don’t provide enough rain. You’d expect that large reservoir to dwindle, not expand. In the same way, there are four drains on wealth that has been gathered in this way. Womanizing, drinking, gambling, and having bad friends, companions, and associates.

There are four inlets for wealth that has been gathered in this way. Not womanizing, drinking, or gambling, and having good friends, companions, and associates. Suppose there was a large reservoir with four inlets and four drains. And someone was to open up the inlets and close off the drains, and the heavens provide plenty of rain. You’d expect that large reservoir to expand, not dwindle. In the same way, there are four inlets for wealth that has been gathered in this way. Not womanizing, drinking, or gambling, and having good friends, companions, and associates.

These are the four things that lead to the welfare and happiness of a gentleman in this life.

These four things lead to the welfare and happiness of a gentleman in lives to come. What four? Accomplishment in faith, ethics, generosity, and wisdom.

And what is accomplishment in faith? It’s when a gentleman has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ This is called accomplishment in faith.

And what is accomplishment in ethics? It’s when a gentleman doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. This is called accomplishment in ethics.

And what is accomplishment in generosity? It’s when a gentleman lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. This is called accomplishment in generosity.

And what is accomplishment in wisdom? It’s when a gentleman is wise. He has the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is called accomplishment in wisdom.

These are the four things that lead to the welfare and happiness of a gentleman in lives to come.

They’re enterprising in the workplace,
diligent in managing things,
they balance their finances,
and preserve their wealth.

Faithful, accomplished in ethics,
bountiful, rid of stinginess,
they always purify the path
to well-being in lives to come.

And so these eight qualities
of a faithful householder of discernment
are declared by the one who is truly named
to lead to happiness in both spheres,

welfare and benefit in this life,
and happiness in lives to come.
This is how, for a householder,
merit grows by generosity.”

AN 8.56 Danger Bhayasutta

“Mendicants, ‘danger’ is a term for sensual pleasures. ‘Suffering’, ‘disease’, ‘boil’, ‘dart’, ‘chain’, ‘bog’, and ‘womb’ are terms for sensual pleasures. And why is ‘danger’ a term for sensual pleasures? Someone who is besotted by sensual greed and shackled by lustful desire is not freed from dangers in this life or in lives to come. That is why ‘danger’ is a term for sensual pleasures. And why are ‘suffering’, ‘disease’, ‘boil’, ‘dart’, ‘chain’, ‘bog’, and ‘womb’ terms for sensual pleasures? Someone who is besotted by sensual greed and shackled by lustful desire is not freed from wombs in this life or in lives to come. That is why ‘womb’ is a term for sensual pleasures.

Danger, suffering, and disease,
boil, dart, and chain,
and bogs and wombs both.
These describe the sensual pleasures
to which ordinary people are attached.

Swamped by things that seem pleasant,
you go to another womb.
But when a mendicant is keen,
and doesn’t forget awareness,

in this way that sort transcend
this grueling swamp.
They watch this population flounder,
fallen into rebirth and old age.”

AN 8.57 Worthy of Offerings Dedicated to the Gods (1st) Paṭhamaāhuneyyasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with eight qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What eight?

It’s when a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken.

They’re learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s totally full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, reciting them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically.

They have good friends, companions, and associates.

They have right view, possessing right perspective.

They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty.

They recollect many kinds of past lives, with features and details.

With clairvoyance that is purified and surpasses the human, they see how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds.

They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

A mendicant with these eight qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 8.58 Worthy of Offerings Dedicated to the Gods (2nd) Dutiyaāhuneyyasutta

“A mendicant with eight qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What eight?

It’s when a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken.

They’re learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s totally full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, reciting them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically.

They live with energy roused up. They’re strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities.

They live in the wilderness, in remote lodgings.

They prevail over desire and discontent, and live having mastered desire and discontent whenever they arose.

They prevail over fear and dread, and live having mastered fear and dread whenever they arose.

They get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when they want, without trouble or difficulty.

They realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.

A mendicant with these eight qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 8.59 Eight Individuals (1st) Paṭhamapuggalasutta

“Mendicants, these eight individuals are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world. What eight? The stream-enterer and the one practicing to realize the fruit of stream-entry. The once-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of once-return. The non-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of non-return. The perfected one, and the one practicing for perfection. These are the eight individuals who are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world.

Four practicing the path,
and four established in the fruit.
This is the upright Saṅgha,
with wisdom, ethics, and immersion.

For humans, those merit-seeking creatures,
who sponsor sacrifices,
making worldly merit,
what is given to the Saṅgha is very fruitful.”

AN 8.60 Eight Individuals (2nd) Dutiyapuggalasutta

“Mendicants, these eight individuals are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world. What eight? The stream-enterer and the one practicing to realize the fruit of stream-entry. The once-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of once-return. The non-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of non-return. The perfected one, and the one practicing for perfection. These are the eight individuals who are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world.

Four practicing the path,
and four established in the fruit.
This is the exalted Saṅgha,
the eight individuals among sentient beings.

For humans, those merit-seeking creatures,
who sponsor sacrifices,
making worldly merit,
what’s given here is very fruitful.”

The Chapter on Householders

AN 8.21 With Ugga of Vesālī Paṭhamauggasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, you should remember the householder Ugga of Vesālī as someone who has eight amazing and incredible qualities.”

That is what the Buddha said. When he had spoken, the Holy One rose from his seat and entered his dwelling.

Then a certain mendicant robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of the householder Ugga of Vesālī, where he sat down on the seat spread out. Then Ugga of Vesālī went up to that mendicant, bowed, and sat down to one side. The mendicant said to him:

“Householder, the Buddha declared that you have eight amazing and incredible qualities. What are the eight qualities that he spoke of?”

“Sir, I don’t know what eight amazing and incredible qualities the Buddha was referring to. But these eight amazing and incredible qualities are found in me. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, householder,” replied the mendicant. Ugga of Vesālī said this:

“Sir, when I first saw the Buddha off in the distance, my heart was inspired as soon as I saw him. This is the first incredible and amazing quality found in me.

With confident heart I paid homage to the Buddha. The Buddha taught me step by step, with a talk on giving, ethical conduct, and heaven. He revealed the drawbacks of sensual pleasures, so sordid and corrupt, and the benefit of renunciation. And when he knew that my mind was ready, pliable, rid of hindrances, elated, and confident he revealed the special teaching of the Buddhas: suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. Just as a clean cloth rid of stains would properly absorb dye, in that very seat the stainless, immaculate vision of the Dhamma arose in me: ‘Everything that is liable to arise is liable to cease.’ I saw, attained, understood, and fathomed the Dhamma. I went beyond doubt, got rid of indecision, and became self-assured and independent of others regarding the Teacher’s instructions. Right there I went for refuge to the Buddha, his teaching, and the Saṅgha. And I undertook the five training rules with chastity as the fifth. This is the second incredible and amazing quality found in me.

I had four teenage wives. And I went to them and said: ‘Sisters, I’ve undertaken the five training rules with chastity as fifth. If you wish, you may stay here, enjoy my wealth, and do good deeds. Or you can return to your own families. Or would you prefer if I gave you to another man?’ When I said this, my eldest wife said to me: ‘Master, please give me to a man named so-and-so.’ Then I summoned that man. Taking my wife with my left hand and a ceremonial vase with my right, I presented her to that man with the pouring of water. But I can’t recall getting upset while giving away my teenage wife. This is the third incredible and amazing quality found in me.

And though my family has wealth, it’s shared without reserve with ethical people of good character. This is the fourth incredible and amazing quality found in me.

When I pay homage to a mendicant, I do so carefully, not carelessly. This is the fifth incredible and amazing quality found in me.

If that venerable teaches me the Dhamma, I listen carefully, not carelessly. But if they don’t teach me the Dhamma, I teach them. This is the sixth incredible and amazing quality found in me.

It’s not unusual for deities to come to me and announce: ‘Householder, the Buddha’s teaching is well explained!’ When they say this I say to them: ‘The Buddha’s teaching is well explained, regardless of whether or not you deities say so!’ But I don’t recall getting too excited by the fact that the deities come to me, and I have a conversation with them. This is the seventh incredible and amazing quality found in me.

Of the five lower fetters taught by the Buddha, I don’t see any that I haven’t given up. This is the eighth incredible and amazing quality found in me.

These eight amazing and incredible qualities are found in me. But I don’t know what eight amazing and incredible qualities the Buddha was referring to.”

Then that mendicant, after taking almsfood in Ugga of Vesālī’s home, rose from his seat and left. Then after the meal, on his return from almsround, he went to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. He informed the Buddha of all he had discussed with the householder Ugga of Vesālī. The Buddha said:

“Good, good, mendicant! When I declared that the householder Ugga of Vesālī was someone who has eight amazing and incredible qualities, I was referring to the same eight qualities that he rightly explained to you. You should remember the householder Ugga of Vesālī as someone who possesses these eight amazing and incredible qualities.”

AN 8.22 With Uggata of Elephant Village Dutiyauggasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Vajjis at Elephant Village. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, you should remember the householder Uggata of Elephant Village as someone who has eight amazing and incredible qualities.”

That is what the Buddha said. When he had spoken, the Holy One rose from his seat and entered his dwelling.

Then a certain mendicant robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of the householder Uggata of Elephant Village, where he sat down on the seat spread out. Then Uggata of Elephant Village went up to that mendicant, bowed, and sat down to one side. The mendicant said to him:

“Householder, the Buddha declared that you have eight amazing and incredible qualities. What are the eight qualities that he spoke of?”

“Sir, I don’t know what eight amazing and incredible qualities the Buddha was referring to. But these eight amazing and incredible qualities are found in me. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, householder,” replied the mendicant. Uggata of Elephant Village said this:

“Sir, when I first saw the Buddha off in the distance I was partying in the Dragon’s Park. My heart was inspired as soon as I saw him, and I sobered up. This is the first incredible and amazing quality found in me.

With confident heart I paid homage to the Buddha. The Buddha taught me step by step, with a talk on giving, ethical conduct, and heaven. He revealed the drawbacks of sensual pleasures, so sordid and corrupt, and the benefit of renunciation. And when he knew that my mind was ready, pliable, rid of hindrances, elated, and confident he revealed the special teaching of the Buddhas: suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. Just as a clean cloth rid of stains would properly absorb dye, in that very seat the stainless, immaculate vision of the Dhamma arose in me: ‘Everything that is liable to arise is liable to cease.’ I saw, attained, understood, and fathomed the Dhamma. I went beyond doubt, got rid of indecision, and became self-assured and independent of others regarding the Teacher’s instructions. Right there I went for refuge to the Buddha, his teaching, and the Saṅgha. And I undertook the five training rules with chastity as the fifth. This is the second incredible and amazing quality found in me.

I had four teenage wives. And I went to them and said: ‘Sisters, I’ve undertaken the five training rules with chastity as fifth. If you wish, you may stay here, enjoy my wealth, and do good deeds. Or you can return to your own families. Or would you prefer if I gave you to another man?’ When I said this, my eldest wife said to me: ‘Master, please give me to the man named so-and-so.’ Then I summoned that man. Taking my wife with my left hand and a ceremonial vase with my right, I presented her to that man with the pouring of water. But I can’t recall getting upset while giving away my teenage wife. This is the third incredible and amazing quality found in me.

And though my family has wealth, it’s shared without reserve with ethical people of good character. This is the fourth incredible and amazing quality found in me.

When I pay homage to a mendicant, I do so carefully, not carelessly. If that venerable teaches me the Dhamma, I listen carefully, not carelessly. But if they don’t teach me the Dhamma, I teach them. This is the fifth incredible and amazing quality found in me.

It’s not unusual for deities to come to me when the Saṅgha has been invited and announce: ‘Householder, that mendicant is freed both ways. That one is freed by wisdom. That one is a direct witness. That one is attained to view. That one is freed by faith. That one is a follower of teachings. That one is a follower by faith. That one is ethical, of good character. That one is unethical, of bad character.’ But while I’m serving the Saṅgha I don’t recall thinking: ‘Let me give this one just a little, and that one a lot.’ Rather, I give impartially. This is the sixth incredible and amazing quality found in me.

It’s not unusual for deities to come to me and announce: ‘Householder, the Buddha’s teaching is well explained!’ When they say this I say to them: ‘The Buddha’s teaching is well explained, regardless of whether or not you deities say so!’ But I don’t recall getting too excited by the fact that the deities come to me, and I have a conversation with them. This is the seventh incredible and amazing quality found in me.

If I pass away before the Buddha, it would be no wonder if the Buddha declares of me: ‘The householder Uggata of Elephant Village is bound by no fetter that might return him to this world.’ This is the eighth incredible and amazing quality found in me.

These eight amazing and incredible qualities are found in me. But I don’t know what eight amazing and incredible qualities the Buddha was referring to.”

Then that mendicant, after taking almsfood in Uggata of Elephant Village’s home, rose from his seat and left. Then after the meal, on his return from almsround, he went to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. He informed the Buddha of all he had discussed with the householder Uggata of Elephant Village. The Buddha said:

“Good, good, mendicant! When I declared that the householder Uggata of Elephant Village was someone who has eight amazing and incredible qualities, I was referring to the same eight qualities that he rightly explained to you. You should remember the householder Uggata of Elephant Village as someone who has these eight amazing and incredible qualities.”

AN 8.23 With Hatthaka (1st) Paṭhamahatthakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Āḷavī, at Āḷavī’s premier shrine. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, you should remember the householder Hatthaka of Āḷavī as someone who has seven amazing and incredible qualities. What seven? He’s faithful, ethical, conscientious, prudent, learned, generous, and wise. You should remember the householder Hatthaka of Āḷavī as someone who possesses these seven amazing and incredible qualities.”

That is what the Buddha said. When he had spoken, the Holy One rose from his seat and entered his dwelling.

Then a certain mendicant robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of the householder Hatthaka of Āḷavī, where he sat down on the seat spread out. Then Hatthaka went up to that mendicant, bowed, and sat down to one side. The mendicant said to Hatthaka:

“Respectable sir, the Buddha declared that you have seven amazing and incredible qualities. What seven? He said that you’re faithful, ethical, conscientious, prudent, learned, generous, and wise. The Buddha declared that you possess these seven amazing and incredible qualities.”

“But sir, I trust that no white-clothed lay people were present?”

“No, there weren’t any white-clothed lay people present.”

“That’s good, sir.”

Then that mendicant, after taking almsfood in Hatthaka of Āḷavī’s home, rose from his seat and left. Then after the meal, on his return from almsround, he went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him of what he had discussed with the householder Hatthaka. The Buddha said:

“Good, good, mendicant! That gentleman has few wishes. He doesn’t want his own good qualities to be made known to others. Well then, mendicant, you should remember the householder Hatthaka of Āḷavī as someone who has this eighth amazing and incredible quality, that is, fewness of wishes.”

AN 8.24 With Hatthaka (2nd) Dutiyahatthakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Āḷavī, at Āḷavī’s premier shrine. Then the householder Hatthaka of Āḷavī, escorted by around five hundred lay followers, went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to Hatthaka:

“Hatthaka, you have a large congregation. How do you bring together such a large congregation?”

“Sir, I bring together such a large congregation by using the four ways of being inclusive as taught by the Buddha. When I know that they can be included by a gift, I include them by giving a gift. When I know that they can be included by kindly words, I include them by kindly words. When I know that they can be included by taking care of them, I include them by caring for them. When I know that they can be included by equality, I include them by treating them equally. But also, worthy sir, my family is wealthy. They wouldn’t think that a poor person was worth listening to in the same way.”

“Good, good, Hatthaka! This is the right way to bring together a large congregation. Whether in the past, future, or present, all those who have brought together a large congregation have done so by using these four ways of being inclusive.”

Then the Buddha educated, encouraged, fired up, and inspired Hatthaka of Āḷavī with a Dhamma talk, after which he got up from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving. Then, not long after Hatthaka had left, the Buddha addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, you should remember the householder Hatthaka of Āḷavī as someone who has eight amazing and incredible qualities. What eight? He’s faithful, ethical, conscientious, prudent, learned, generous, wise, and has few wishes. You should remember the householder Hatthaka of Āḷavī as someone who possesses these eight amazing and incredible qualities.”

AN 8.25 With Mahānāma Mahānāmasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Sakyans, near Kapilavatthu in the Banyan Tree Monastery. Then Mahānāma the Sakyan went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, how is a lay follower defined?”

“Mahānāma, when you’ve gone for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, you’re considered to be a lay follower.”

“But how is an ethical lay follower defined?”

“When a lay follower doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor, they’re considered to be an ethical lay follower.”

“But how do we define a lay follower who is practicing to benefit themselves, not others?”

“A lay follower is accomplished in faith, but doesn’t encourage others to do the same. They’re accomplished in ethical conduct, but don’t encourage others to do the same. They’re accomplished in generosity, but don’t encourage others to do the same. They like to see the mendicants, but don’t encourage others to do the same. They like to hear the true teaching, but don’t encourage others to do the same. They readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard, but don’t encourage others to do the same. They examine the meaning of the teachings they’ve memorized, but don’t encourage others to do the same. Understanding the meaning and the teaching, they practice in line with the teaching, but they don’t encourage others to do the same. That’s how we define a lay follower who is practicing to benefit themselves, not others.”

“But how do we define a lay follower who is practicing to benefit both themselves and others?”

“A lay follower is accomplished in faith and encourages others to do the same. They’re accomplished in ethical conduct and encourage others to do the same. They’re accomplished in generosity and encourage others to do the same. They like to see the mendicants and encourage others to do the same. They like to hear the true teaching and encourage others to do the same. They readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard and encourage others to do the same. They examine the meaning of the teachings they’ve memorized and encourage others to do the same. Understanding the meaning and the teaching, they practice in line with the teaching and they encourage others to do the same. That’s how we define a lay follower who is practicing to benefit both themselves and others.”

AN 8.26 With Jīvaka Jīvakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in Jīvaka’s Mango Grove. Then Jīvaka Komārabhacca went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, how is a lay follower defined?”

“Jīvaka, when you’ve gone for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha, you’re considered to be a lay follower.”

“But how is an ethical lay follower defined?”

“When a lay follower doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor, they’re considered to be an ethical lay follower.”

“But how do we define a lay follower who is practicing to benefit themselves, not others?”

“A lay follower is accomplished in faith, but doesn’t encourage others to do the same. They’re accomplished in ethical conduct … they’re accomplished in generosity … they like to see the mendicants … they like to hear the true teaching … they memorize the teachings … they examine the meaning … Understanding the meaning and the teaching, they practice in line with the teaching, but they don’t encourage others to do the same. That’s how we define a lay follower who is practicing to benefit themselves, not others.”

“But how do we define a lay follower who is practicing to benefit both themselves and others?”

“A lay follower is accomplished in faith and encourages others to do the same. They’re accomplished in ethical conduct and encourage others to do the same. They’re accomplished in generosity and encourage others to do the same. They like to see the mendicants and encourage others to do the same. They like to hear the true teaching and encourage others to do the same. They readily memorize the teachings they’ve heard and encourage others to do the same. They examine the meaning of the teachings they’ve memorized and encourage others to do the same. Understanding the meaning and the teaching, they practice in line with the teaching and they encourage others to do the same. That’s how we define a lay follower who is practicing to benefit both themselves and others.”

AN 8.27 Powers (1st) Paṭhamabalasutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight powers. What eight? Crying is the power of babies. Anger is the power of ladies. Weapons are the power of bandits. Authority is the power of rulers. Complaining is the power of fools. Reason is the power of the astute. Reflection is the power of the learned. Patience is the power of ascetics and brahmins. These are the eight powers.”

AN 8.28 Powers (2nd) Dutiyabalasutta

Then Venerable Sāriputta went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Sāriputta, how many powers does a mendicant who has ended the defilements have that qualify them to claim: ‘My defilements have ended’?”

“Sir, a mendicant who has ended the defilements has eight powers that qualify them to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

What eight? Firstly, a mendicant with defilements ended has clearly seen with right wisdom all conditions as truly impermanent. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

Furthermore, a mendicant with defilements ended has clearly seen with right wisdom that sensual pleasures are truly like a pit of glowing coals. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

Furthermore, the mind of a mendicant with defilements ended slants, slopes, and inclines to seclusion. They’re withdrawn, loving renunciation, and have totally eliminated defiling influences. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

Furthermore, a mendicant with defilements ended has well developed the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

Furthermore, a mendicant with defilements ended has well developed the four bases of psychic power … the five faculties … the seven awakening factors … the noble eightfold path. This is a power that a mendicant who has ended the defilements relies on to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’

A mendicant who has ended the defilements possesses these eight powers that qualify them to claim: ‘My defilements have ended.’”

AN 8.29 Lost Opportunities Akkhaṇasutta

“‘Now is the time! Now is the time!’ So says an unlearned ordinary person. But they don’t know whether it’s time or not. Mendicants, there are eight lost opportunities for spiritual practice. What eight?

Firstly, a Realized One has arisen in the world—perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed. He teaches the Dhamma leading to peace, extinguishment, awakening, as proclaimed by the Holy One. But an individual has been reborn in hell. This is the first lost opportunity for spiritual practice.

Furthermore, a Realized One has arisen in the world … He teaches the Dhamma leading to peace, extinguishment, awakening, as proclaimed by the Holy One. But an individual has been reborn in the animal realm. This is the second lost opportunity …

Furthermore, a Realized One has arisen in the world … But an individual has been reborn in the ghost realm. This is the third lost opportunity …

Furthermore, a Realized One has arisen in the world … But an individual has been reborn in one of the long-lived orders of gods. This is the fourth lost opportunity …

Furthermore, a Realized One has arisen in the world … But an individual has been reborn in the borderlands, among uneducated foreigners, where monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen do not go. This is the fifth lost opportunity …

Furthermore, a Realized One has arisen in the world … And an individual is reborn in a central country. But they have wrong view and distorted perspective: ‘There’s no meaning in giving, sacrifice, or offerings. There’s no fruit or result of good and bad deeds. There’s no afterlife. There’s no such thing as mother and father, or beings that are reborn spontaneously. And there’s no ascetic or brahmin who is rightly comported and rightly practiced, and who describes the afterlife after realizing it with their own insight.’ This is the sixth lost opportunity …

Furthermore, a Realized One has arisen in the world … And an individual is reborn in a central country. But they’re witless, dull, idiotic, and unable to distinguish what is well said from what is poorly said. This is the seventh lost opportunity for spiritual practice.

Furthermore, a Realized One has not arisen in the world … So he doesn’t teach the Dhamma leading to peace, extinguishment, awakening, as proclaimed by the Holy One. And an individual is reborn in a central country. And they’re wise, bright, clever, and able to distinguish what is well said from what is poorly said. This is the eighth lost opportunity for spiritual practice.

There are these eight lost opportunities for spiritual practice.

Mendicants, there is just one opportunity for spiritual practice. What is that one? It’s when a Realized One has arisen in the world, perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed. He teaches the Dhamma leading to peace, extinguishment, awakening, as proclaimed by the Holy One. And an individual is reborn in a central country. And they’re wise, bright, clever, and able to distinguish what is well said from what is poorly said. This is the one opportunity for spiritual practice.

When you’ve gained the human state,
and the true teaching has been so well proclaimed,
those who don’t seize the moment
are wasting their time.

For many wrong times are spoken of,
which obstruct the path.
Only on rare occasions
do Realized Ones arise.

If you find yourself in their presence,
so hard to find in the world,
and if you’ve gained a human birth,
and the teaching of the Dhamma;
that’s enough to make an effort,
for a personage who desires self-knowledge.

How is the true teaching to be understood
so that the moment doesn’t pass you by?
For if you miss your moment
you’ll grieve when sent to hell.

If you fail to achieve
certainty regarding the true teaching
you’ll regret it for a long time,
like the merchant in the story of the past.

A man shrouded by ignorance,
a failure in the true teaching,
will long undergo
transmigration through birth and death.

Those who’ve gained the human state
when the true teaching has been so well proclaimed,
and have completed what the Teacher taught—
or will do so, or are doing so now—

have realized the right time in the world
for the supreme spiritual life.
You should live guarded, ever mindful,
not festering with defilements,

among those restrained ones
who have practiced the path
proclaimed by the Realized One, the Clear-eyed One,
and taught by the Kinsman of the Sun.

Having cut off all underlying tendencies
that follow those drifting in Māra’s dominion,
they’re the ones in this world who’ve truly crossed over,
having reached the ending of defilements.”

AN 8.30 Anuruddha and the Great Thoughts Anuruddhamahāvitakkasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Bhaggas at Crocodile’s Bellow, in the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood. And at that time Venerable Anuruddha was staying in the land of the Cetīs in the Park of the East-Raftered Hall. Then as Anuruddha was in private retreat this thought came to his mind:

“This teaching is for those of few wishes, not those of many wishes. It’s for the contented, not those who lack contentment. It’s for the secluded, not those who enjoy company. It’s for the energetic, not the lazy. It’s for the mindful, not the unmindful. It’s for those with immersion, not those without immersion. It’s for the wise, not the witless.”

Then the Buddha knew Anuruddha’s train of thought. As easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, he vanished from the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood in the land of the Bhaggas and reappeared in front of Anuruddha in the Park of the East-Raftered Hall in the land of the Cetīs, and sat down on the seat spread out. Anuruddha bowed to the Buddha and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Good, good, Anuruddha! It’s good that you reflect on these thoughts of a great man: ‘This teaching is for those of few wishes, not those of many wishes. It’s for the contented, not those who lack contentment. It’s for the secluded, not those who enjoy company. It’s for the energetic, not the lazy. It’s for the mindful, not the unmindful. It’s for those with immersion, not those without immersion. It’s for the wise, not the witless.’ Well then, Anuruddha, you should also reflect on the following eighth thought of a great man: ‘This teaching is for those who don’t enjoy proliferating and don’t like to proliferate, not for those who enjoy proliferating and like to proliferate.’

First you’ll reflect on these eight thoughts of a great man. Then as far as you want, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, you’ll enter and remain in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected.

You’ll enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected.

You’ll enter and remain in the third absorption, where you’ll meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.’

With the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, you’ll enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness.

First you’ll reflect on these eight thoughts of a great man, and you’ll get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when you want, without trouble or difficulty. Then as you live contented, your rag robe will seem to you like a chest full of garments of different colors seems to a householder or householder’s child. It will be for your enjoyment, relief, and comfort, and for alighting upon extinguishment.

As you live contented, your scraps of almsfood will seem to you like boiled fine rice with the dark grains picked out, served with many soups and sauces seems to a householder or householder’s child. It will be for your enjoyment, relief, and comfort, and for alighting upon extinguishment.

As you live contented, your lodging at the root of a tree will seem to you like a bungalow, plastered inside and out, draft-free, with door fastened and window shuttered seems to a householder or householder’s child. It will be for your enjoyment, relief, and comfort, and for alighting upon extinguishment.

As you live contented, your grass mat for lodging will seem to you like a couch spread with woolen covers—shag-piled, pure white, or embroidered with flowers—and spread with a fine deer hide, with a canopy above and red pillows at both ends seems to a householder or householder’s child. It will be for your enjoyment, relief, and comfort, and for alighting upon extinguishment.

As you live contented your rancid urine as medicine will seem to you like various medicines—ghee, butter, oil, honey, and molasses—seem to a householder or householder’s child. It will be for your enjoyment, relief, and comfort, and for alighting upon extinguishment. Well then, Anuruddha, for the next rainy season residence you should stay right here in the land of the Cetīs in the Park of the East-Raftered Hall.”

“Yes, sir,” Anuruddha replied.

After advising Anuruddha like this, the Buddha—as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, vanished from the Park of the East-Raftered Hall in the land of the Cetīs and reappeared in the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood in the land of the Bhaggas at Crocodile’s Bellow. He sat down on the seat spread out and addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, I will teach you the eight thoughts of a great man. Listen …

And what are the eight thoughts of a great man? This teaching is for those of few wishes, not those of many wishes. It’s for the contented, not those who lack contentment. It’s for the secluded, not those who enjoy company. It’s for the energetic, not the lazy. It’s for the mindful, not the unmindful. It’s for those with immersion, not those without immersion. It’s for the wise, not the witless. It’s for those who don’t enjoy proliferating and don’t like to proliferate, not for those who enjoy proliferating and like to proliferate.

‘This teaching is for those of few wishes, not those of many wishes.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? A mendicant with few wishes doesn’t wish: ‘May they know me as having few wishes!’ When contented, they don’t wish: ‘May they know me as contented!’ When secluded, they don’t wish: ‘May they know me as secluded!’ When energetic, they don’t wish: ‘May they know me as energetic!’ When mindful, they don’t wish: ‘May they know me as mindful!’ When immersed, they don’t wish: ‘May they know me as immersed!’ When wise, they don’t wish: ‘May they know me as wise!’ When not enjoying proliferation, they don’t wish: ‘May they know me as one who doesn’t enjoy proliferating!’ ‘This teaching is for those of few wishes, not those of many wishes.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘This teaching is for the contented, not those who lack contentment.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? It’s for a mendicant who’s content with any kind of robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. ‘This teaching is for the contented, not those who lack contentment.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘This teaching is for the secluded, not those who enjoy company.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? It’s for a mendicant who lives secluded. But monks, nuns, laymen, laywomen, rulers and their chief ministers, monastics of other religions and their disciples go to visit them. With a mind slanting, sloping, and inclining to seclusion, withdrawn, and loving renunciation, that mendicant invariably gives a talk concerned only with sending them away. ‘This teaching is for the secluded, not those who enjoy company.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘This teaching is for the energetic, not the lazy.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? It’s for a mendicant who lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They’re strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. ‘This teaching is for the energetic, not the lazy.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘This teaching is for the mindful, not the unmindful.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? It’s for a mendicant who’s mindful. They have utmost mindfulness and alertness, and can remember and recall what was said and done long ago. ‘This teaching is for the mindful, not the unmindful.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘This teaching is for those with immersion, not those without immersion.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? It’s for a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption … second absorption … third absorption … fourth absorption. ‘This teaching is for those with immersion, not those without immersion.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘This teaching is for the wise, not the witless.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? It’s for a mendicant who’s wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. ‘This teaching is for the wise, not the witless.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘This teaching is for those who don’t enjoy proliferating and don’t like to proliferate, not for those who enjoy proliferating and like to proliferate.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? It’s for a mendicant whose mind leaps forth, gains confidence, settles down, and becomes decided regarding the cessation of proliferation. ‘This teaching is for those who don’t enjoy proliferating and don’t like to proliferate, not for those who enjoy proliferating and like to proliferate.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

Then Anuruddha stayed the next rainy season residence right there in the land of the Cetīs in the Park of the East-Raftered Hall. And Anuruddha, living alone, withdrawn, diligent, keen, and resolute, soon realized the supreme culmination of the spiritual path in this very life. He lived having achieved with his own insight the goal for which gentlemen rightly go forth from the lay life to homelessness.

He understood: “Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.” And Venerable Anuruddha became one of the perfected. And on the occasion of attaining perfection he recited these verses:

“Knowing my thoughts,
the supreme Teacher in the world
came to me in a mind-made body,
using his psychic power.

He taught me more
than I had thought of.
The Buddha who loves non-proliferation
taught me non-proliferation.

Understanding that teaching,
I happily did his bidding.
I’ve attained the three knowledges,
and have fulfilled the Buddha’s instructions.”

The Great Chapter

AN 8.11 At Verañjā Verañjasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying in Verañjā at the root of a neem tree dedicated to Naḷeru. Then the brahmin Verañja went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, I have heard that the ascetic Gotama doesn’t bow to old brahmins, the elderly and senior, who are advanced in years and have reached the final stage of life; nor does he rise in their presence or offer them a seat. And this is indeed the case, for the worthy Gotama does not bow to old brahmins, elderly and senior, who are advanced in years and have reached the final stage of life; nor does he rise in their presence or offer them a seat. This is not appropriate, worthy Gotama.”

“Brahmin, I don’t see anyone in this world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans—for whom I should bow down or rise up or offer a seat. If the Realized One bowed down or rose up or offered a seat to anyone, their head would explode!”

“Worthy Gotama lacks taste.”

“There is, brahmin, a sense in which you could rightly say that I lack taste. For the Realized One has given up taste for sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches. It’s cut off at the root, made like a palm stump, obliterated, and unable to arise in the future. In this sense you could rightly say that I lack taste. But that’s not what you’re talking about.”

“Worthy Gotama is indelicate.”

“There is, brahmin, a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m indelicate. For the Realized One has given up delight in sights, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches. It’s cut off at the root, made like a palm stump, obliterated, and unable to arise in the future. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m indelicate. But that’s not what you’re talking about.”

“Worthy Gotama is a teacher of inaction.”

“There is, brahmin, a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m a teacher of inaction. For I teach inaction regarding bad bodily, verbal, and mental conduct, and the many kinds of unskillful things. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m a teacher of inaction. But that’s not what you’re talking about.”

“Worthy Gotama is a teacher of annihilationism.”

“There is, brahmin, a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m a teacher of annihilationism. For I teach the annihilation of greed, hate, and delusion, and the many kinds of unskillful things. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m a teacher of annihilationism. But that’s not what you’re talking about.”

“Worthy Gotama is disgusted.”

“There is, brahmin, a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m disgusted. For I’m disgusted by bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind, and by attainment of the many kinds of unskillful things. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m disgusted. But that’s not what you’re talking about.”

“Worthy Gotama is an exterminator.”

“There is, brahmin, a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m an exterminator. For I teach the extermination of greed, hate, and delusion, and the many kinds of unskillful things. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m an exterminator. But that’s not what you’re talking about.”

“Worthy Gotama is a mortifier.”

“There is, brahmin, a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m a mortifier. For I say that bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind should be mortified. I say that a mortifier is someone who has given up unskillful qualities that should be mortified. They’ve cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so that they’re unable to arise in the future. The Realized One is someone who has given up unskillful qualities that should be mortified. He has cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so that they’re unable to arise in the future. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m a mortifier. But that’s not what you’re talking about.”

“Worthy Gotama is gutless.”

“There is, brahmin, a sense in which you could rightly say that I am gutless. I say that a gutless person is someone who has given up future wombs and regeneration into a new state of existence. They’ve cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so that they’re unable to arise in the future. The Realized One has given up future wombs and regeneration into a new state of existence. He has cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so that they’re unable to arise in the future. In this sense you could rightly say that I am gutless. But that’s not what you’re talking about.

Suppose, brahmin, there was a chicken with eight or ten or twelve eggs. And she properly sat on them to keep them warm and incubated. Now, the chick that is first to break out of the eggshell with its claws and beak and hatch safely: should that be called the eldest or the youngest?”

“Worthy Gotama, that should be called the eldest. For it is the eldest among them.”

“In the same way, in this population lost in ignorance, swaddled in their shells, I alone have broken open the egg of ignorance and realized the supreme perfect awakening. So, brahmin, I am the eldest and the first in the world.

My energy was roused up and unflagging, my mindfulness was established and lucid, my body was tranquil and undisturbed, and my mind was immersed and unified in samādhi. Quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, I entered and remained in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected were stilled, I entered and remained in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected. And with the fading away of rapture, I entered and remained in the third absorption, where I meditated with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, ‘Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.’ With the giving up of pleasure and pain, and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, I entered and remained in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness.

When my mind had immersed in samādhi like this—purified, bright, flawless, rid of corruptions, pliable, workable, steady, and imperturbable—I extended it toward recollection of past lives. I recollected many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. I remembered: ‘There, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn somewhere else. There, too, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn here.’ And so I recollected my many kinds of past lives, with features and details.

This was the first knowledge, which I achieved in the first watch of the night. Ignorance was banished and knowledge arose; darkness was banished and light arose, as happens for a meditator who is diligent, keen, and resolute. This was my first breaking out, like a chick breaking out of the eggshell.

When my mind had immersed in samādhi like this—purified, bright, flawless, rid of corruptions, pliable, workable, steady, and imperturbable—I extended it toward knowledge of the death and rebirth of sentient beings. With clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, I saw sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. I understood how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds: ‘These dear beings did bad things by way of body, speech, and mind. They denounced the noble ones; they had wrong view; and they chose to act out of that wrong view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a place of loss, a bad place, the underworld, hell. These dear beings, however, did good things by way of body, speech, and mind. They never denounced the noble ones; they had right view; and they chose to act out of that right view. When their body broke up, after death, they were reborn in a good place, a heavenly realm.’ And so, with clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, I saw sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place. I understood how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds.

This was the second knowledge, which I achieved in the middle watch of the night. Ignorance was banished and knowledge arose; darkness was banished and light arose, as happens for a meditator who is diligent, keen, and resolute. This was my second breaking out, like a chick breaking out of the eggshell.

When my mind had immersed in samādhi like this—purified, bright, flawless, rid of corruptions, pliable, workable, steady, and imperturbable—I extended it toward knowledge of the ending of defilements. I truly understood: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. I truly understood: ‘These are defilements’ … ‘This is the origin of defilements’ … ‘This is the cessation of defilements’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of defilements’. Knowing and seeing like this, my mind was freed from the defilements of sensuality, desire to be reborn, and ignorance. When it was freed, I knew it was freed.

I understood: ‘Rebirth is ended; the spiritual journey has been completed; what had to be done has been done; there is nothing further for this place.’

This was the third knowledge, which I achieved in the last watch of the night. Ignorance was banished and knowledge arose; darkness was banished and light arose, as happens for a meditator who is diligent, keen, and resolute. This was my third breaking out, like a chick breaking out of the eggshell.”

When he said this, the brahmin Verañja said to the Buddha:

“The worthy Gotama is the eldest! The worthy Gotama is the best! Excellent, worthy Gotama! Excellent! As if he were righting the overturned, or revealing the hidden, or pointing out the path to the lost, or lighting a lamp in the dark so people with clear eyes can see what’s there, worthy Gotama has made the teaching clear in many ways. I go for refuge to the worthy Gotama, to the teaching, and to the mendicant Saṅgha. From this day forth, may the worthy Gotama remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

AN 8.12 With Sīha Sīhasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof. Now at that time several very prominent Licchavis were sitting together at the town hall, praising the Buddha, his teaching, and the Saṅgha in many ways.

Now at that time General Sīha, a disciple of the Jains, was sitting in that assembly. He thought, “That Blessed One must without a doubt be a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha. For several very prominent Licchavis are praising the Buddha, his teaching, and the Saṅgha in many ways. Why don’t I go to see that Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha!”

Then General Sīha went to the Jain ascetic of the Ñātika clan and said to him, “Sir, I’d like to go to see the ascetic Gotama.”

“But Sīha, you believe in the doctrine of action. Why should you go to see the ascetic Gotama, who teaches a doctrine of inaction? For the ascetic Gotama believes in a doctrine of inaction, he teaches inaction, and he guides his disciples in that way.”

Then Sīha’s determination to go and see the Buddha died down.

For a second time, several prominent Licchavis were sitting together at the town hall, praising the Buddha, his teaching, and the Saṅgha in many ways. And for a second time Sīha thought: “Why don’t I go to see that Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha!”

Then General Sīha went to the Jain Ñātika …

Then for a second time Sīha’s determination to go and see the Buddha died down.

For a third time, several prominent Licchavis were sitting together at the town hall, praising the Buddha, his teaching, and the Saṅgha in many ways. And for a third time Sīha thought, “That Blessed One must without a doubt be a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha. For several very prominent Licchavis are praising the Buddha, his teaching, and the Saṅgha in many ways. What can these Jains do to me, whether I take leave of them or not? Why don’t I, without taking leave of them, go to see that Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha!”

Then Sīha, with around five hundred chariots, set out from Vesālī in the middle of the day to see the Buddha. He went by carriage as far as the terrain allowed, then descended and went by foot. Then General Sīha went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, I have heard this: ‘The ascetic Gotama believes in a doctrine of inaction, he teaches inaction, and he guides his disciples in that way.’ I trust those who say this repeat what the Buddha has said, and do not misrepresent him with an untruth? Is their explanation in line with the teaching? Are there any legitimate grounds for rebuttal and criticism? For we don’t want to misrepresent the Blessed One.”

“There is, Sīha, a sense in which you could rightly say that I believe in inaction, I teach inaction, and I guide my disciples in that way.

And there is a sense in which you could rightly say that I believe in action, I teach action, and I guide my disciples in that way.

And there is a sense in which you could rightly say that I believe in annihilationism, I teach annihilation, and I guide my disciples in that way.

And there is a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m disgusted, I teach disgust, and I guide my disciples in that way.

And there is a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m an exterminator, I teach extermination, and I guide my disciples in that way.

And there is a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m a mortifier, I teach mortification, and I guide my disciples in that way.

And there is a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m gutless, I teach gutlessness, and I guide my disciples in that way.

And there is a sense in which you could rightly say that I’m ambitious, I teach ambition, and I guide my disciples in that way.

And what’s the sense in which you could rightly say that I believe in inaction, I teach inaction, and I guide my disciples in that way? I teach inaction regarding bad bodily, verbal, and mental conduct, and the many kinds of unskillful things. In this sense you could rightly say that I teach inaction.

And what’s the sense in which you could rightly say that I believe in action, I teach action, and I guide my disciples in that way? I teach action regarding good bodily, verbal, and mental conduct, and the many kinds of skillful things. In this sense you could rightly say that I teach action.

And what’s the sense in which you could rightly say that I believe in annihilationism, I teach annihilation, and I guide my disciples in that way? I teach the annihilation of greed, hate, and delusion, and the many kinds of unskillful things. In this sense you could rightly say that I teach annihilationism.

And what’s the sense in which you could rightly say that I’m disgusted, I teach disgust, and I guide my disciples in that way? I’m disgusted by bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind, and by attainment of the many kinds of unskillful things. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m disgusted.

And what’s the sense in which you could rightly say that I’m an exterminator, I teach extermination, and I guide my disciples in that way? I teach the extermination of greed, hate, and delusion, and the many kinds of unskillful things. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m an exterminator.

And what’s the sense in which you could rightly say that I’m a mortifier, I teach mortification, and I guide my disciples in that way? I say that bad conduct by way of body, speech, and mind should be mortified. I say that a mortifier is someone who has given up unskillful qualities that should be mortified. They’ve cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so that they’re unable to arise in the future. The Realized One is someone who has given up unskillful qualities that should be mortified. He has cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so that they’re unable to arise in the future. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m a mortifier.

And what’s the sense in which you could rightly say that I’m gutless, I teach gutlessness, and I guide my disciples in that way? I say that a gutless person is someone who has given up future wombs and rebirth into a new state of existence. They’ve cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so that they’re unable to arise in the future. The Realized One has given up future wombs and regeneration into a new state of existence. He has cut them off at the root, made them like a palm stump, obliterated them, so that they’re unable to arise in the future. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m gutless.

And what’s the sense in which you could rightly say that I’m ambitious, I teach ambition, and I guide my disciples in that way? I’m ambitious to offer solace, the highest solace, I teach solace, and I guide my disciples in that way. In this sense you could rightly say that I’m ambitious.”

When he said this, General Sīha said to the Buddha, “Excellent, sir! Excellent! From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

“Sīha, you should act after careful consideration. It’s good for well-known people such as yourself to act after careful consideration.”

“Now I’m even more delighted and satisfied with the Buddha, since he tells me to act after careful consideration. For if the followers of other religions were to gain me as a disciple, they’d carry a banner all over Vesālī, saying: ‘General Sīha has become our disciple!’ And yet the Buddha tells me to act after careful consideration. For a second time, I go for refuge to the Buddha, to the teaching, and to the mendicant Saṅgha. From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

“For a long time now, Sīha, your family has been a well-spring of support for the Jain ascetics. You should consider giving to them when they come.”

“Now I’m even more delighted and satisfied with the Buddha, since he tells me to consider giving to the Jain ascetics when they come. Sir, I have heard that the ascetic Gotama says this: ‘Gifts should only be given to me, and to my disciples. Only what is given to me is very fruitful, not what is given to others. Only what is given to my disciples is very fruitful, not what is given to the disciples of others.’ Yet the Buddha encourages me to give to the Jain ascetics. Well, sir, we’ll know the proper time for that. For a third time, I go for refuge to the Buddha, to the teaching, and to the mendicant Saṅgha. From this day forth, may the Buddha remember me as a lay follower who has gone for refuge for life.”

Then the Buddha taught Sīha step by step, with a talk on giving, ethical conduct, and heaven. He revealed the drawbacks of sensual pleasures, so sordid and corrupt, and the benefit of renunciation. And when the Buddha knew that Sīha’s mind was ready, pliable, rid of hindrances, elated, and confident he revealed the special teaching of the Buddhas: suffering, its origin, its cessation, and the path. Just as a clean cloth rid of stains would properly absorb dye, in that very seat the stainless, immaculate vision of the Dhamma arose in General Sīha: “Everything that is liable to arise is liable to cease.”

Then Sīha saw, attained, understood, and fathomed the Dhamma. He went beyond doubt, got rid of indecision, and became self-assured and independent of others regarding the Teacher’s instructions. He said to the Buddha, “Sir, would the Buddha together with the mendicant Saṅgha please accept tomorrow’s meal from me?” The Buddha consented with silence. Then, knowing that the Buddha had consented, Sīha rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

Then Sīha addressed a certain man, “My man, please find out if there is any meat ready for sale.” And when the night had passed General Sīha had delicious fresh and cooked foods prepared in his own home. Then he had the Buddha informed of the time, saying, “Sir, it’s time. The meal is ready.”

Then the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to Sīha’s home, where he sat down on the seat spread out together with the Saṅgha of mendicants. Now at that time many Jain ascetics in Vesālī went from street to street and from square to square, calling out with raised arms: “Today General Sīha has slaughtered a fat calf for the ascetic Gotama’s meal. The ascetic Gotama knowingly eats meat prepared specially for him: this is a deed he caused.”

Then a certain person went up to Sīha and whispered in his ear, “Please sir, you should know this. Many Jain ascetics in Vesālī are going from street to street and square to square, calling out with raised arms: ‘Today General Sīha has slaughtered a fat calf for the ascetic Gotama’s meal. The ascetic Gotama knowingly eats meat prepared specially for him: this is a deed he caused.’”

“Enough, master. For a long time those venerables have wanted to discredit the Buddha, his teaching, and his Saṅgha. They’ll never stop misrepresenting the Buddha with their incorrect, hollow, false, untruthful claims. We would never deliberately take the life of a living creature, not even for life’s sake.”

Then Sīha served and satisfied the mendicant Saṅgha headed by the Buddha with his own hands with delicious fresh and cooked foods. When the Buddha had eaten and washed his hand and bowl, Sīha sat down to one side. Then the Buddha educated, encouraged, fired up, and inspired him with a Dhamma talk, after which he rose from his seat and left.

AN 8.13 A Thoroughbred Assājānīyasutta

“Mendicants, a fine royal thoroughbred with eight factors is worthy of a king, fit to serve a king, and reckoned a factor of kingship. What eight?

It’s when a fine royal thoroughbred is well born on both the mother’s and the father’s sides.

He’s bred in the region fine thoroughbreds come from.

Whatever food he’s given, fresh or dry, he eats carefully, without making a mess.

He’s disgusted by sitting or lying down in excrement or urine.

He’s gentle and pleasant to live with, and he doesn’t upset the other horses.

He openly shows his tricks, bluffs, ruses, and feints to his trainer, so the trainer can try to subdue them.

He carries his load, determining: ‘Whether or not the other horses carry their loads, I’ll carry mine.’

He always walks in a straight path. He’s strong, and stays strong even until death.

A fine royal thoroughbred with these eight factors is worthy of a king. …

In the same way, a mendicant with eight qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world. What eight?

It’s when a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken.

Whatever food they’re given, coarse or fine, they eat carefully, without bother.

They’re disgusted with bad conduct by way of body, speech, or mind, and by attainment of the many kinds of unskillful things.

They’re gentle and pleasant to live with, and they don’t upset the other mendicants.

They openly show their tricks, bluffs, ruses, and feints to their sensible spiritual companions, so they can try to subdue them.

They do their training, determining: ‘Whether or not the other mendicants do their training, I’ll do mine.’

They always walk in a straight path. And here the straight path is right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion.

They’re energetic: ‘Gladly, let my skin, sinews, and bones remain! Let the blood and flesh waste away in my body! I will not stop trying until I have achieved what is possible by human strength, energy, and vigor.’

A mendicant with these eight qualities is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of veneration with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.”

AN 8.14 A Wild Colt Assakhaḷuṅkasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you about eight wild colts and eight defects in horses, and about eight wild people and eight defects in people. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“And what, mendicants, are the eight wild colts and eight defects in horses?

Firstly, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, some wild colts back right up and spin the chariot behind them. Some wild colts are like that. This is the first defect of a horse.

Furthermore, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, some wild colts jump back, wreck the hub, and break the triple rod. Some wild colts are like that. This is the second defect of a horse.

Furthermore, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, some wild colts shake the draft-pole off their thigh and trample it. Some wild colts are like that. This is the third defect of a horse.

Furthermore, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, some wild colts take a wrong turn, sending the chariot off track. Some wild colts are like that. This is the fourth defect of a horse.

Furthermore, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, some wild colts rear up and strike out with their fore-legs. Some wild colts are like that. This is the fifth defect of a horse.

Furthermore, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, some wild colts ignore the trainer and the goad, spit out the bit, and go wherever they want. Some wild colts are like that. This is the sixth defect of a horse.

Furthermore, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, some wild colts don’t step forward or turn back but stand right there still as a post. Some wild colts are like that. This is the seventh defect of a horse.

Furthermore, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, some wild colts tuck in their fore-legs and hind-legs, and sit right down on their four legs. Some wild colts are like that. This is the eighth defect of a horse. These are the eight wild colts and the eight defects in horses.

And what are the eight wild people and eight defects in people?

Firstly, the mendicants accuse a mendicant of an offense. But the accused mendicant evades it by saying they don’t remember. I say that this individual is comparable to the wild colts who, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, back right up and spin the chariot behind them. Some wild people are like that. This is the first defect of a person.

Furthermore, the mendicants accuse a mendicant of an offense. But the accused mendicant objects to the accuser: ‘What has an incompetent fool like you got to say? How on earth could you imagine you’ve got something worth saying!’ I say that this individual is comparable to the wild colts who, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, jump back, wreck the hub, and break the triple rod. Some wild people are like that. This is the second defect of a person.

Furthermore, the mendicants accuse a mendicant of an offense. But the accused mendicant retorts to the accuser: ‘Well, you’ve fallen into an offense named such-and-such. You should deal with that first.’ I say that this individual is comparable to the wild colts who, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, shake the draft-pole off their thigh and trample it. Some wild people are like that. This is the third defect of a person.

Furthermore, the mendicants accuse a mendicant of an offense. But the accused mendicant dodges the issue, distracts the discussion with irrelevant points, and displays annoyance, hate, and bitterness. I say that this individual is comparable to the wild colts who, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, take a wrong turn, sending the chariot off track. Some wild people are like that. This is the fourth defect of a person.

Furthermore, the mendicants accuse a mendicant of an offense. But the accused mendicant gesticulates while speaking in the middle of the Saṅgha. I say that this individual is comparable to the wild colts who, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, rear up and strike out with their fore-legs. Some wild people are like that. This is the fifth defect of a person.

Furthermore, the mendicants accuse a mendicant of an offense. But the accused mendicant ignores the Saṅgha and the accusation and, though still guilty of the offense, they go wherever they want. I say that this individual is comparable to the wild colts who, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, ignore the trainer and the goad, spit out the bit, and go wherever they want. Some wild people are like that. This is the sixth defect of a person.

Furthermore, the mendicants accuse a mendicant of an offense. But the accused mendicant neither confesses to the offense nor denies it, but frustrates the Saṅgha by staying silent. I say that this individual is comparable to the wild colts who, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, don’t step forward or turn back but stand right there still as a post. Some wild people are like that. This is the seventh defect of a person.

Furthermore, the mendicants accuse a mendicant of an offense. But the accused mendicant says this: ‘Why are you venerables making so much of an issue over me? Now I’ll resign the training and return to a lesser life.’ When they have resigned the training, they say: ‘Well, venerables, are you happy now?’ I say that this individual is comparable to the wild colts who, when the trainer says ‘giddyup!’ and spurs and goads them on, tuck in their fore-legs and hind-legs, and sit right down on their four legs. Some wild people are like that. This is the eighth defect of a person.

These are the eight wild people and eight defects in people.”

AN 8.15 Stains Malasutta

“Mendicants, there are these eight stains. What eight? Not rehearsing is the stain of hymns. Neglect is the stain of houses. Laziness is the stain of beauty. Negligence is a guard’s stain. Misconduct is a woman’s stain. Stinginess is a giver’s stain. Bad, unskillful qualities are a stain in this world and the next. Worse than any of these is ignorance, the worst stain of all. These are the eight stains.

Not rehearsing is the stain of hymns.
The stain of houses is neglect.
Laziness is the stain of beauty.
A guard’s stain is negligence.

Misconduct is a woman’s stain.
A giver’s stain is stinginess.
Bad qualities are a stain
in this world and the next.
But a worse stain than these
is ignorance, the worst stain of all.”

AN 8.16 Going on a Mission Dūteyyasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with eight qualities is worthy of going on a mission. What eight? It’s a mendicant who learns and educates others. They memorize and remember. They understand and help others understand. They’re skilled at knowing what’s on topic and what isn’t. And they don’t cause quarrels. A mendicant with these eight qualities is worthy of going on a mission.

Having eight qualities Sāriputta is worthy of going on a mission. What eight? He learns and educates others. He memorizes and remembers. He understands and helps others understand. He’s skilled at knowing what’s on topic and what isn’t. And he doesn’t cause quarrels. Having these eight qualities Sāriputta is worthy of going on a mission.

They don’t tremble when arriving
at an assembly of fierce debaters.
They don’t miss out any words,
or conceal the instructions.

Their words aren’t poisoned,
and they don’t tremble when questioned.
Such a mendicant
is worthy of going on a mission.”

AN 8.17 Catching (1st) Paṭhamabandhanasutta

“Mendicants, a woman catches a man using eight features. What eight? With weeping, laughing, speaking, appearance, gifts of wildflowers, scents, tastes, and touches. A woman catches a man using these eight features. But those beings who are caught by touch are well and truly caught.”

AN 8.18 Catching (2nd) Dutiyabandhanasutta

“Mendicants, a man catches a woman using eight features. What eight? With weeping, laughing, speaking, appearance, gifts of wildflowers, scents, tastes, and touches. A man catches a woman using these eight features. But those beings who are caught by touch are well and truly caught.”

AN 8.19 With Pahārāda Pahārādasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in Verañjā at the root of a neem tree dedicated to Naḷeru.

Then Pahārāda, lord of titans, went up to the Buddha, bowed, and stood to one side. The Buddha said to him, “Well, Pahārāda, do the titans love the ocean?”

“Sir, they do indeed.”

“But seeing what incredible and amazing things do the titans love the ocean?”

“Sir, seeing eight incredible and amazing things the titans love the ocean. What eight? The ocean gradually slants, slopes, and inclines, with no abrupt precipice. This is the first thing the titans love about the ocean.

Furthermore, the ocean is consistent and doesn’t overflow its boundaries. This is the second thing the titans love about the ocean.

Furthermore, the ocean doesn’t accommodate a carcass, but quickly carries it to the shore and strands it on the beach. This is the third thing the titans love about the ocean.

Furthermore, when they reach the ocean, all the great rivers—that is, the Ganges, Yamunā, Aciravatī, Sarabhū, and Mahī—lose their names and clans and are simply reckoned as ‘the ocean’. This is the fourth thing the titans love about the ocean.

Furthermore, for all the world’s streams that reach it, and the showers that fall from the sky, the ocean never empties or fills up. This is the fifth thing the titans love about the ocean.

Furthermore, the ocean has just one taste, the taste of salt. This is the sixth thing the titans love about the ocean.

Furthermore, the ocean is full of many kinds of treasures, such as pearls, gems, beryl, conch, quartz, coral, silver, native gold, rubies, and emeralds. This is the seventh thing the titans love about the ocean.

Furthermore, many great beings live in the ocean, such as leviathans, leviathan-gulpers, leviathan-gulper-gulpers, titans, dragons, and centaurs. In the ocean there are life-forms a hundred leagues long, or even two hundred, three hundred, four hundred, or five hundred leagues long. This is the eighth thing the titans love about the ocean.

Seeing these eight incredible and amazing things the titans love the ocean.

Well, sir, do the mendicants love this teaching and training?”

“They do indeed, Pahārāda.”

“But seeing how many incredible and amazing things do the mendicants love this teaching and training?”

“Seeing eight incredible and amazing things, Pahārāda, the mendicants love this teaching and training. What eight?

The ocean gradually slants, slopes, and inclines, with no abrupt precipice. In the same way in this teaching and training the penetration to enlightenment comes from gradual training, progress, and practice, not abruptly. This is the first thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training.

The ocean is consistent and doesn’t overflow its boundaries. In the same way, when a training rule is laid down for my disciples they wouldn’t break it even for the sake of their own life. This is the second thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training.

The ocean doesn’t accommodate a carcass, but quickly carries it to the shore and strands it on the beach. In the same way, the Saṅgha doesn’t accommodate an individual who is unethical, of bad qualities, filthy, with suspicious behavior, underhand, no true ascetic or spiritual practitioner—though claiming to be one—rotten inside, festering, and depraved. But they quickly gather and expel them. Even if they are sitting in the middle of the Saṅgha, they’re far from the Saṅgha, and the Saṅgha is far from them. This is the third thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training.

When they reach the ocean, all the great rivers—that is, the Ganges, Yamunā, Aciravatī, Sarabhū, and Mahī—lose their names and clans and are simply reckoned as ‘the ocean’. In the same way, when they go forth from the lay life to homelessness, all four classes—aristocrats, brahmins, peasants, and menials—lose their former names and clans and are simply reckoned as ‘ascetics who follow the Sakyan’. This is the fourth thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training.

For all the world’s streams that reach it, and the showers that fall from the sky, the ocean never empties or fills up. In the same way, though several mendicants become fully extinguished in the element of extinguishment with no residue, the element of extinguishment never empties or fills up. This is the fifth thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training.

The ocean has just one taste, the taste of salt. In the same way, this teaching and training has one taste, the taste of freedom. This is the sixth thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training.

The ocean is full of many kinds of treasures, such as pearls, gems, beryl, conch, quartz, coral, silver, native gold, rubies, and emeralds. In the same way, this teaching and training is full of many kinds of treasures, such as the four kinds of mindfulness meditation, the four right efforts, the four bases of psychic power, the five faculties, the five powers, the seven awakening factors, and the noble eightfold path. This is the seventh thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training.

Many great beings live in the ocean, such as leviathans, leviathan-gulpers, leviathan-gulper-gulpers, titans, dragons, and centaurs. In the ocean there are life-forms a hundred leagues long, or even two hundred, three hundred, four hundred, or five hundred leagues long. In the same way, great beings live in this teaching and training, and these are those beings. The stream-enterer and the one practicing to realize the fruit of stream-entry. The once-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of once-return. The non-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of non-return. The perfected one, and the one practicing for perfection. This is the eighth thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training.

Seeing these eight incredible and amazing things, Pahārāda, the mendicants love this teaching and training.”

AN 8.20 Sabbath Uposathasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother in the Eastern Monastery.

Now, at that time it was the sabbath, and the Buddha was sitting surrounded by the Saṅgha of monks. And then, as the night was getting late, in the first watch of the night, Venerable Ānanda rose from his seat, arranged his robe over one shoulder, raised his cupped palms toward the Buddha and said, “Sir, the night is getting late. It is the first watch of the night, and the Saṅgha of monks has been sitting long. Please, sir, may the Buddha recite the monastic code to the monks.”

But when he said this, the Buddha kept silent.

For a second time, as the night was getting late, in the middle watch of the night, Ānanda rose from his seat, arranged his robe over one shoulder, raised his cupped palms toward the Buddha and said, “Sir, the night is getting late. It is the middle watch of the night, and the Saṅgha of monks has been sitting long. Please, sir, may the Buddha recite the monastic code to the monks.”

But for a second time the Buddha kept silent.

For a third time, as the night was getting late, in the last watch of the night, as dawn stirred, bringing joy to the night, Ānanda rose from his seat, arranged his robe over one shoulder, raised his cupped palms toward the Buddha and said, “Sir, the night is getting late. It is the last watch of the night and dawn stirs, bringing joy to the night. And the Saṅgha has been sitting long. Please, sir, may the Buddha recite the monastic code to the monks.”

“Ānanda, the assembly is not pure.”

Then Venerable Mahāmoggallāna thought, “Who is the Buddha talking about?”

Then he focused on encompassing the minds of everyone in the Saṅgha. He saw that unethical individual, of bad qualities, filthy, with suspicious behavior, underhand, no true ascetic or spiritual practitioner—though claiming to be one—rotten inside, festering, and depraved, sitting in the middle of the Saṅgha.

When he saw him he rose from his seat, went up to him and said, “Get up, reverend. The Buddha has seen you. You can’t live in communion with the monks.”

But when he said this, that individual kept silent.

For a second time

and a third time, he asked that monk to leave.

But for a third time that individual kept silent.

Then Venerable Mahāmoggallāna took that individual by the arm, ejected him out the gate, and bolted the door. Then he went up to the Buddha, and said to him, “I have ejected that individual. The assembly is pure. Please, sir, may the Buddha recite the monastic code to the monks.”

“It’s incredible, Moggallāna, it’s amazing, how that futile man waited to be taken by the arm!”

Then the Buddha said to the monks:

“Now, monks, you should perform the sabbath and recite the monastic code. From this day forth, I will not perform the sabbath or recite the monastic code. It’s impossible, monks, it can’t happen that a Realized One could recite the monastic code in an impure assembly.

Seeing these eight incredible and amazing things the titans love the ocean. What eight? The ocean gradually slants, slopes, and inclines, with no abrupt precipice. This is the first thing the titans love about the ocean.

(Tell in full as in the previous discourse.)

Furthermore, many great beings live in the ocean, such as leviathans, leviathan-gulpers, leviathan-gulper-gulpers, titans, dragons, and centaurs. In the ocean there are life-forms a hundred leagues long, or even two hundred, three hundred, four hundred, or five hundred leagues long. This is the eighth thing the titans love about the ocean. Seeing these eight incredible and amazing things the titans love the ocean.

In the same way, seeing eight incredible and amazing things, monks, the mendicants love this teaching and training. What eight?

The ocean gradually slants, slopes, and inclines, with no abrupt precipice. In the same way in this teaching and training the penetration to enlightenment comes from gradual training, progress, and practice, not abruptly. This is the first thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training. …

Many great beings live in the ocean, such as leviathans, leviathan-gulpers, leviathan-gulper-gulpers, titans, dragons, and centaurs. In the ocean there are life-forms a hundred leagues long, or even two hundred, three hundred, four hundred, or five hundred leagues long. In the same way, great beings live in this teaching and training, and these are those beings. The stream-enterer and the one practicing to realize the fruit of stream-entry. The once-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of once-return. The non-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of non-return. The perfected one, and the one practicing for perfection. This is the eighth thing the mendicants love about this teaching and training.

Seeing these eight incredible and amazing things, the mendicants love this teaching and training.”

The First Fifty

The Chapter on Love

AN 8.1 The Benefits of Love Mettāsutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, you can expect eight benefits when the heart’s release by love has been cultivated, developed, and practiced, made a vehicle and a basis, kept up, consolidated, and properly implemented. What eight? You sleep at ease. You wake happily. You don’t have bad dreams. Humans love you. Non-humans love you. Deities protect you. You can’t be harmed by fire, poison, or blade. If you don’t penetrate any higher, you’ll be reborn in a realm of divinity. You can expect these eight benefits when the heart’s release by love has been cultivated, developed, and practiced, made a vehicle and a basis, kept up, consolidated, and properly implemented.

A mindful one who develops
limitless love
weakens the fetters,
seeing the ending of attachments.

Loving just one creature with a hateless heart
makes you a true person.
Sympathetic for all creatures,
a noble one creates abundant merit.

The royal potentates conquered this land
and traveled around sponsoring sacrifices—
horse sacrifice, human sacrifice,
the sacrifices of the ‘casting of the yoke-pin’, the ‘royal soma drinking’, and the ‘unimpeded’.

These are not worth a sixteenth part
of the mind developed with love,
as all the constellations of stars
aren’t worth a sixteenth part of the moon’s light.

Don’t kill or cause others to kill,
don’t conquer or encourage others to conquer,
with love for all sentient beings,
you’ll have no enmity for anyone.”

AN 8.2 Wisdom Paññāsutta

“Mendicants, there are eight causes and reasons that lead to acquiring the wisdom fundamental to the spiritual life, and to its increase, growth, and full development once it has been acquired. What eight?

It’s when a mendicant lives relying on the Teacher or a spiritual companion in a teacher’s role. And they set up a keen sense of conscience and prudence for them, with warmth and respect. This is the first cause.

When a mendicant lives relying on the Teacher or a spiritual companion in a teacher’s role—with a keen sense of conscience and prudence for them, with warmth and respect—from time to time they go and ask them questions: ‘Why, sir, does it say this? What does that mean?’ Those venerables reveal what is hidden, clarify what is unclear, and dispel doubt regarding the many doubtful matters. This is the second cause.

After hearing that teaching they perfect withdrawal of both body and mind. This is the third cause.

A mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. This is the fourth cause.

They’re very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. These teachings are good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased, describing a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. They are very learned in such teachings, remembering them, rehearsing them, mentally scrutinizing them, and penetrating them theoretically. This is the fifth cause.

They live with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They’re strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. This is the sixth cause.

When in the Saṅgha they don’t engage in motley talk or low talk. Either they talk on Dhamma, or they invite someone else to do so, or they respect noble silence. This is the seventh cause.

They meditate observing rise and fall in the five grasping aggregates. ‘Such is form, such is the origin of form, such is the disappearance of form. Such is feeling, such is the origin of feeling, such is the disappearance of feeling. Such is perception, such is the origin of perception, such is the disappearance of perception. Such are choices, such is the origin of choices, such is the disappearance of choices. Such is consciousness, such is the origin of consciousness, such is the disappearance of consciousness.’ This is the eighth cause.

Their spiritual companions esteem them: ‘This venerable lives relying on the Teacher or a spiritual companion in a teacher’s role. They set up a keen sense of conscience and prudence for them, with warmth and respect. Clearly this venerable knows and sees.’ This quality leads to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

‘This venerable lives relying on the Teacher or a spiritual companion in a teacher’s role, and from time to time they go and ask them questions … Clearly this venerable knows and sees.’ This quality also leads to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

‘After hearing that teaching they perfect withdrawal of both body and mind. Clearly this venerable knows and sees.’ This quality also leads to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

‘This venerable is ethical … Clearly this venerable knows and sees.’ This quality also leads to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

‘This venerable is very learned, remembering and keeping what they’ve learned. … Clearly this venerable knows and sees.’ This quality also leads to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

‘This venerable lives with energy roused up … Clearly this venerable knows and sees.’ This quality also leads to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

‘When in the Saṅgha they don’t engage in motley talk or low talk. Either they talk on Dhamma, or they invite someone else to do so, or they respect noble silence. Clearly this venerable knows and sees.’ This quality also leads to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

‘They meditate observing rise and fall in the five grasping aggregates. … Clearly this venerable knows and sees.’ This quality also leads to fondness, respect, esteem, harmony, and unity.

These are the eight causes and reasons that lead to acquiring the wisdom fundamental to the spiritual life, and to its increase, growth, and full development once it has been acquired.”

AN 8.3 Disliked (1st) Paṭhamaappiyasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with eight qualities is disliked and disapproved by their spiritual companions, not respected or admired. What eight? It’s when a mendicant praises the disliked and criticizes the liked. They desire material things and honor. They lack conscience and prudence. They have corrupt wishes and wrong view. A mendicant with these eight qualities is disliked and disapproved by their spiritual companions, not respected or admired.

A mendicant with eight qualities is liked and approved by their spiritual companions, and respected and admired. What eight? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t praise the disliked and criticize the liked. They don’t desire material things and honor. They have conscience and prudence. They have few desires and right view. A mendicant with these eight qualities is liked and approved by their spiritual companions, and respected and admired.”

AN 8.4 Disliked (2nd) Dutiyaappiyasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant with eight qualities is disliked and disapproved by their spiritual companions, not respected or admired. What eight? It’s when a mendicant desires material things, honor, and status. They know neither moderation nor the proper time. Their conduct is impure, they talk a lot, and they insult and abuse their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these eight qualities is disliked and disapproved by their spiritual companions, not respected or admired.

A mendicant with eight qualities is liked and approved by their spiritual companions, and respected and admired. What eight? It’s when a mendicant doesn’t desire material things, honor, and status. They know moderation and the proper time. Their conduct is pure, they don’t talk a lot, and they don’t insult and abuse their spiritual companions. A mendicant with these eight qualities is liked and approved by their spiritual companions, and respected and admired.”

AN 8.5 Worldly Conditions (1st) Paṭhamalokadhammasutta

“Mendicants, the eight worldly conditions revolve around the world, and the world revolves around the eight worldly conditions. What eight? Gain and loss, fame and disgrace, blame and praise, pleasure and pain. These eight worldly conditions revolve around the world, and the world revolves around these eight worldly conditions.

Gain and loss, fame and disgrace,
blame and praise, and pleasure and pain.
These qualities among mankind are impermanent,
transient, and perishable.

An intelligent and mindful person knows these things,
seeing that they’re perishable.
Desirable things don’t disturb their mind,
nor are they repelled by the undesirable.

Both favoring and opposing
are cleared and disappeared, they are no more.
Knowing the stainless, sorrowless state,
they who have gone beyond rebirth understand rightly.”

AN 8.6 Worldly Conditions (2nd) Dutiyalokadhammasutta

“Mendicants, the eight worldly conditions revolve around the world, and the world revolves around the eight worldly conditions. What eight? Gain and loss, fame and disgrace, blame and praise, pleasure and pain. These eight worldly conditions revolve around the world, and the world revolves around these eight worldly conditions.

An unlearned ordinary person encounters gain and loss, fame and disgrace, blame and praise, and pleasure and pain. And so does a learned noble disciple. What, then, is the difference between a learned noble disciple and an ordinary unlearned person?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. Sir, may the Buddha himself please clarify the meaning of this. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, mendicants, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, an unlearned ordinary person encounters gain. They don’t reflect: ‘I’ve encountered this gain. It’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable.’ They don’t truly understand it. They encounter loss … fame … disgrace … blame … praise … pleasure … pain. They don’t reflect: ‘I’ve encountered this pain. It’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable.’ They don’t truly understand it.

So gain and loss, fame and disgrace, blame and praise, and pleasure and pain occupy their mind. They favor gain and oppose loss. They favor fame and oppose disgrace. They favor praise and oppose blame. They favor pleasure and oppose pain. Being so full of favoring and opposing, they’re not freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from suffering, I say.

A learned noble disciple encounters gain. They reflect: ‘I’ve encountered this gain. It’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable.’ They truly understand it. They encounter loss … fame … disgrace … blame … praise … pleasure … pain. They reflect: ‘I’ve encountered this pain. It’s impermanent, suffering, and perishable.’ They truly understand it.

So gain and loss, fame and disgrace, blame and praise, and pleasure and pain don’t occupy their mind. They don’t favor gain or oppose loss. They don’t favor fame or oppose disgrace. They don’t favor praise or oppose blame. They don’t favor pleasure or oppose pain. Having given up favoring and opposing, they’re freed from rebirth, old age, and death, from sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re freed from suffering, I say. This is the difference between a learned noble disciple and an unlearned ordinary person.

Gain and loss, fame and disgrace,
blame and praise, and pleasure and pain.
These qualities among mankind are impermanent,
transient, and perishable.

An intelligent and mindful person knows these things,
seeing that they’re perishable.
Desirable things don’t disturb their mind,
nor are they repelled by the undesirable.

Both favoring and opposing
are cleared and disappeared, they are no more.
Knowing the stainless, sorrowless state,
they who have gone beyond rebirth understand rightly.”

AN 8.7 Devadatta’s Failure Devadattavipattisutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain, not long after Devadatta had left. There the Buddha spoke to the mendicants about Devadatta:

“Mendicants, it’s good for a mendicant to check their own failings from time to time. It’s good for a mendicant to check the failings of others from time to time. It’s good for a mendicant to check their own successes from time to time. It’s good for a mendicant to check the successes of others from time to time. Overcome and overwhelmed by eight things that oppose the true teaching, Devadatta is going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable.

What eight? Overcome and overwhelmed by gain … loss … fame … disgrace … honor … dishonor … corrupt wishes … bad friendship, Devadatta is going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable. Overcome and overwhelmed by these eight things that oppose the true teaching, Devadatta is going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable.

It’s good for a mendicant, whenever they encounter it, to overcome gain … loss … fame … disgrace … honor … dishonor … corrupt wishes … bad friendship.

What advantage does a mendicant gain by overcoming these eight things?

The distressing and feverish defilements that might arise in someone who lives without overcoming these eight things do not arise when they have overcome them. This is the advantage that a mendicant gains by overcoming these eight things.

So, mendicants, you should train like this: ‘Whenever we encounter it, we will overcome gain … loss … fame … disgrace … honor … dishonor … corrupt wishes … bad friendship.’ That’s how you should train.”

AN 8.8 Uttara on Failure Uttaravipattisutta

At one time Venerable Uttara was staying on the Saṅkheyyaka Mountain in the Mahisa region near Dhavajālikā. There Uttara addressed the mendicants: “Mendicants, it’s good for a mendicant to check their own failings from time to time. It’s good for a mendicant to check the failings of others from time to time. It’s good for a mendicant to check their own successes from time to time. It’s good for a mendicant to check the successes of others from time to time.”

Now at that time the great king Vessavaṇa was on his way from the north to the south on some business. He heard Venerable Uttara teaching this to the mendicants on Saṅkheyyaka Mountain.

Then Vessavaṇa vanished from Saṅkheyyaka Mountain and appeared among the gods of the thirty-three, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm. Then he went up to Sakka, lord of gods, and said to him:

“Please good fellow, you should know this. Venerable Uttara is teaching the mendicants on Saṅkheyyaka Mountain in this way: ‘It’s good for a mendicant from time to time to check their own failings. … the failings of others … their own successes … the successes of others.’”

Then, as easily as a strong person would extend or contract their arm, Sakka vanished from the gods of the thirty-three and reappeared on Saṅkheyyaka Mountain in front of Venerable Uttara. Then Sakka went up to Venerable Uttara, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him:

“Is it really true, sir, that you teach the mendicants in this way: ‘It’s good for a mendicant from time to time to check their own failings … the failings of others … their own successes … the successes of others’?”

“Indeed, lord of gods.”

“Sir, did this teaching come to you from your own inspiration, or was it spoken by the Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha?”

“Well then, lord of gods, I shall give you a simile. For by means of a simile some sensible people understand the meaning of what is said.

Suppose there was a large heap of grain not far from a town or village. And a large crowd were to take away grain with carrying poles, baskets, hip sacks, or their cupped hands. If someone were to go to that crowd and ask them where they got the grain from, how should that crowd rightly reply?”

“Sir, they should reply that they took it from the large heap of grain.”

“In the same way, lord of gods, whatever is well spoken is spoken by the Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha. Both myself and others rely completely on that when we speak.”

“It’s incredible, sir, it’s amazing! How well this was said by Venerable Uttara! ‘Whatever is well spoken is spoken by the Blessed One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha. Both myself and others rely completely on that when we speak.’ At one time, Honorable Uttara, the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain, not long after Devadatta had left. There the Buddha spoke to the mendicants about Devadatta:

‘Mendicants, it’s good for a mendicant from time to time to check their own failings … the failings of others … their own successes … the successes of others. Overcome and overwhelmed by eight things that oppose the true teaching, Devadatta is going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable. What eight? Overcome and overwhelmed by gain … loss … fame … disgrace … honor … dishonor … corrupt wishes … bad friendship, Devadatta is going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable. Overcome and overwhelmed by these eight things that oppose the true teaching, Devadatta is going to a place of loss, to hell, there to remain for an eon, irredeemable.

It’s good for a mendicant, whenever they encounter it, to overcome gain … loss … fame … disgrace … honor … dishonor … corrupt wishes … bad friendship.

What advantage does a mendicant gain by overcoming these eight things?

The distressing and feverish defilements that might arise in someone who lives without overcoming these eight things do not arise when they have overcome them. This is the advantage that a mendicant gains by overcoming these eight things.

So you should train like this:

“Whenever we encounter it, we will overcome gain … loss … fame … disgrace … honor … dishonor … corrupt wishes … bad friendship.” That’s how you should train.’

Honorable Uttara, this exposition of the teaching is not established anywhere in the four assemblies—monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen. Sir, learn this exposition of the teaching! Memorize this exposition of the teaching! Remember this exposition of the teaching! Sir, this exposition of the teaching is beneficial and relevant to the fundamentals of the spiritual life.”

AN 8.9 Nanda Nandasutta

“Mendicants, you could rightly call Nanda ‘Gentleman’, ‘strong’, ‘lovely’, and ‘lustful’. How could he live the full and pure spiritual life unless he guards the sense doors, eats in moderation, is dedicated to wakefulness, and has mindfulness and situational awareness?

This is how Nanda guards the sense doors. If he has to look to the east, he wholeheartedly concentrates before looking, thinking: ‘When I look to the east, bad, unskillful qualities of covetousness and displeasure will not overwhelm me.’ In this way he’s aware of the situation.

If he has to look to the west … north … south … up … down … If he has to survey the intermediate directions, he wholeheartedly concentrates before looking, thinking: ‘When I survey the intermediate directions, bad, unskillful qualities of covetousness and displeasure will not overwhelm me.’ In this way he’s aware of the situation. This is how Nanda guards the sense doors.

This is how Nanda eats in moderation. Nanda reflects rationally on the food he eats: ‘Not for fun, indulgence, adornment, or decoration, but only to sustain this body, to avoid harm, and to support spiritual practice. In this way, I shall put an end to old discomfort and not give rise to new discomfort, and I will have the means to keep going, blamelessness, and a comfortable abiding.’ This is how Nanda eats in moderation.

This is how Nanda is committed to wakefulness. Nanda practices walking and sitting meditation by day, purifying his mind from obstacles. In the first watch of the night, he continues to practice walking and sitting meditation. In the middle watch, he lies down in the lion’s posture—on the right side, placing one foot on top of the other—mindful and aware, and focused on the time of getting up. In the last watch, he gets up and continues to practice walking and sitting meditation, purifying his mind from obstacles. This is how Nanda is committed to wakefulness.

This is how Nanda has mindfulness and situational awareness. Nanda knows feelings as they arise, as they remain, and as they go away. He knows perceptions as they arise, as they remain, and as they go away. He knows thoughts as they arise, as they remain, and as they go away. This is how Nanda has mindfulness and situational awareness.

How could Nanda live the full and pure spiritual life unless he guards the sense doors, eats in moderation, is dedicated to wakefulness, and has mindfulness and situational awareness?”

AN 8.10 Trash Kāraṇḍavasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Campā on the banks of the Gaggarā Lotus Pond. Now at that time the mendicants accused a mendicant of an offense. The accused mendicant dodged the issue, distracted the discussion with irrelevant points, and displayed annoyance, hate, and bitterness.

Then the Buddha said to the mendicants, “Mendicants, throw this individual out! Throw this individual out! This individual should be shown the door. Why should you be vexed by an outsider?

Take a case where a certain individual looks just the same as other good-natured mendicants when going out and coming back, when looking ahead and aside, when bending and extending the limbs, and when bearing the outer robe, bowl and robes. That is, so long as the mendicants don’t notice his offense. But when the mendicants notice the offense, they know that he’s a corrupt ascetic, just useless trash. When they realize this they send him away. Why is that? So that he doesn’t corrupt good-natured mendicants.

Suppose in a growing field of barley some bad barley appeared, just useless trash. Its roots, stem, and leaves would look just the same as the healthy barley. That is, so long as the head doesn’t appear. But when the head appears, they know that it’s bad barley, just useless trash. When they realize this they pull it up by the roots and throw it outside the field. Why is that? So that it doesn’t spoil the good barley.

In the same way, take a case where a certain individual looks just the same as other good-natured mendicants when going out and coming back, when looking ahead and aside, when bending and extending the limbs, and when bearing the outer robe, bowl and robes. That is, so long as the mendicants don’t notice his offense. But when the mendicants notice the offense, they know that he’s a corrupt ascetic, just useless trash. When they realize this they send him away. Why is that? So that he doesn’t corrupt good-natured mendicants.

Suppose that a large heap of grain is being winnowed. The grains that are firm and solid form a heap on one side. And the grains that are flimsy and insubstantial are blown over to the other side. The owners take a broom and sweep them even further away. Why is that? So that it doesn’t spoil the good grain. In the same way, take a case where a certain individual looks just the same as other good-natured mendicants when going out and coming back, when looking ahead and aside, when bending and extending the limbs, and when bearing the outer robe, bowl and robes. That is, so long as the mendicants don’t notice his offense. But when the mendicants notice the offense, they know that he’s a corrupt ascetic, just useless trash. When they realize this they send him away. Why is that? So that he doesn’t corrupt good-natured mendicants.

Suppose a man needs an irrigation gutter for a well. He’d take a sharp axe and enter the wood, where he’d knock various trees with the axe. The trees that were firm and solid made a cracking sound. But the trees that were rotten inside, decomposing and decayed, made a thud. He’d cut down such a tree at the root, lop off the crown, and thoroughly clear out the insides. Then he’d use it as an irrigation gutter for the well. In the same way, take a case where a certain individual looks just the same as other good-natured mendicants when going out and coming back, when looking ahead and aside, when bending and extending the limbs, and when bearing the outer robe, bowl and robes. That is, so long as the mendicants don’t notice his offense. But when the mendicants notice the offense, they know that he’s a corrupt ascetic, just useless trash. When they realize this they send him away. Why is that? So that he doesn’t corrupt good-natured mendicants.

By living together, know that
they’re irritable, with corrupt wishes,
offensive, stubborn, and contemptuous,
jealous, stingy, and devious.

They speak to people with a voice
so smooth, just like an ascetic.
But they act in secret, with their bad views
and their lack of regard for others.

You should recognize them for what they are:
a creep and liar.
Then having gathered in harmony,
you should expel them.

Throw out the trash!
Get rid of the rubbish!
And sweep away the scraps—
they’re not ascetics, they just think they are.

When you’ve thrown out those of corrupt wishes,
of bad behavior and alms-resort,
dwell in communion, ever mindful,
the pure with the pure.
Then in harmony, alert,
you’ll make an end of suffering.”

Abbreviated Texts Beginning With Greed

AN 8.118 Untitled Discourse on Greed (1st) ~

“For insight into greed, eight things should be developed. What eight? Right view, right purpose, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right immersion. For insight into greed, these eight things should be developed.”

AN 8.119 Untitled Discourse on Greed (2nd) ~

“For insight into greed, eight things should be developed. What eight? Perceiving form internally, they see forms externally, limited, both pretty and ugly. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ Perceiving form internally, they see forms externally, limitless, both pretty and ugly. … Not perceiving form internally, they see forms externally, limited, both pretty and ugly. … Not perceiving form internally, they see forms externally, limitless, both pretty and ugly. … Not perceiving form internally, they see forms externally, blue, with blue color and blue appearance. … yellow … red … Not perceiving form internally, they see forms externally, white, with white color and white appearance. Mastering them, they perceive: ‘I know and see.’ For insight into greed, these eight things should be developed.”

AN 8.120 Untitled Discourse on Greed (3rd) ~

“For insight into greed, eight things should be developed. What eight? Having physical form, they see forms … not perceiving form internally, they see forms externally … they’re focused only on beauty … going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite space … going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite consciousness … going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, they enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness … going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, they enter and remain in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception … going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, they enter and remain in the cessation of perception and feeling … For insight into greed, these eight things should be developed.”

AN 8.121–147 Untitled Discourses on Greed ~

“For the complete understanding of greed … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … letting go … these eight things should be developed.”

AN 8.148–627 Untitled Discourses on Hate, Etc. ~

“For insight into hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … jealousy … stinginess … deceitfulness … deviousness … obstinacy … aggression … conceit … arrogance … vanity …

For insight into negligence … complete understanding … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … For the letting go of negligence these eight things should be developed.”

The Book of the Eights is finished.

The Chapter on Mindfulness

AN 8.81 Mindfulness and Situational Awareness Satisampajaññasutta

“Mendicants, when there is no mindfulness and situational awareness, one who lacks mindfulness and situational awareness has destroyed a vital condition for conscience and prudence. When there is no conscience and prudence, one who lacks conscience and prudence has destroyed a vital condition for sense restraint. When there is no sense restraint, one who lacks sense restraint has destroyed a vital condition for ethical conduct. When there is no ethical conduct, one who lacks ethics has destroyed a vital condition for right immersion. When there is no right immersion, one who lacks right immersion has destroyed a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is no true knowledge and vision, one who lacks true knowledge and vision has destroyed a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is no disillusionment and dispassion, one who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that lacked branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would not grow to fullness.

In the same way, when there is no mindfulness and situational awareness, one who lacks mindfulness and situational awareness has destroyed a vital condition for conscience and prudence. When there is no conscience and prudence … One who lacks disillusionment and dispassion has destroyed a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

When there is mindfulness and situational awareness, one who has fulfilled mindfulness and situational awareness has fulfilled a vital condition for conscience and prudence. When there is conscience and prudence, one who has fulfilled conscience and prudence has fulfilled a vital condition for sense restraint. When there is sense restraint, one who has fulfilled sense restraint has fulfilled a vital condition for ethical conduct. When there is ethical conduct, one who has fulfilled ethical conduct has fulfilled a vital condition for right immersion. When there is right immersion, one who has fulfilled right immersion has fulfilled a vital condition for true knowledge and vision. When there is true knowledge and vision, one who has fulfilled true knowledge and vision has fulfilled a vital condition for disillusionment and dispassion. When there is disillusionment and dispassion, one who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.

Suppose there was a tree that was complete with branches and foliage. Its shoots, bark, softwood, and heartwood would grow to fullness.

In the same way, when there is mindfulness and situational awareness, one who has fulfilled mindfulness and situational awareness has fulfilled a vital condition for conscience and prudence. When there is conscience and prudence … One who has fulfilled disillusionment and dispassion has fulfilled a vital condition for knowledge and vision of freedom.”

AN 8.82 With Puṇṇiya Puṇṇiyasutta

Then Venerable Puṇṇiya went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, what is the cause, what is the reason why sometimes the Realized One feels inspired to teach, and other times not?”

“Puṇṇiya, when a mendicant has faith but doesn’t approach, the Realized One doesn’t feel inspired to teach. But when a mendicant has faith and approaches, the Realized One feels inspired to teach. When a mendicant has faith and approaches, but doesn’t pay homage … they pay homage, but don’t ask questions … they ask questions, but don’t actively listen to the teaching … they actively listen to the teaching, but don’t remember the teaching they’ve heard … they remember the teaching they’ve heard, but don’t examine the meaning of the teachings they’ve remembered … they examine the meaning of the teachings they’ve remembered, but, not having understood the meaning and the teaching, they don’t practice in line with the principle of the teaching. The Realized One doesn’t feel inspired to teach.

But when a mendicant has faith, approaches, pays homage, asks questions, actively listens to the teachings, remembers the teachings, examines the meaning, and practices in line with the principle of the teaching, the Realized One feels inspired to teach. When someone possesses these eight qualities, the Realized One feels totally inspired to teach.”

AN 8.83 Rooted Mūlakasutta

“Mendicants, if wanderers of other religions were to ask: ‘Reverends, all things have what as their root? What produces them? What is their origin? What is their meeting place? What is their chief? What is their ruler? What is their overseer? What is their core?’ How would you answer them?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. He is our guide and our refuge. Sir, may the Buddha himself please clarify the meaning of this. The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, mendicants, I will teach it. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, if wanderers of other religions were to ask: ‘Reverends, all things have what as their root? What produces them? What is their origin? What is their meeting place? What is their chief? What is their ruler? What is their overseer? What is their core?’ You should answer them: ‘Reverends, all things are rooted in desire. They are produced by application of mind. Contact is their origin. Feeling is their meeting place. Immersion is their chief. Mindfulness is their ruler. Wisdom is their overseer. Freedom is their core.’ When questioned by wanderers of other religions, that’s how you should answer them.”

AN 8.84 A Master Thief Corasutta

“Mendicants, a master thief with eight factors is soon executed, and doesn’t have long to live. What eight? He attacks unprovoked. He steals everything without exception. He kills a woman. He rapes a girl. He robs a monk. He robs the royal treasury. He works close to home. He’s not skilled at hiding his booty. A master thief with these eight factors is soon executed, and doesn’t have long to live.

A master thief with eight factors is not soon executed, and lives long. What eight? He doesn’t attack unprovoked. He doesn’t steal everything without exception. He doesn’t kill a woman. He doesn’t rape a girl. He doesn’t rob a monk. He doesn’t rob the royal treasury. He doesn’t work close to home. He’s skilled at hiding his booty. A master thief with these eight factors is not soon executed, and lives long.”

AN 8.85 Terms for the Realized One Samaṇasutta

“‘Ascetic’ is a term for the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha. ‘Brahmin’, ‘Knowledge Master’, ‘Healer’, ‘Unstained’, ‘Immaculate’, ‘Knower’, and ‘Freed’ are terms for the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha.

The supreme should be attained by an ascetic,
a brahmin who has lived the life;
it should be attained by a knowledge master,
a healer.

The supreme should be attained by the unstained,
stainless and pure;
it should be attained by a knower,
who is free.

I am victorious in battle!
Released, I release others from their chains.
I am a giant completely tamed,
an adept, I am quenched.”

AN 8.86 With Nāgita Yasasutta

At one time the Buddha was wandering in the land of the Kosalans together with a large Saṅgha of mendicants when he arrived at a village of the Kosalan brahmins named Icchānaṅgala. He stayed in a forest near Icchānaṅgala. The brahmins and householders of Icchānaṅgala heard:

“It seems the ascetic Gotama—a Sakyan, gone forth from a Sakyan family—has arrived at Icchānaṅgala. He is staying in a forest near Icchānaṅgala. He has this good reputation: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ … It’s good to see such perfected ones.”

Then, when the night had passed, they took abundant fresh and cooked foods and went to the forest near Icchānaṅgala, where they stood outside the gates making a colossal racket.

Now, at that time Venerable Nāgita was the Buddha’s attendant. Then the Buddha said to Nāgita, “Nāgita, who’s making that colossal racket? You’d think it was fishermen hauling in a catch!”

“Sir, it’s these brahmins and householders of Icchānaṅgala. They’ve brought abundant fresh and cooked foods, and they’re standing outside the gates wanting to offer it specially to the Buddha and the mendicant Saṅgha.”

“Nāgita, may I never become famous. May fame not come to me. There are those who can’t get the pleasure of renunciation, the pleasure of seclusion, the pleasure of peace, the pleasure of awakening when they want, without trouble or difficulty like I can. Let them enjoy the filthy, lazy pleasure of possessions, honor, and popularity.”

“Sir, may the Blessed One please relent now! May the Holy One relent! Now is the time for the Buddha to relent. Wherever the Buddha now goes, the brahmins and householders, and people of town and country will incline the same way. It’s like when the heavens rain heavily and the water flows downhill. In the same way, wherever the Buddha now goes, the brahmins and householders, and people of town and country will incline the same way. Why is that? Because of the Buddha’s ethics and wisdom.”

“Nāgita, may I never become famous. May fame not come to me. There are those who can’t get the pleasure of renunciation, the pleasure of seclusion, the pleasure of peace, the pleasure of awakening when they want, without trouble or difficulty like I can. Let them enjoy the filthy, lazy pleasure of possessions, honor, and popularity.

Even some of the deities can’t get the pleasure of renunciation, the pleasure of seclusion, the pleasure of peace, the pleasure of awakening when they want, without trouble or difficulty like I can. When you all come together to enjoy each other’s company, I think: ‘These venerables mustn’t get the pleasure of renunciation, the pleasure of seclusion, the pleasure of peace, the pleasure of awakening when they want, without trouble or difficulty like I can. That must be because they come together to enjoy each other’s company.’

Take mendicants I see poking each other with their fingers, giggling and playing together. I think to myself: ‘These venerables mustn’t get the pleasure of renunciation, the pleasure of seclusion, the pleasure of peace, the pleasure of awakening when they want, without trouble or difficulty like I can. That must be because they’re poking each other with their fingers, giggling and playing together.’

Take mendicants I see eat as much as they like until their bellies are full, then indulge in the pleasures of sleeping, lying down, and drowsing. I think to myself: ‘These venerables mustn’t get the pleasure of renunciation, the pleasure of seclusion, the pleasure of peace, the pleasure of awakening when they want, without trouble or difficulty like I can. That must be because they eat as much as they like until their bellies are full, then indulge in the pleasures of sleeping, lying down, and drowsing.’

Take a mendicant living within a village who I see sitting immersed in samādhi. I think to myself: ‘Now a monastery worker, a novice, or a fellow practitioner will make this venerable fall from immersion.’ So I’m not pleased that that mendicant is living within a village.

Take a mendicant in the wilderness who I see sitting nodding in meditation. I think to myself: ‘Now this venerable, having dispelled that sleepiness and weariness, will focus just on the unified perception of wilderness.’ So I’m pleased that that mendicant is living in the wilderness.

Take a mendicant in the wilderness who I see sitting without being immersed in samādhi. I think to myself: ‘Now if this venerable’s mind is not immersed in samādhi they will immerse it; or if it is immersed in samādhi, they will preserve it.’ So I’m pleased that that mendicant is living in the wilderness.

Take a mendicant in the wilderness who I see sitting immersed in samādhi. I think to myself: ‘Now this venerable will free the unfreed mind or preserve the freed mind.’ So I’m pleased that that mendicant is living in the wilderness.

Take a mendicant who I see living within a village receiving robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. Enjoying possessions, honor, and popularity they neglect retreat, and they neglect remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. They come down to villages, towns, and capital cities and make their home there. So I’m not pleased that that mendicant is living within a village.

Take a mendicant who I see in the wilderness receiving robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. Fending off possessions, honor, and popularity they don’t neglect retreat, and they don’t neglect remote lodgings in the wilderness and the forest. So I’m pleased that that mendicant is living in the wilderness.

Nāgita, when I’m walking along a road and I don’t see anyone ahead or behind I feel relaxed, even if I need to urinate or defecate.”

AN 8.87 Turning the Bowl Upside Down Pattanikujjanasutta

“Mendicants, the Saṅgha may, if it wishes, turn the bowl upside down for a lay follower on eight grounds. What eight? They try to prevent the mendicants from getting material things. They try to harm mendicants. They try to drive mendicants from a monastery. They insult and abuse mendicants. They divide mendicants against each other. They criticize the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha. The Saṅgha may, if it wishes, turn the bowl upside down for a lay follower on these eight grounds.

The Saṅgha may, if it wishes, turn the bowl upright for a lay follower on eight grounds. What eight? They don’t try to prevent the mendicants from getting material things. They don’t try to harm mendicants. They don’t try to drive mendicants from a monastery. They don’t insult and abuse mendicants. They don’t divide mendicants against each other. They don’t criticize the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha. The Saṅgha may, if it wishes, turn the bowl upright for a lay follower on these eight grounds.”

AN 8.88 A Proclamation of No Confidence Appasādapavedanīyasutta

“Mendicants, the lay followers may, if they wish, make a proclamation of no confidence in a mendicant who has eight qualities. What eight? They try to prevent laypeople from getting material things. They try to harm laypeople. They insult and abuse laypeople. They divide lay people against each other. They criticize the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha. They’re seen at an inappropriate place for collecting alms. The lay followers may, if they wish, make a proclamation of no confidence in a mendicant who possesses these eight qualities.

The lay followers may, if they wish, make a proclamation of confidence in a mendicant who has eight qualities. What eight? They don’t try to prevent laypeople from getting material things. They don’t try to harm laypeople. They don’t insult and abuse laypeople. They don’t divide laypeople against each other. They don’t criticize the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha. They’re not seen at an inappropriate place for collecting alms. The lay followers may, if they wish, make a proclamation of confidence in a mendicant who possesses these eight qualities.”

AN 8.89 Reconciliation Paṭisāraṇīyasutta

“Mendicants, the Saṅgha may, if it wishes, perform an act requiring that a mendicant who has eight qualities should pursue reconciliation. What eight? They try to prevent laypeople from getting material things. They try to harm laypeople. They insult and abuse lay people. They divide laypeople against each other. They criticize the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha. They don’t keep a legitimate promise made to a layperson. The Saṅgha may, if it wishes, perform an act requiring that a mendicant who has eight qualities should pursue reconciliation.

The Saṅgha may, if it wishes, revoke the act requiring that a mendicant who has eight qualities should pursue reconciliation. What eight? They don’t try to prevent the laypeople from getting material things. They don’t try to harm laypeople. They don’t insult and abuse laypeople. They don’t divide laypeople against each other. They don’t criticize the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha. They keep a legitimate promise made to a layperson. The Saṅgha may, if it wishes, revoke the act requiring that a mendicant who has eight qualities should pursue reconciliation.”

AN 8.90 Proper Behavior in a Case of Aggravated Misconduct Sammāvattanasutta

“Mendicants, a mendicant who has been convicted of aggravated misconduct must behave themselves properly in eight respects. They must not perform an ordination, give dependence, or be attended by a novice. They must not consent to being appointed as adviser for nuns, and if they are appointed they should not give such advice. They must not consent to any Saṅgha appointment. They must not be put in a position of seniority. They must not resolve others from any offense similar to that which they have transgressed. A mendicant who has been convicted of aggravated misconduct must behave themselves properly in these eight respects.”

The Chapter on Sabbath

AN 8.41 The Sabbath With Eight Factors, In Brief Saṅkhittūposathasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, the observance of the sabbath with its eight factors is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful. And how should it be observed? It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. They are scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I, too, for this day and night will give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. I’ll be scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its first factor.

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up stealing. They take only what’s given, and expect only what’s given. They keep themselves clean by not thieving. I, too, for this day and night will give up stealing. I’ll take only what’s given, and expect only what’s given. I’ll keep myself clean by not thieving. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its second factor.

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up unchastity. They are chaste, set apart, refraining from the vulgar act of sex. I, too, for this day and night will give up unchastity. I will be chaste, set apart, refraining from the vulgar act of sex. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its third factor.

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up lying. They speak the truth and stick to the truth. They’re honest and dependable, and don’t trick the world with their words. I, too, for this day and night will give up lying. I’ll speak the truth and stick to the truth. I’ll be honest and dependable, and won’t trick the world with my words. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its fourth factor.

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. I, too, for this day and night will give up intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its fifth factor.

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones eat in one part of the day, abstaining from eating at night and from food at the wrong time. I, too, for this day and night will eat in one part of the day, abstaining from eating at night and food at the wrong time. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its sixth factor.

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up seeing shows of dancing, singing, and music; and attiring and adorning themselves with garlands, fragrance, and makeup. I, too, for this day and night will give up seeing shows of dancing, singing, and music; and attiring and adorning myself with garlands, fragrance, and makeup. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its seventh factor.

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up high and luxurious beds. They sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I, too, for this day and night will give up high and luxurious beds. I’ll sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its eighth factor.

The observance of the sabbath with its eight factors in this way is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful.”

AN 8.42 The Sabbath With Eight Factors, In Detail Vitthatūposathasutta

“Mendicants, the observance of the sabbath with its eight factors is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful. And how should it be observed?

It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. They are scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I, too, for this day and night will give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. I’ll be scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its first factor. …

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up high and luxurious beds. They sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I, too, for this day and night will give up high and luxurious beds. I’ll sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its eighth factor. The observance of the sabbath with its eight factors in this way is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful.

How much so? Suppose you were to rule as sovereign lord over these sixteen great countries—Aṅga, Magadha, Kāsi, Kosala, Vajji, Malla, Cetī, Vaccha, Kuru, Pañcāla, Maccha, Sūrasena, Assaka, Avanti, Gandhāra, and Kamboja—full of the seven treasures. This wouldn’t be worth a sixteenth part of the sabbath with its eight factors. Why is that? Because human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.

Fifty years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods of the four great kings. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The lifespan of the gods of the four great kings is five hundred of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods of the four great kings. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

A hundred years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods of the thirty-three. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The lifespan of the gods of the thirty-three is a thousand of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods of the thirty-three. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

Two hundred years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods of Yama. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The lifespan of the gods of Yama is two thousand of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods of Yama. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

Four hundred years in the human realm is one day and night for the joyful gods. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The lifespan of the joyful gods is four thousand of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the joyful gods. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

Eight hundred years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods who love to create. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The lifespan of the gods who love to create is eight thousand of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods who love to create. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

Sixteen hundred years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods who control what is created by others. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The lifespan of the gods who control what is created by others is sixteen thousand of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods who control what is created by others. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

You shouldn’t kill living creatures, or steal,
or lie, or drink liquor.
Be chaste, refraining from sex,
and don’t eat at night, the wrong time.

Not wearing garlands or applying fragrance,
you should sleep on a low bed, or a mat on the ground.
This is the eight-factored sabbath, they say,
revealed by the Buddha, who has gone to suffering’s end.

The moon and sun are both fair to see,
radiating as far as they revolve.
Those dispellers of darkness, travelers in midair,
shine in the firmament, dazzling the quarters.

All of the wealth that’s found in this realm—
pearls, gems, fine beryl too,
mountain gold or lustrous gold,
or the native gold called ‘coruscant’—

they’re not worth a sixteenth part
of the sabbath with its eight factors,
as starlight cannot rival the moon.

So an ethical woman or man,
who has observed the eight-factored sabbath,
having made merit whose outcome is happiness,
blameless, they go to a heavenly place.”

AN 8.43 With Visākhā on the Sabbath Visākhāsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother in the Eastern Monastery. Then Visākhā, Migāra’s mother, went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to her:

“Visākhā, the observance of the sabbath with its eight factors is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful. And how should it be observed? It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. They are scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I, too, for this day and night will give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. I’ll be scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its first factor. …

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up high and luxurious beds. They sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I, too, for this day and night will give up high and luxurious beds. I’ll sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its eighth factor. The observance of the sabbath with its eight factors in this way is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful.

How much so? Suppose you were to rule as sovereign lord over these sixteen great countries—Aṅga, Magadha, Kāsi, Kosala, Vajji, Malla, Cetī, Vaccha, Kuru, Pañcāla, Maccha, Sūrasena, Assaka, Avanti, Gandhāra, and Kamboja—full of the seven treasures. This wouldn’t be worth a sixteenth part of the sabbath with its eight factors. Why is that? Because human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.

Fifty years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods of the four great kings. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The lifespan of the gods of the four great kings is five hundred of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods of the four great kings. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

A hundred years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods of the thirty-three. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The life span of the gods of the thirty-three is a thousand of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods of the thirty-three. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

Two hundred years in the human realm …

Four hundred years in the human realm …

Eight hundred years in the human realm …

Sixteen hundred years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods who control what is created by others. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The lifespan of the gods who control what is created by others is sixteen thousand of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods who control what is created by others. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

You shouldn’t kill living creatures, or steal,
or lie, or drink liquor.
Be chaste, refraining from sex,
and don’t eat at night, the wrong time.

Not wearing garlands or applying fragrance,
you should sleep on a low bed, or a mat on the ground.
This is the eight-factored sabbath, they say,
revealed by the Buddha, who has gone to suffering’s end.

The moon and sun are both fair to see,
radiating as far as they revolve.
Those dispellers of darkness, travelers in midair,
shine in the firmament, dazzling the quarters.

All of the wealth that’s found in this realm—
pearls, gems, fine beryl too,
mountain gold or lustrous gold,
or the native gold called ‘coruscant’—

they’re not worth a sixteenth part
of the sabbath with its eight factors,
as starlight cannot rival the moon.

So an ethical woman or man,
who has observed the eight-factored sabbath,
having made merit whose outcome is happiness,
blameless, they go to a heavenly place.”

AN 8.44 With Vāseṭṭha on the Sabbath Vāseṭṭhasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof. Then the layman Vāseṭṭha went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Vāseṭṭha, the observance of the sabbath with its eight factors is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful … blameless, they go to a heavenly place.”

When he said this, Vāseṭṭha said to the Buddha:

“If my loved ones—relatives and kin—were to observe this sabbath with its eight factors, it would be for their lasting welfare and happiness. If all the aristocrats, brahmins, peasants, and menials were to observe this sabbath with its eight factors, it would be for their lasting welfare and happiness.”

“That’s so true, Vāseṭṭha! That’s so true, Vāseṭṭha! If all the aristocrats, brahmins, peasants, and menials were to observe this sabbath with its eight factors, it would be for their lasting welfare and happiness. If the whole world—with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, gods and humans—were to observe this sabbath with its eight factors, it would be for their lasting welfare and happiness. If these great sal trees were to observe this sabbath with its eight factors, it would be for their lasting welfare and happiness—if they were sentient. How much more then a human being!”

AN 8.45 With Bojjhā on the Sabbath Bojjhasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Then the laywoman Bojjhā went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to her:

“Bojjhā, the observance of the sabbath with its eight factors is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful. And how should it be observed?

It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. They are scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I, too, for this day and night will give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. I’ll be scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its first factor. …

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up high and luxurious beds. They sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I, too, for this day and night will give up high and luxurious beds. I’ll sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its eighth factor. The observance of the sabbath with its eight factors in this way is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful.

How much so? Suppose you were to rule as sovereign lord over these sixteen great countries—Aṅga, Magadha, Kāsi, Kosala, Vajji, Malla, Cetī, Vaccha, Kuru, Pañcāla, Maccha, Sūrasena, Assaka, Avanti, Gandhāra, and Kamboja—full of the seven treasures. This wouldn’t be worth a sixteenth part of the sabbath with its eight factors. Why is that? Because human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.

Fifty years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods of the four great kings. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The lifespan of the gods of the four great kings is five hundred of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods of the four great kings. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

A hundred years in the human realm …

Two hundred years in the human realm …

Four hundred years in the human realm …

Eight hundred years in the human realm …

Sixteen hundred years in the human realm is one day and night for the gods who control what is created by others. Thirty such days make up a month. Twelve such months make up a year. The life span of the gods who control what is created by others is sixteen thousand of these heavenly years. It’s possible that some woman or man who has observed the eight-factored sabbath will—when their body breaks up, after death—be reborn in the company of the gods who control what is created by others. This is what I was referring to when I said: ‘Human kingship is a poor thing compared to the happiness of the gods.’

You shouldn’t kill living creatures, or steal,
or lie, or drink liquor.
Be chaste, refraining from sex,
and don’t eat at night, the wrong time.

Not wearing garlands or applying fragrance,
you should sleep on a low bed, or a mat on the ground.
This is the eight-factored sabbath, they say,
revealed by the Buddha, who has gone to suffering’s end.

The moon and sun are both fair to see,
radiating as far as they revolve.
Those dispellers of darkness, travelers in midair,
shine in the firmament, dazzling the quarters.

All of the wealth that’s found in this realm—
pearls, gems, fine beryl too,
mountain gold or lustrous gold,
or the native gold called ‘coruscant’—

they’re not worth a sixteenth part
of the mind developed with love,
as starlight cannot rival the moon.

So an ethical woman or man,
who has observed the eight-factored sabbath,
having made merit whose outcome is happiness,
blameless, they go to a heavenly place.”

AN 8.46 Anuruddha and the Agreeable Deities Anuruddhasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery.

Now at that time Venerable Anuruddha had gone into retreat for the day’s meditation. Then several deities of the Agreeable Host went up to Venerable Anuruddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him:

“Honorable Anuruddha, we are the deities called ‘Agreeable’. We wield authority and control over three things. We can turn any color we want on the spot. We can get any voice that we want on the spot. We can get any pleasure that we want on the spot. We are the deities called ‘Agreeable’. We wield authority and control over these three things.”

Then Venerable Anuruddha thought, “If only these deities would all turn blue, of blue color, clad in blue, adorned with blue!” Then those deities, knowing Anuruddha’s thought, all turned blue.

Then Venerable Anuruddha thought, “If only these deities would all turn yellow …”

“If only these gods would all turn red …”

“If only these gods would all turn white …” Then those deities, knowing Anuruddha’s thought, all turned white.

Then one of those deities sang, one danced, and one snapped her fingers. Suppose there was a quintet made up of skilled musicians who had practiced well and kept excellent rhythm. They’d sound graceful, tantalizing, sensuous, endearing, and intoxicating. In the same way the performance by those deities sounded graceful, tantalizing, sensuous, endearing, and intoxicating. But Venerable Anuruddha averted his senses.

Then those deities, thinking “Master Anuruddha isn’t enjoying this,” vanished right there. Then in the late afternoon, Anuruddha came out of retreat and went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened, adding:

“How many qualities do ladies have so that—when their body breaks up, after death—they are reborn in company with the Gods of the Agreeable Host?”

“Anuruddha, when they have eight qualities ladies—when their body breaks up, after death—are reborn in company with the Gods of the Agreeable Host. What eight?

Take the case of a lady whose mother and father give her to a husband wanting what’s best for her, out of kindness and sympathy. She would get up before him and go to bed after him, and be obliging, behaving nicely and speaking politely.

She honors, respects, esteems, and venerates those her husband respects, such as mother and father, and ascetics and brahmins. And when they arrive she serves them with a seat and water.

She’s deft and tireless in her husband’s household duties, such as knitting and sewing. She understands how to go about things in order to complete and organize the work.

She knows what work her husband’s domestic bondservants, servants, and workers have completed, and what they’ve left incomplete. She knows who is sick, and who is fit or unwell. She distributes to each a fair portion of fresh and cooked foods.

She ensures that any income her husband earns is guarded and protected, whether money, grain, silver, or gold. She doesn’t overspend, steal, waste, or lose it.

She’s a lay follower who has gone for refuge to the Buddha, his teaching, and the Saṅgha.

She’s ethical. She doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor.

She’s generous. She lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share.

When they possess these eight qualities ladies—when their body breaks up, after death—are reborn in company with the Gods of the Agreeable Host.

She’d never look down on her husband,
who’s always eager to work hard,
always looking after her,
and bringing whatever she wants.

And a good woman never scolds her husband
with jealous words.
Being astute, she reveres
those respected by her husband.

She gets up early, works tirelessly,
and manages the domestic help.
She’s agreeable to her husband,
and preserves his wealth.

A lady who fulfills these duties
according to her husband’s desire,
is reborn among the gods
called ‘Agreeable’.”

AN 8.47 With Visākhā on the Agreeable Gods Dutiyavisākhāsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother in the Eastern Monastery. Then Visākhā, Migāra’s mother, went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to her:

“Visākhā, when they have eight qualities ladies—when their body breaks up, after death—are reborn in company with the Gods of the Agreeable Host. What eight? Take the case of a lady whose mother and father give her to a husband wanting what’s best for her, out of kindness and sympathy. She would get up before him and go to bed after him, and be obliging, behaving nicely and speaking politely. …

She’s generous. She lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. When they possess these eight qualities ladies—when their body breaks up, after death—are reborn in company with the Gods of the Agreeable Host.

She’d never look down on her husband,
who’s always eager to work hard,
always looking after her,
and bringing whatever she wants.

And a good woman never scolds her husband
with jealous words.
Being astute, she reveres
those respected by her husband.

She gets up early, works tirelessly,
and manages the domestic help.
She’s agreeable to her husband,
and preserves his wealth.

A lady who fulfills these duties
according to her husband’s desire,
is reborn among the gods
called ‘Agreeable’.”

AN 8.48 With Nakula’s Mother on the Agreeable Gods Nakulamātāsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Bhaggas at Crocodile’s Bellow, in the deer park at Bhesakaḷā’s Wood. Then the housewife Nakula’s mother went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to her:

“Nakula’s mother, when they have eight qualities ladies—when their body breaks up, after death—are reborn in company with the Gods of the Agreeable Host. What eight?

Take the case of a lady whose mother and father give her to a husband wanting what’s best for her, out of kindness and sympathy. She would get up before him and go to bed after him, and be obliging, behaving nicely and speaking politely.

She honors, respects, esteems, and venerates those her husband respects, such as mother and father, and ascetics and brahmins. And when they arrive she serves them with a seat and water.

She’s deft and tireless in her husband’s household duties, such as knitting and sewing. She understands how to go about things in order to complete and organize the work.

She knows what work her husband’s domestic bondservants, servants, and workers have completed, and what they’ve left incomplete. She knows who is sick, and who is fit or unwell. She distributes to each a fair portion of fresh and cooked foods.

She ensures that any income her husband earns is guarded and protected, whether money, grain, silver, or gold. She doesn’t overspend, steal, waste, or lose it.

She’s a lay follower who has gone for refuge to the Buddha, his teaching, and the Saṅgha.

She’s ethical. She doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor.

She’s generous. She lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share.

When they possess these eight qualities ladies—when their body breaks up, after death—are reborn in company with the Gods of the Agreeable Host.

She’d never look down on her husband,
who’s always eager to work hard,
always looking after her,
and bringing whatever she wants.

And a good woman never scolds her husband
with jealous words.
Being astute, she reveres
those respected by her husband.

She gets up early, works tirelessly,
and manages the domestic help.
She’s agreeable to her husband,
and preserves his wealth.

A lady who fulfills these duties
according to her husband’s desire,
is reborn among the gods
called ‘Agreeable’.”

AN 8.49 Winning in This Life (1st) Paṭhamaidhalokikasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in the stilt longhouse of Migāra’s mother in the Eastern Monastery. Then Visākhā, Migāra’s mother, went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to her:

“Visākhā, a lady who has four qualities is practicing to win in this life, and she succeeds at it. What four? It’s when a lady is well-organized at work, manages the domestic help, acts lovingly toward her husband, and preserves his earnings.

And how is a lady well-organized at work? It’s when she’s deft and tireless in doing domestic duties for her husband, such as knitting and sewing. She understands how to go about things in order to complete and organize the work. That’s how a lady is well-organized at work.

And how does a lady manage the domestic help? It’s when she knows what work her husband’s domestic bondservants, servants, and workers have completed, and what they’ve left incomplete. She knows who is sick, and who is fit or unwell. She distributes to each a fair portion of fresh and cooked foods. That’s how a lady manages the domestic help.

And how does a lady act lovingly toward her husband? It’s when a lady would not transgress in any way that her husband would not consider agreeable, even for the sake of her own life. That’s how a lady acts lovingly toward her husband.

And how does a lady preserve his earnings? It’s when she ensures that any income her husband earns is guarded and protected, whether money, grain, silver, or gold. She doesn’t overspend, steal, waste, or lose it. That’s how a lady preserves his earnings.

A lady who possesses these four qualities is practicing to win in this life, and she succeeds at it.

A lady who has four qualities is practicing to win in the next life, and she succeeds at it. What four? It’s when a lady is accomplished in faith, ethics, generosity, and wisdom.

And how is a lady accomplished in faith? It’s when a lady has faith in the Realized One’s awakening: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’ That’s how a lady is accomplished in faith.

And how is a lady accomplished in ethics? It’s when a lady doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. That’s how a lady is accomplished in ethics.

And how is a lady accomplished in generosity? It’s when she lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. That’s how a lady is accomplished in generosity.

And how is a lady accomplished in wisdom? It’s when a lady is wise. She has the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. That’s how a lady is accomplished in wisdom.

A lady who possesses these four qualities is practicing to win in the next life, and she succeeds at it.

She’s organized at work,
and manages the domestic help.
She’s agreeable to her husband,
and preserves his wealth.

Faithful, accomplished in ethics,
bountiful, rid of stinginess,
she always purifies the path
to well-being in lives to come.

And so, a lady in whom
these eight qualities are found
is known as virtuous,
firmly principled, and truthful.

Accomplished in sixteen respects,
complete with the eight factors,
a virtuous laywoman such as she
is reborn in the realm of the Agreeable Gods.”

AN 8.50 Winning in This Life (2nd) Dutiyaidhalokikasutta

“Mendicants, a lady who has four qualities is practicing to win in this life, and she succeeds at it. What four?

It’s when a lady is well-organized at work, manages the domestic help, acts lovingly toward her husband, and preserves his earnings.

And how is a lady well-organized at work? It’s when she’s skilled and tireless in doing domestic duties for her husband … That’s how a lady is well-organized at work.

And how does a lady manage the domestic help? It’s when she knows what work her husband’s domestic bondservants, servants, and workers have completed, and what they’ve left incomplete. She knows who is sick, and who is fit or unwell. She distributes to each a fair portion of fresh and cooked foods. That’s how a lady manages the domestic help.

And how does a lady act lovingly toward her husband? It’s when a lady would not transgress in any way that her husband would not consider agreeable, even for the sake of her own life. That’s how a lady acts lovingly toward her husband.

And how does a lady preserve his earnings? It’s when she tries to guard and protect any income her husband earns … That’s how a lady preserves his earnings.

A lady who possesses these four qualities is practicing to win in this life, and she succeeds at it.

A lady who has four qualities is practicing to win in the next life, and she succeeds at it. What four? It’s when a lady is accomplished in faith, ethics, generosity, and wisdom.

And how is a lady accomplished in faith? It’s when a lady has faith in the Realized One’s awakening … That’s how a lady is accomplished in faith.

And how is a lady accomplished in ethics? It’s when a lady doesn’t kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. That’s how a lady is accomplished in ethics.

And how is a lady accomplished in generosity? It’s when she lives at home with heart rid of the stain of stinginess, freely generous, open-handed, loving to let go, committed to charity, loving to give and to share. That’s how a lady is accomplished in generosity.

And how is a lady accomplished in wisdom? It’s when a lady is wise. She has the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. That’s how a lady is accomplished in wisdom.

A lady who possesses these four qualities is practicing to win in the next life, and she succeeds at it.

She’s organized at work,
and manages the domestic help.
She’s agreeable to her husband,
and preserves his wealth.

Faithful, accomplished in ethics,
being bountiful and rid of stinginess.
She always purifies the path
to well-being in lives to come.

And so, a lady in whom
these eight qualities are found
is known as virtuous,
firmly principled, and truthful.

Accomplished in sixteen respects,
complete with the eight factors,
a virtuous laywoman such as she
is reborn in the realm of the Agreeable Gods.”

The Second Fifty

The Chapter on a Safe Place

AN 9.52 A Safe Place Khemasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘a safe place’. In what way did the Buddha speak of a safe place?”

“First, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. To this extent the Buddha spoke of a safe place in a qualified sense. …

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. To this extent the Buddha spoke of a safe place in a definitive sense.”

AN 9.53 Reaching a Safe Place Khemappattasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘reaching a safe place’. …”

AN 9.54 Freedom From Death Amatasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘freedom from death’. …”

AN 9.55 Reaching Freedom From Death Amatappattasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘reaching freedom from death’. …”

AN 9.56 A Place Without Fear Abhayasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘a place without fear’. …”

AN 9.57 Reaching a Place Without Fear Abhayappattasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘reaching a place without fear’. …”

AN 9.58 Tranquility Passaddhisutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘tranquility’. …”

AN 9.59 Progressive Tranquility Anupubbapassaddhisutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘progressive tranquility’. …”

AN 9.60 Cessation Nirodhasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘cessation’. …”

AN 9.61 Progressive Cessation Anupubbanirodhasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘progressive cessation’. What is the progressive cessation that the Buddha spoke of?”

“First, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. To this extent the Buddha spoke of progressive cessation in a qualified sense. …

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. To this extent the Buddha spoke of progressive cessation in a definitive sense.”

AN 9.62 Impossible Abhabbasutta

“Mendicants, without giving up nine things you can’t realize perfection. What nine? Greed, hate, delusion, anger, acrimony, disdain, contempt, jealousy, and stinginess. Without giving up these nine things you can’t realize perfection.

After giving up nine things you can realize perfection. What nine? Greed, hate, delusion, anger, acrimony, disdain, contempt, jealousy, and stinginess. After giving up these nine things you can realize the fruit of perfection.”

The Chapter on Bases of Psychic Power

AN 9.83 Weaknesses in Training and the Bases of Psychic Power Sikkhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five weaknesses when you’re training. What five? Killing living creatures, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, and intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. These are the five weaknesses when you’re training.

To give up these five weaknesses in your training you should develop the four bases of psychic power. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort. They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy, and active effort. They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to mental development, and active effort. They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to inquiry, and active effort. To give up these five weaknesses in your training you should develop these four bases of psychic power.”

AN 9.84–91 Hindrances, Etc. Nīvaraṇasuttādi

(Tell in full as in the chapter on mindfulness meditation.)

AN 9.92 Shackles of the Heart Cetasovinibandhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five shackles of the heart. What five? Firstly, a mendicant isn’t free of greed for sensual pleasures. … These are the five shackles of the heart.

To give up these five shackles of the heart you should develop the four bases of psychic power. What four? It’s when a mendicant develops the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to enthusiasm, and active effort. They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to energy, and active effort. They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to mental development, and active effort. They develop the basis of psychic power that has immersion due to inquiry, and active effort. To give up these five shackles of the heart you should develop these four bases of psychic power.”

The Great Chapter

AN 9.32 Progressive Meditations Anupubbavihārasutta

“Mendicants, there are these nine progressive meditations. What nine? The first absorption, the second absorption, the third absorption, the fourth absorption, the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness, the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, and the cessation of perception and feeling. These are the nine progressive meditations.”

AN 9.33 The Nine Progressive Meditative Attainments Anupubbavihārasamāpattisutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you the nine progressive meditative attainments … And what are the nine progressive meditative attainments?

Where sensual pleasures cease, and those who have thoroughly ended sensual pleasures meditate, I say: ‘Clearly those venerables are desireless, quenched, crossed over, and gone beyond in that respect.’ If someone should say, ‘I do not know or see where sensual pleasures cease’, they should be told: ‘Reverend, it’s when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. That’s where sensual pleasures cease.’ Clearly someone who is not devious or deceitful would approve and agree with that statement. They’d say ‘Good!’ and bowing down, they’d pay homage with cupped palms.

Where the placing of the mind and keeping it connected cease, and those who have thoroughly ended the placing of the mind and keeping it connected meditate, I say: ‘Clearly those venerables are desireless, quenched, crossed over, and gone beyond in that respect.’ If someone should say, ‘I do not know or see where the placing of the mind and keeping it connected cease’, they should be told: ‘It’s when a mendicant, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, enters and remains in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected. That’s where the placing of the mind and keeping it connected cease.’ Clearly someone who is not devious or deceitful would approve and agree with that statement. They’d say ‘Good!’ and bowing down, they’d pay homage with cupped palms.

Where rapture ceases, and those who have thoroughly ended rapture meditate, I say: ‘Clearly those venerables are desireless, quenched, crossed over, and gone beyond in that respect.’ If someone should say, ‘I do not know or see where rapture ceases’, they should be told: ‘It’s when a mendicant, with the fading away of rapture, enters and remains in the third absorption, where they meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, “Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss”. That’s where rapture ceases.’ Clearly someone who is not devious or deceitful would approve and agree with that statement. They’d say ‘Good!’ and bowing down, they’d pay homage with cupped palms.

Where bliss with equanimity ceases, and those who have thoroughly ended bliss with equanimity meditate, I say: ‘Clearly those venerables are desireless, quenched, crossed over, and gone beyond in that respect.’ If someone should say, ‘I do not know or see where bliss with equanimity ceases’, they should be told: ‘It’s when a mendicant, with the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, enters and remains in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness. That’s where bliss with equanimity ceases.’ Clearly someone who is not devious or deceitful would approve and agree with that statement. They’d say ‘Good!’ and bowing down, they’d pay homage with cupped palms.

Where perceptions of form ceases, and those who have thoroughly ended perceptions of form meditate, I say: ‘Clearly those venerables are desireless, quenched, crossed over, and gone beyond in that respect.’ If someone should say, ‘I do not know or see where perceptions of form ceases’, they should be told: ‘It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that “space is infinite”, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. That’s where perceptions of form cease.’ Clearly someone who is not devious or deceitful would approve and agree with that statement. They’d say ‘Good!’ and bowing down, they’d pay homage with cupped palms.

Where the perception of the dimension of infinite space ceases, and those who have thoroughly ended the perception of the dimension of infinite space meditate, I say: ‘Clearly those venerables are desireless, quenched, crossed over, and gone beyond in that respect.’ If someone should say, ‘I do not know or see where the perception of the dimension of infinite space ceases’, they should be told: ‘It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that “consciousness is infinite”, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness. That’s where the perception of the dimension of infinite space ceases.’ Clearly someone who is not devious or deceitful would approve and agree with that statement. They’d say ‘Good!’ and bowing down, they’d pay homage with cupped palms.

Where the perception of the dimension of infinite consciousness ceases, and those who have thoroughly ended the perception of the dimension of infinite consciousness meditate, I say: ‘Clearly those venerables are desireless, quenched, crossed over, and gone beyond in that respect.’ If someone should say, ‘I do not know or see where the perception of the dimension of infinite consciousness ceases’, they should be told: ‘It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that “there is nothing at all”, enters and remains in the dimension of nothingness. That’s where the perception of the dimension of infinite consciousness ceases.’ Clearly someone who is not devious or deceitful would approve and agree with that statement. They’d say ‘Good!’ and bowing down, they’d pay homage with cupped palms.

Where the perception of the dimension of nothingness ceases, and those who have thoroughly ended the perception of the dimension of nothingness meditate, I say: ‘Clearly those venerables are desireless, quenched, crossed over, and gone beyond in that respect.’ If someone should say, ‘I do not know or see where the perception of the dimension of nothingness ceases’, they should be told: ‘It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, enters and remains in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. That’s where the perception of the dimension of nothingness ceases.’ Clearly someone who is not devious or deceitful would approve and agree with that statement. They’d say ‘Good!’ and bowing down, they’d pay homage with cupped palms.

Where the perception of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception ceases, and those who have thoroughly ended the perception of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception meditate, I say: ‘Clearly those venerables are desireless, quenched, crossed over, and gone beyond in that respect.’ If someone should say, ‘I do not know or see where the perception of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception ceases’, they should be told: ‘It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. That’s where the perception of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception ceases.’ Clearly someone who is not devious or deceitful would approve and agree with that statement. They’d say ‘Good!’ and bowing down, they’d pay homage with cupped palms.

These are the nine progressive meditative attainments.”

AN 9.34 Extinguishment is Bliss Nibbānasukhasutta

At one time Venerable Sāriputta was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground.

There he addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, extinguishment is bliss! Extinguishment is bliss!”

When he said this, Venerable Udāyī said to him, “But Reverend Sāriputta, what’s blissful about it, since nothing is felt?”

“The fact that nothing is felt is precisely what’s blissful about it.

Reverend, there are these five kinds of sensual stimulation. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds known by the ear … Smells known by the nose … Tastes known by the tongue … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These are the five kinds of sensual stimulation. The pleasure and happiness that arise from these five kinds of sensual stimulation is called sensual pleasure.

First, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. While a mendicant is practicing such a meditation, if perception and focus accompanied by sensual pleasures beset them, that’s an affliction for them. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, should perception and focus accompanied by sensual pleasures beset them, that’s an affliction for them. And affliction has been called suffering by the Buddha. That’s the way to understand how extinguishment is bliss.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, enters and remains in the second absorption. While a mendicant is practicing such a meditation, if perception and focus accompanied by placing of the mind beset them, that’s an affliction for them. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, should perception and focus accompanied by placing of the mind beset them, that’s an affliction for them. And affliction has been called suffering by the Buddha. That too is a way to understand how extinguishment is bliss.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, with the fading away of rapture, enters and remains in the third absorption. While a mendicant is practicing such a meditation, if perception and focus accompanied by rapture beset them, that’s an affliction for them. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, should perception and focus accompanied by rapture beset them, that’s an affliction for them. And affliction has been called suffering by the Buddha. That too is a way to understand how extinguishment is bliss.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, with the giving up of pleasure and pain and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, enters and remains in the fourth absorption. While a mendicant is practicing such a meditation, if perception and focus accompanied by bliss with equanimity beset them, that’s an affliction for them. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, should perception and focus accompanied by bliss with equanimity beset them, that’s an affliction for them. And affliction has been called suffering by the Buddha. That too is a way to understand how extinguishment is bliss.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. While a mendicant is practicing such a meditation, if perception and focus accompanied by form beset them, that’s an affliction for them. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, should perception and focus accompanied by form beset them, that’s an affliction for them. And affliction has been called suffering by the Buddha. That too is a way to understand how extinguishment is bliss.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness. While a mendicant is practicing such a meditation, if perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite space beset them, that’s an affliction for them. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, should perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite space beset them, that’s an affliction for them. And affliction has been called suffering by the Buddha. That too is a way to understand how extinguishment is bliss.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, enters and remains in the dimension of nothingness. While a mendicant is practicing such a meditation, if perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite consciousness beset them, that’s an affliction for them. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, should perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite consciousness beset them, that’s an affliction for them. And affliction has been called suffering by the Buddha. That too is a way to understand how extinguishment is bliss.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, enters and remains in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. While a mendicant is practicing such a meditation, if perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of nothingness beset them, that’s an affliction for them. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, should perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of nothingness beset them, that’s an affliction for them. And affliction has been called suffering by the Buddha. That too is a way to understand how extinguishment is bliss.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end.

That too is a way to understand how extinguishment is bliss.”

AN 9.35 The Simile of the Cow Gāvīupamāsutta

“Mendicants, suppose there was a mountain cow who was foolish, incompetent, unskillful, and lacked common sense when roaming on rugged mountains. She might think, ‘Why don’t I go somewhere I’ve never been before? I could eat grass and drink water that I’ve never tried before.’ She’d take a step with a fore-hoof; but before it was properly set down, she’d lift up a hind-hoof. She wouldn’t go somewhere she’d never been before, or eat grass and drink water that she’d never tried before. And she’d never return safely to the place she had started from. Why is that? Because that mountain cow was foolish, incompetent, unskillful, and lacked common sense when roaming on rugged mountains.

In the same way, some foolish, incompetent, unskillful mendicant, lacking common sense, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. But they don’t cultivate, develop, and make much of that basis; they don’t ensure it is properly stabilized.

They think, ‘Why don’t I, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected.’ But they’re not able to enter and remain in the second absorption. They think, ‘Why don’t I, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enter and remain in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected.’ But they’re not able to enter and remain in the first absorption. This is called a mendicant who has slipped and fallen from both sides. They’re like the mountain cow who was foolish, incompetent, unskillful, and lacking in common sense when roaming on rugged mountains.

Suppose there was a mountain cow who was astute, competent, skillful, and used common sense when roaming on rugged mountains. She might think, ‘Why don’t I go somewhere I’ve never been before? I could eat grass and drink water that I’ve never tried before.’ She’d take a step with a fore-hoof; and after it was properly set down, she’d lift up a hind-hoof. She’d go somewhere she’d never been before, and eat grass and drink water that she’d never tried before. And she’d return safely to the place she had started from. Why is that? Because that mountain cow was astute, competent, skillful, and used common sense when roaming on rugged mountains. In the same way, some astute, competent, skillful mendicant, using common sense, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. They cultivate, develop, and make much of that basis, ensuring that it’s properly stabilized.

They think, ‘Why don’t I, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, enter and remain in the second absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of immersion, with internal clarity and mind at one, without placing the mind and keeping it connected.’ Without charging at the second absorption, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, they enter and remain in the second absorption. They cultivate, develop, and make much of that basis, ensuring that it’s properly stabilized.

They think, ‘Why don’t I, with the fading away of rapture, enter and remain in the third absorption, where I will meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, “Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss.”’ Without charging at the third absorption, with the fading away of rapture, they enter and remain in the third absorption. They cultivate, develop, and make much of that basis, ensuring that it’s properly stabilized.

They think, ‘Why don’t I, with the giving up of pleasure and pain, and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness.’ Without charging at the fourth absorption, with the giving up of pleasure and pain, and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, they enter and remain in the fourth absorption. They cultivate, develop, and make much of that basis, ensuring that it’s properly stabilized.

They think, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that “space is infinite”, enter and remain in the dimension of infinite space.’ Without charging at the dimension of infinite space, with the fading away of rapture, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite space. They cultivate, develop, and make much of that basis, ensuring that it’s properly stabilized.

They think, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that “consciousness is infinite”, enter and remain in the dimension of infinite consciousness.’ Without charging at the dimension of infinite consciousness, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite consciousness. They cultivate, develop, and make much of that basis, ensuring that it’s properly stabilized.

They think, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that “there is nothing at all”, enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness.’ Without charging at the dimension of nothingness, they enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness. They cultivate, develop, and make much of that basis, ensuring that it’s properly stabilized.

They think, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, enter and remain in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception.’ Without charging at the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, they enter and remain in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. They cultivate, develop, and make much of that basis, ensuring that it’s properly stabilized.

They think, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enter and remain in the cessation of perception and feeling.’ Without charging at the cessation of perception and feeling, they enter and remain in the cessation of perception and feeling.

When a mendicant enters and emerges from any one of these attainments, their mind becomes pliable and workable. With a pliable and workable mind, their immersion becomes limitless and well developed. They extend the mind to realize by insight each and every thing that can be realized by insight; and they are capable of realizing those things, since each and every one is within range.

They might wish: ‘May I wield the many kinds of psychic power: multiplying myself and becoming one again … controlling the body as far as the realm of divinity.’ They are capable of realizing it, since each and every one is within range.

They might wish: ‘With clairaudience that is purified and superhuman, may I hear both kinds of sounds, human and heavenly, whether near or far.’ They are capable of realizing it, since each and every one is within range.

They might wish: ‘May I understand the minds of other beings and individuals, having encompassed them with my mind. May I understand mind with greed as “mind with greed”, and mind without greed as “mind without greed”; mind with hate as “mind with hate”, and mind without hate as “mind without hate”; mind with delusion as “mind with delusion”, and mind without delusion as “mind without delusion”; constricted mind … scattered mind … expansive mind … unexpansive mind … mind that is not supreme … mind that is supreme … mind immersed in samādhi … mind not immersed in samādhi … freed mind … and unfreed mind as “unfreed mind”.’ They are capable of realizing it, since each and every one is within range.

They might wish: ‘May I recollect many kinds of past lives. That is: one, two, three, four, five, ten, twenty, thirty, forty, fifty, a hundred, a thousand, a hundred thousand rebirths; many eons of the world contracting, many eons of the world expanding, many eons of the world contracting and expanding. They remember: “There, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn somewhere else. There, too, I was named this, my clan was that, I looked like this, and that was my food. This was how I felt pleasure and pain, and that was how my life ended. When I passed away from that place I was reborn here.” May I recollect my many past lives, with features and details.’ They’re capable of realizing it, since each and every one is within range.

They might wish: ‘With clairvoyance that is purified and superhuman, may I see sentient beings passing away and being reborn—inferior and superior, beautiful and ugly, in a good place or a bad place—and understand how sentient beings pass on according to their deeds.’ They’re capable of realizing it, since each and every one is within range.

They might wish: ‘May I realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with my own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.’ They’re capable of realizing it, since each and every one is within range.”

AN 9.36 Depending on Absorption Jhānasutta

“Mendicants, I say that the first absorption is a basis for ending the defilements. The second absorption is also a basis for ending the defilements. The third absorption is also a basis for ending the defilements. The fourth absorption is also a basis for ending the defilements. The dimension of infinite space is also a basis for ending the defilements. The dimension of infinite consciousness is also a basis for ending the defilements. The dimension of nothingness is also a basis for ending the defilements. The dimension of neither perception nor non-perception is also a basis for ending the defilements. The cessation of perception and feeling is also a basis for ending the defilements.

‘The first absorption is a basis for ending the defilements.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption. They contemplate the phenomena there—included in form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness—as impermanent, as suffering, as diseased, as a boil, as a dart, as gloom, as an affliction, as alien, as breaking apart, as empty, as not-self. They turn their mind away from those things, and apply it to freedom from death: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world.

It’s like an archer or their apprentice who first practices on a straw man or a clay model. At a later time they become a long-distance shooter, a marksman, who shatters large objects. In the same way a noble disciple, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, enters and remains in the first absorption. They contemplate the phenomena there—included in form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness—as impermanent, as suffering, as diseased, as a boil, as a dart, as gloom, as an affliction, as alien, as breaking apart, as empty, as not-self. They turn their mind away from those things, and apply it to freedom from death: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. ‘The first absorption is a basis for ending the defilements.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘The second absorption is also a basis for ending the defilements.’ …

‘The third absorption is also a basis for ending the defilements.’ …

‘The fourth absorption is also a basis for ending the defilements.’ …

‘The dimension of infinite space is also a basis for ending the defilements.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Take a mendicant who, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. They contemplate the phenomena there—included in feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness—as impermanent, as suffering, as diseased, as a boil, as a dart, as gloom, as an affliction, as alien, as breaking apart, as empty, as not-self. They turn their mind away from those things, and apply it to freedom from death: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world.

It’s like an archer or their apprentice who first practices on a straw man or a clay model. At a later time they become a long-distance shooter, a marksman, who shatters large objects. In the same way, take a mendicant who enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. … ‘The dimension of infinite space is a basis for ending the defilements.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘The dimension of infinite consciousness is a basis for ending the defilements.’ …

‘The dimension of nothingness is a basis for ending the defilements.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, enters and remains in the dimension of nothingness. They contemplate the phenomena there—included in feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness—as impermanent, as suffering, as diseased, as a boil, as a dart, as gloom, as an affliction, as alien, as breaking apart, as empty, as not-self. They turn their mind away from those things, and apply it to freedom from death: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world.

It’s like an archer or their apprentice who first practices on a straw man or a clay model. At a later time they become a long-distance shooter, a marksman, who shatters large objects. In the same way, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, enters and remains in the dimension of nothingness. They contemplate the phenomena there—included in feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness—as impermanent, as suffering, as diseased, as a boil, as a dart, as gloom, as an affliction, as alien, as breaking apart, as empty, as not-self. They turn their mind away from those things, and apply it to freedom from death: ‘This is peaceful; this is sublime—that is, the stilling of all activities, the letting go of all attachments, the ending of craving, fading away, cessation, extinguishment.’ Abiding in that they attain the ending of defilements. If they don’t attain the ending of defilements, with the ending of the five lower fetters they’re reborn spontaneously, because of their passion and love for that meditation. They are extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. ‘The dimension of nothingness is a basis for ending the defilements.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

And so, mendicants, penetration to enlightenment extends as far as attainments with perception. But the two dimensions that depend on these—the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, and the cessation of perception and feeling—are properly explained by meditators who are skilled in these attainments and skilled in emerging from them, after they’ve entered them and emerged from them.”

AN 9.37 By Ānanda Ānandasutta

At one time Venerable Ānanda was staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery. There Ānanda addressed the mendicants: “Reverends, mendicants!”

“Reverend,” they replied. Ānanda said this:

“It’s incredible, reverends, it’s amazing! How this Blessed One who knows and sees, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha, has found an opening amid confinement. It’s in order to purify sentient beings, to get past sorrow and crying, to make an end of pain and sadness, to discover the system, and to realize extinguishment.

The eye itself is actually present, and so are those sights. Yet one will not experience that sense-field. The ear itself is actually present, and so are those sounds. Yet one will not experience that sense-field. The nose itself is actually present, and so are those smells. Yet one will not experience that sense-field. The tongue itself is actually present, and so are those tastes. Yet one will not experience that sense-field. The body itself is actually present, and so are those touches. Yet one will not experience that sense-field.”

When he said this, Venerable Udāyī said to Venerable Ānanda:

“Reverend Ānanda, is one who doesn’t experience that sense-field actually percipient or not?”

“Reverend, one who doesn’t experience that sense-field is actually percipient, not non-percipient.”

“But what does one who doesn’t experience that sense-field perceive?”

“It’s when a mendicant, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. One who doesn’t experience that sense-field perceives in this way.

Furthermore, a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness. One who doesn’t experience that sense-field perceives in this way.

Furthermore, a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, enters and remains in the dimension of nothingness. One who doesn’t experience that sense-field perceives in this way.

Reverend, this one time I was staying near Sāketa in the deer park in Añjana Wood. Then the nun Jaṭilagāhikā came up to me, bowed, stood to one side, and said to me: ‘Honorable Ānanda, regarding the immersion that does not lean forward or pull back, and is not held in place by forceful suppression. Being free, it’s stable. Being stable, it’s content. Being content, one is not anxious. What did the Buddha say was the fruit of this immersion?’

When she said this, I said to her: ‘Sister, regarding the immersion that does not lean forward or pull back, and is not held in place by forceful suppression. Being free, it’s stable. Being stable, it’s content. Being content, one is not anxious. The Buddha said that the fruit of this immersion is enlightenment.’ One who doesn’t experience that sense-field perceives in this way, too.”

AN 9.38 Brahmin Cosmologists Lokāyatikasutta

Then two brahmin cosmologists went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, they sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Worthy Gotama, Pūraṇa Kassapa claims to be all-knowing and all-seeing, to know and see everything without exception, thus: ‘Knowledge and vision are constantly and continually present to me, while walking, standing, sleeping, and waking.’ He says: ‘With infinite knowledge I know and see that the cosmos is infinite.’ And the Jain ascetic of the Ñātika clan also claims to be all-knowing and all-seeing, to know and see everything without exception, thus: ‘Knowledge and vision are constantly and continually present to me, while walking, standing, sleeping, and waking.’ He says: ‘With infinite knowledge I know and see that the cosmos is finite.’ These two claim to speak from knowledge, but they directly contradict each other. Which one of them speaks the truth, and which falsehood?”

“Enough, brahmins, let that be. I will teach you the Dhamma. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, worthy sir,” those brahmins replied. The Buddha said this:

“Suppose there were four men standing in the four quarters. Each of them was extremely fast, with an extremely mighty stride. They’re as fast as a light arrow easily shot across the shadow of a palm tree by a well-trained expert archer with a strong bow. Their stride was such that it spanned from the eastern ocean to the western ocean. Then the man standing in the east would say: ‘I will reach the end of the world by traveling.’ Though he’d travel for his whole lifespan of a hundred years—pausing only to eat and drink, go to the toilet, and sleep to dispel weariness—he’d die along the way, never reaching the end of the world. Then the man standing in the west … Then the man standing in the north … Then the man standing in the south would say: ‘I will reach the end of the world by traveling.’ Though he’d travel for his whole lifespan of a hundred years—pausing only to eat and drink, go to the toilet, and sleep to dispel weariness—he’d die along the way, never reaching the end of the world. Why is that? I say it’s not possible to know or see or reach the end of the world by running like this. But I also say there’s no making an end of suffering without reaching the end of the world.

These five kinds of sensual stimulation are called the world in the training of the Noble One. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds known by the ear … Smells known by the nose … Tastes known by the tongue … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These five kinds of sensual stimulation are called the world in the training of the Noble One.

Take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. This is called a mendicant who, having gone to the end of the world, meditates at the end of the world. Others say of them: ‘They’re included in the world, and haven’t yet left the world.’ And I also say this: ‘They’re included in the world, and haven’t yet left the world.’

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, enters and remains in the second absorption … third absorption … fourth absorption. This is called a mendicant who, having gone to the end of the world, meditates at the end of the world. Others say of them: ‘They’re included in the world, and haven’t yet left the world.’ And I also say this: ‘They’re included in the world, and haven’t yet left the world.’

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. This is called a mendicant who, having gone to the end of the world, meditates at the end of the world. Others say of them: ‘They’re included in the world, and haven’t yet left the world.’ And I also say this: ‘They’re included in the world, and haven’t yet left the world.’

Furthermore, take a mendicant who enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness. … the dimension of nothingness … the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. This is called a mendicant who, having gone to the end of the world, meditates at the end of the world. Others say of them: ‘They’re included in the world, and haven’t yet left the world.’ And I also say this: ‘They’re included in the world, and haven’t yet left the world.’

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. This is called a mendicant who, having gone to the end of the world, meditates at the end of the world. And they’ve crossed over clinging to the world.”

AN 9.39 The War Between the Gods and the Titans Devāsurasaṅgāmasutta

“Once upon a time, mendicants, a battle was fought between the gods and the titans. In that battle the titans won and the gods lost. Defeated, the gods fled north with the titans in pursuit.

Then the gods thought, ‘The titans are still in pursuit. Why don’t we engage them in battle a second time?’ And so a second battle was fought between the gods and the titans. And for a second time the titans won and the gods lost. Defeated, the gods fled north with the titans in pursuit.

Then the gods thought, ‘The titans are still in pursuit. Why don’t we engage them in battle a third time?’ And so a third battle was fought between the gods and the titans. And for a third time the titans won and the gods lost. Defeated and terrified, the gods fled right into the castle of the gods.

When they had entered their castle, they thought, ‘Now we’re in a secure location and the titans can’t do anything to us.’ The titans also thought, ‘Now the gods are in a secure location and we can’t do anything to them.’

Once upon a time, a battle was fought between the gods and the titans. In that battle the gods won and the titans lost. Defeated, the titans fled south with the gods in pursuit.

Then the titans thought, ‘The gods are still in pursuit. Why don’t we engage them in battle a second time?’ And so a second battle was fought between the gods and the titans. And for a second time the gods won and the titans lost. Defeated, the titans fled south with the gods in pursuit.

Then the titans thought, ‘The gods are still in pursuit. Why don’t we engage them in battle a third time?’ And so a third battle was fought between the gods and the titans. And for a third time the gods won and the titans lost. Defeated and terrified, the titans fled right into the citadel of the titans.

When they had entered their citadel, they thought, ‘Now we’re in a secure location and the gods can’t do anything to us.’ And the gods also thought, ‘Now the titans are in a secure location and we can’t do anything to them.’

In the same way, there’s a time when a mendicant, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, enters and remains in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. At that time the mendicant thinks, ‘Now I’m in a secure location and Māra can’t do anything to me.’ And Māra the Wicked also thinks, ‘Now the mendicant is in a secure location and we can’t do anything to them.’

There’s a time when, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, a mendicant enters and remains in the second absorption … third absorption … fourth absorption. At that time the mendicant thinks, ‘Now I’m in a secure location and Māra can’t do anything to me.’ And Māra the Wicked also thinks, ‘Now the mendicant is in a secure location and we can’t do anything to them.’

There’s a time when a mendicant, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. This is called a mendicant who has blinded Māra, put out his eyes without a trace, and gone where the Wicked One cannot see.

There’s a time when a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness. … Going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, they enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness. … Going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, they enter and remain in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. …

Going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, they enter and remain in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. This is called a mendicant who has blinded Māra, put out his eyes without a trace, and gone where the Wicked One cannot see. And they’ve crossed over clinging to the world.”

AN 9.40 The Simile of the Bull Elephant in the Forest Nāgasutta

“Mendicants, when a wild bull elephant is engrossed in the pasture, but other elephants—males, females, younglings, or cubs—got there first and trampled the grass, the wild bull elephant is horrified, repelled, and disgusted by that. When the wild bull elephant is engrossed in the pasture, but other elephants—males, females, younglings, or cubs—eat the broken branches that he has dragged down, the wild bull elephant is horrified, repelled, and disgusted by that. When a wild bull elephant has plunged into the pool, but other elephants—males, females, younglings, or cubs—got there first and stirred up the water with their trunks, the wild bull elephant is horrified, repelled, and disgusted by that. When a wild bull elephant has come out of the pool and the female elephants bump into him, the wild bull elephant is horrified, repelled, and disgusted by that.

At that time the wild bull elephant thinks: ‘These days I live crowded by other males, females, younglings, and cubs. I eat the grass they’ve trampled, and they eat the broken branches I’ve dragged down. I drink muddy water, and after my bath the female elephants bump into me. Why don’t I live alone, withdrawn from the herd?’ After some time he lives alone, withdrawn from the herd, and he eats untrampled grass, and other elephants don’t eat the broken branches he has dragged down. He doesn’t drink muddy water, and the female elephants don’t bump into him after his bath.

At that time the wild bull elephant thinks: ‘Formerly I lived crowded by other males, females, younglings, and cubs. I ate the grass they’d trampled, and they ate the broken branches I’d dragged down. I drank muddy water, and after my bath the female elephants bumped into me. Now I live alone, and I’m free of all these things.’ He breaks off a branch and scratches his body, happily relieving his itches.

In the same way, when a mendicant lives crowded by monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen; by rulers and their chief ministers, and by monastics of other religions and their disciples, they think: ‘These days I live crowded by monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen; by rulers and their chief ministers, and monastics of other religions and their disciples. Why don’t I live alone, withdrawn from the group?’ They frequent a secluded lodging—a wilderness, the root of a tree, a hill, a ravine, a mountain cave, a charnel ground, a forest, the open air, a heap of straw. Gone to a wilderness, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty hut, they sit down cross-legged, set their body straight, and bring mindfulness to the present.

Giving up covetousness for the world, they meditate with a heart rid of covetousness, cleansing the mind of covetousness. Giving up ill will and malevolence, they meditate with a mind rid of ill will, full of sympathy for all living beings, cleansing the mind of ill will. Giving up dullness and drowsiness, they meditate with a mind rid of dullness and drowsiness, perceiving light, mindful and aware, cleansing the mind of dullness and drowsiness. Giving up restlessness and remorse, they meditate without restlessness, their mind settled internally, cleansing the mind of restlessness and remorse. Giving up doubt, they meditate having gone beyond doubt, not undecided about skillful qualities, cleansing the mind of doubt. They give up these five hindrances, corruptions of the heart that weaken wisdom. Then, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, they enter and remain in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. They happily relieve their itches. As the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, they enter and remain in the second absorption … third absorption … fourth absorption. They happily relieve their itches.

Going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite space. They happily relieve their itches. Going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, they enter and remain in the dimension of infinite consciousness. … Going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, they enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness. … Going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, they enter and remain in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. … Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. They happily relieve their itches.”

AN 9.41 With the Householder Tapussa Tapussasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying in the land of the Mallas, near the Mallian town named Uruvelakappa.

Then the Buddha robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Uruvelakappa for alms. Then, after the meal, on his return from almsround, he addressed Venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, you stay right here, while I plunge deep into the Great Wood for the day’s meditation.”

“Yes, sir,” Ānanda replied. Then the Buddha plunged deep into the Great Wood and sat at the root of a tree for the day’s meditation.

The householder Tapussa went up to Venerable Ānanda, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Honorable Ānanda, we are laypeople who enjoy sensual pleasures. We like sensual pleasures, we love them and take joy in them. But renunciation seems like an abyss. I have heard that in this teaching and training there are very young mendicants whose minds leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in renunciation. They see it as peaceful. Renunciation is the dividing line between the multitude and the mendicants in this teaching and training.”

“Householder, we should see the Buddha about this matter. Come, let’s go to the Buddha and inform him about this. As he answers, so we’ll remember it.”

“Yes, sir,” replied Tapussa. Then Ānanda together with Tapussa went to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. Ānanda told him what had happened.

“That’s so true, Ānanda! That’s so true! Before my awakening—when I was still unawakened but intent on awakening—I too thought, ‘Renunciation is good! Seclusion is good!’ But my mind did not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in renunciation. I didn’t see it as peaceful. Then I thought, ‘What is the cause, what is the reason why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in renunciation? Why don’t I see it as peaceful?’ Then I thought, ‘I haven’t seen the drawbacks of sensual pleasures, and so I haven’t cultivated that. I haven’t realized the benefits of renunciation, and so I haven’t developed that. That’s why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in renunciation. And it’s why I don’t see it as peaceful.’ Then I thought, ‘Suppose that, seeing the drawbacks of sensual pleasures, I were to cultivate that. And suppose that, realizing the benefits of renunciation, I were to develop that. It’s possible that my mind would leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in renunciation. And I would see it as peaceful.’ And so, after some time, I saw the drawbacks of sensual pleasures and cultivated that, and I realized the benefits of renunciation and developed that. Then my mind leapt forth, gained confidence, settled down, and became decided in renunciation. I saw it as peaceful. And so, quite secluded from sensual pleasures, secluded from unskillful qualities, I entered and remained in the first absorption, which has the rapture and bliss born of seclusion, while placing the mind and keeping it connected. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by sensual pleasures beset me, and that was an affliction for me. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, when perception and focus accompanied by sensual pleasures beset me, that was an affliction for me.

Then I thought, ‘Why don’t I, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled … enter and remain in the second absorption?’ But my mind did not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in not placing the mind. I didn’t see it as peaceful. Then I thought, ‘What is the cause, what is the reason why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in not placing the mind? Why don’t I see it as peaceful?’ Then I thought, ‘I haven’t seen the drawbacks of placing the mind, and so I haven’t cultivated that. I haven’t realized the benefits of not placing the mind, and so I haven’t developed that. That’s why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in not placing the mind. And it’s why I don’t see it as peaceful.’ Then I thought, ‘Suppose that, seeing the drawbacks of placing the mind, I were to cultivate that. And suppose that, realizing the benefits of not placing the mind, I were to develop that. It’s possible that my mind would leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in not placing the mind. And I would see it as peaceful.’ And so, after some time, I saw the drawbacks of placing the mind and cultivated that, and I realized the benefits of not placing the mind and developed that. Then my mind did leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in not placing the mind. I saw it as peaceful. And so, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected were stilled … I entered and remained in the second absorption. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by placing the mind beset me, and that was an affliction for me. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, when perception and focus accompanied by placing the mind and keeping it connected beset me, that was an affliction for me.

Then I thought, ‘Why don’t I, with the fading away of rapture, enter and remain in the third absorption, where I will meditate with equanimity, mindful and aware, experiencing for themselves the bliss of which the noble ones declare, “Equanimous and mindful, one meditates in bliss”?’ But my mind did not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in freedom from rapture. I didn’t see it as peaceful. Then I thought, ‘What is the cause, what is the reason why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in freedom from rapture? Why don’t I see it as peaceful?’ Then I thought, ‘I haven’t seen the drawbacks of rapture, and so I haven’t cultivated that. I haven’t realized the benefits of freedom from rapture, and so I haven’t developed that. That’s why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in freedom from rapture. And it’s why I don’t see it as peaceful.’ Then I thought, ‘Suppose that, seeing the drawbacks of rapture, I were to cultivate that. And suppose that, realizing the benefits of freedom from rapture, I were to develop that. It’s possible that my mind would leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in being free from rapture. And I would see it as peaceful.’ And so, after some time, I saw the drawbacks of rapture and cultivated that, and I realized the benefits of freedom from rapture and developed that. Then my mind leapt forth, gained confidence, settled down, and became decided in freedom from rapture. I saw it as peaceful. And so, with the fading away of rapture … I entered and remained in the third absorption. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by rapture beset me, and that was an affliction for me. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, when perception and focus accompanied by rapture beset me, that was an affliction for me.

Then I thought, ‘Why don’t I, with the giving up of pleasure and pain, and the disappearance of former happiness and sadness, enter and remain in the fourth absorption, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and mindfulness?’ But my mind did not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in being without pleasure and pain. I didn’t see it as peaceful. Then I thought, ‘What is the cause, what is the reason why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in being without pleasure and pain? Why don’t I see it as peaceful?’ Then I thought, ‘I haven’t seen the drawbacks of bliss with equanimity, and so I haven’t cultivated that. I haven’t realized the benefits of being without pleasure and pain, and so I haven’t developed that. That’s why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in being without pleasure and pain. And it’s why I don’t see it as peaceful.’ Then I thought, ‘Suppose that, seeing the drawbacks of bliss with equanimity, I were to cultivate that. And suppose that, realizing the benefits of being without pleasure and pain, I were to develop that. It’s possible that my mind would leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in being without pleasure and pain. And I would see it as peaceful.’ And so, after some time, I saw the drawbacks of bliss with equanimity and cultivated that, and I realized the benefits of being without pleasure and pain and developed that. Then my mind did leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in being without pleasure and pain. I saw it as peaceful. And so, giving up pleasure and pain … I entered and remained in the fourth absorption. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by bliss with equanimity beset me, and that was an affliction for me. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, when perception and focus accompanied by bliss with equanimity beset me, that was an affliction for me.

Then I thought, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that “space is infinite”, enter and remain in the dimension of infinite space?’ But my mind did not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of infinite space. I didn’t see it as peaceful. Then I thought, ‘What is the cause, what is the reason why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of infinite space? Why don’t I see it as peaceful?’ Then I thought, ‘I haven’t seen the drawbacks of forms, and so I haven’t cultivated that. I haven’t realized the benefits of the dimension of infinite space, and so I haven’t developed that. That’s why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of infinite space. And it’s why I don’t see it as peaceful.’ Then I thought, ‘Suppose that, seeing the drawbacks of forms, I were to cultivate that. And suppose that, realizing the benefits of the dimension of infinite space, I were to develop that. It’s possible that my mind would leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of infinite space. And I would see it as peaceful.’ And so, after some time, I saw the drawbacks of forms and cultivated that, and I realized the benefits of the dimension of infinite space and developed that. Then my mind leapt forth, gained confidence, settled down, and became decided in the dimension of infinite space. I saw it as peaceful. And so, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, I entered and remained in the dimension of infinite space. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by forms beset me, and that was an affliction for me. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, when perception and focus accompanied by forms beset me, that was an affliction for me.

Then I thought, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that “consciousness is infinite”, enter and remain in the dimension of infinite consciousness?’ But my mind did not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of infinite consciousness. I didn’t see it as peaceful. Then I thought, ‘What is the cause, what is the reason why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of infinite consciousness? Why don’t I see it as peaceful?’ Then I thought, ‘I haven’t seen the drawbacks of the dimension of infinite space, and so I haven’t cultivated that. I haven’t realized the benefits of the dimension of infinite consciousness, and so I haven’t developed that. That’s why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of infinite consciousness. And it’s why I don’t see it as peaceful.’ Then I thought, ‘Suppose that, seeing the drawbacks of the dimension of infinite space, I were to cultivate that. And suppose that, realizing the benefits of the dimension of infinite consciousness, I were to develop that. It’s possible that my mind would leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of infinite consciousness. And I would see it as peaceful.’ And so, after some time, I saw the drawbacks of the dimension of infinite space and cultivated that, and I realized the benefits of the dimension of infinite consciousness and developed that. Then my mind leapt forth, gained confidence, settled down, and became decided in the dimension of infinite consciousness. I saw it as peaceful. And so, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, I entered and remained in the dimension of infinite consciousness. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite space beset me, and that was an affliction for me. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, when perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite space beset me, that was an affliction for me.

Then I thought, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that “there is nothing at all”, enter and remain in the dimension of nothingness?’ But my mind did not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of nothingness. I didn’t see it as peaceful. Then I thought, ‘What is the cause, what is the reason why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of nothingness? Why don’t I see it as peaceful?’ Then I thought, ‘I haven’t seen the drawbacks of the dimension of infinite consciousness, and so I haven’t cultivated that. I haven’t realized the benefits of the dimension of nothingness, and so I haven’t developed that. That’s why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of nothingness. And it’s why I don’t see it as peaceful.’ Then I thought, ‘Suppose that, seeing the drawbacks of the dimension of infinite consciousness, I were to cultivate that. And suppose that, realizing the benefits of the dimension of nothingness, I were to develop that. It’s possible that my mind would leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of nothingness. And I would see it as peaceful.’ And so, after some time, I saw the drawbacks of the dimension of infinite consciousness and cultivated that, and I realized the benefits of the dimension of nothingness and developed that. Then my mind leapt forth, gained confidence, settled down, and became decided in the dimension of nothingness. I saw it as peaceful. And so, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, I entered and remained in the dimension of nothingness. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite consciousness beset me, and that was an affliction for me. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, when perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of infinite consciousness beset me, that was an affliction for me.

Then I thought, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, enter and remain in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception?’ But my mind did not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. I didn’t see it as peaceful. Then I thought, ‘What is the cause, what is the reason why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception? Why don’t I see it as peaceful?’ Then I thought, ‘I haven’t seen the drawbacks of the dimension of nothingness, and so I haven’t cultivated that. I haven’t realized the benefits of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, and so I haven’t developed that. That’s why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. And it’s why I don’t see it as peaceful.’ Then I thought, ‘Suppose that, seeing the drawbacks of the dimension of nothingness, I were to cultivate that. And suppose that, realizing the benefits of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, I were to develop that. It’s possible that my mind would leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. And I would see it as peaceful.’ And so, after some time, I saw the drawbacks of the dimension of nothingness and cultivated that, and I realized the benefits of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception and developed that. Then my mind leapt forth, gained confidence, settled down, and became decided in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. I saw it as peaceful. And so, going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, I entered and remained in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. While I was in that meditation, perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of nothingness beset me, and that was an affliction for me. Suppose a happy person were to experience pain; that would be an affliction for them. In the same way, when perception and focus accompanied by the dimension of nothingness beset me, that was an affliction for me.

Then I thought, ‘Why don’t I, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enter and remain in the cessation of perception and feeling?’ But my mind did not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the cessation of perception and feeling. I didn’t see it as peaceful. Then I thought, ‘What is the cause, what is the reason why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the cessation of perception and feeling? Why don’t I see it as peaceful?’ Then I thought, ‘I haven’t seen the drawbacks of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, and so I haven’t cultivated that. I haven’t realized the benefits of the cessation of perception and feeling, and so I haven’t developed that. That’s why my mind does not leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the cessation of perception and feeling. And it’s why I don’t see it as peaceful.’ Then I thought, ‘Suppose that, seeing the drawbacks of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, I were to cultivate that. And suppose that, realizing the benefits of the cessation of perception and feeling, I were to develop that. It’s possible that my mind would leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the cessation of perception and feeling. And I would see it as peaceful.’ And so, after some time, I saw the drawbacks of the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception and cultivated that, and I realized the benefits of the cessation of perception and feeling and developed that. Then my mind did leap forth, gain confidence, settle down, and become decided in the cessation of perception and feeling. I saw it as peaceful. And so, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, I entered and remained in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, my defilements were ended.

As long as I hadn’t entered into and withdrawn from these nine progressive meditative attainments in both forward and reverse order, I didn’t announce my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

But when I had entered into and withdrawn from these nine progressive meditative attainments in both forward and reverse order, I announced my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Māras, and divinities, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

Knowledge and vision arose in me: ‘My freedom is unshakable; this is my last rebirth; now there’ll be no more future lives.’”

The First Fifty

The Chapter on Awakening

AN 9.1 Awakening Sambodhisutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants:

“Mendicants, if wanderers of other religions were to ask: ‘Reverends, what is the vital condition for the development of the qualities on the same side as awakening?’ How would you answer them?”

“Our teachings are rooted in the Buddha. … The mendicants will listen and remember it.”

“Well then, mendicants, listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.”

“Yes, sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, if wanderers of other religions were to ask: ‘Reverends, what is the vital condition for the development of the qualities on the same side as awakening?’ You should answer them:

‘It’s when a mendicant has good friends, companions, and associates. This is the first vital condition for the development of the awakening factors.

Furthermore, a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. This is the second vital condition for the development of the qualities on the same side as awakening.

Furthermore, a mendicant gets to take part in talk about self-effacement that helps open the heart, when they want, without trouble or difficulty. That is, talk about fewness of wishes, contentment, seclusion, aloofness, arousing energy, ethics, immersion, wisdom, freedom, and the knowledge and vision of freedom. This is the third vital condition for the development of the qualities on the same side as awakening.

Furthermore, a mendicant lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They are strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. This is the fourth vital condition for the development of the qualities on the same side as awakening.

Furthermore, a mendicant is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is the fifth vital condition for the development of the qualities on the same side as awakening.’

A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to be ethical …

A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to take part in talk about self-effacement that helps open the heart …

A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to live with energy roused up …

A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to be wise …

But then, a mendicant grounded on these five things should develop four further things. They should develop the perception of ugliness to give up greed, love to give up hate, mindfulness of breathing to cut off thinking, and perception of impermanence to uproot the conceit ‘I am’. When you perceive impermanence, the perception of not-self becomes stabilized. Perceiving not-self, you uproot the conceit ‘I am’ and attain extinguishment in this very life.”

AN 9.2 Supported Nissayasutta

Then a mendicant went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Sir, they speak of being ‘supported’. How is a mendicant who is supported defined?”

“Mendicant, if a mendicant supported by faith gives up the unskillful and develops the skillful, the unskillful is actually given up by them.

If a mendicant supported by conscience …

If a mendicant supported by prudence …

If a mendicant supported by energy …

If a mendicant supported by wisdom gives up the unskillful and develops the skillful, the unskillful is actually given up by them. What’s been given up is completely given up when it has been given up by seeing with noble wisdom.

But then, a mendicant grounded on these five things should rely on four things. What four? After appraisal, a mendicant uses some things, endures some things, avoids some things, and dispels some things. That’s how a mendicant is supported.”

AN 9.3 With Meghiya Meghiyasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Cālikā, on the Cālikā mountain.

Now, at that time Venerable Meghiya was the Buddha’s attendant. Then Venerable Meghiya went up to the Buddha, bowed, stood to one side, and said to him, “Sir, I’d like to enter Jantu village for alms.”

“Please, Meghiya, go at your convenience.”

Then Meghiya robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Jantu village for alms. After the meal, on his return from almsround in Jantu village, he went to the shore of Kimikālā River. As he was going for a walk along the shore of the river he saw a lovely and delightful mango grove.

Seeing this, it occurred to him, “Oh, this mango grove is lovely and delightful! This is good enough for striving for a gentleman wanting to strive. If the Buddha allows me, I’ll come back to this mango grove to meditate.”

Then Venerable Meghiya went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened, adding, “If the Buddha allows me, I’ll go back to that mango grove to meditate.”

“We’re alone, Meghiya. Wait until another mendicant comes.”

For a second time Meghiya said to the Buddha, “Sir, the Buddha has nothing more to do, and nothing that needs improvement. But I have. If you allow me, I’ll go back to that mango grove to meditate.”

“We’re alone, Meghiya. Wait until another mendicant comes.”

For a third time Meghiya said to the Buddha, “Sir, the Buddha has nothing more to do, and nothing that needs improvement. But I have. If you allow me, I’ll go back to that mango grove to meditate.”

“Meghiya, since you speak of striving in meditation, what can I say? Please, Meghiya, go at your convenience.”

Then Meghiya got up from his seat, bowed and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right. Then he went to that mango grove, and, having plunged deep into it, sat at the root of a certain tree for the day’s meditation. But while Meghiya was meditating in that mango grove he was beset mostly by three kinds of bad, unskillful thoughts, namely, sensual, malicious, and cruel thoughts.

Then he thought, “Oh lord, how incredible, how amazing! I’ve gone forth out of faith from the lay life to homelessness, but I’m still harassed by these three kinds of bad, unskillful thoughts: sensual, malicious, and cruel thoughts.”

Then Venerable Meghiya went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“Meghiya, when the heart’s release is not ripe, five things help it ripen. What five?

Firstly, a mendicant has good friends, companions, and associates. This is the first thing …

Furthermore, a mendicant is ethical, restrained in the monastic code, conducting themselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, they keep the rules they’ve undertaken. This is the second thing …

Furthermore, a mendicant gets to take part in talk about self-effacement that helps open the heart, when they want, without trouble or difficulty. That is, talk about fewness of wishes, contentment, seclusion, aloofness, arousing energy, ethics, immersion, wisdom, freedom, and the knowledge and vision of freedom. This is the third thing …

Furthermore, a mendicant lives with energy roused up for giving up unskillful qualities and embracing skillful qualities. They are strong, staunchly vigorous, not slacking off when it comes to developing skillful qualities. This is the fourth thing …

Furthermore, a mendicant is wise. They have the wisdom of arising and passing away which is noble, penetrative, and leads to the complete ending of suffering. This is the fifth thing that, when the heart’s release is not ripe, helps it ripen.

A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to be ethical …

A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to take part in talk about self-effacement that helps open the heart …

A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to be energetic …

A mendicant with good friends, companions, and associates can expect to be wise …

But then, a mendicant grounded on these five things should develop four further things. They should develop the perception of ugliness to give up greed, love to give up hate, mindfulness of breathing to cut off thinking, and perception of impermanence to uproot the conceit ‘I am’. When you perceive impermanence, the perception of not-self becomes stabilized. Perceiving not-self, you uproot the conceit ‘I am’ and attain extinguishment in this very life.”

AN 9.4 With Nandaka Nandakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Now at that time Venerable Nandaka was educating, encouraging, firing up, and inspiring the mendicants in the assembly hall with a Dhamma talk. Then in the late afternoon, the Buddha came out of retreat and went to the assembly hall. He stood outside the door waiting for the talk to end. When he knew the talk had ended he cleared his throat and knocked on the door-panel. The mendicants opened the door for the Buddha, and he entered the assembly hall, where he sat down on the seat spread out.

He said to Nandaka, “Nandaka, that was a long exposition of the teaching you gave to the mendicants. My back was aching while I stood outside the door waiting for the talk to end.”

When he said this, Nandaka felt embarrassed and said to the Buddha, “Sir, we didn’t know that the Buddha was standing outside the door. If we’d known, I wouldn’t have said so much.”

Then the Buddha, knowing that Nandaka was embarrassed, said to him, “Good, good, Nandaka! It’s appropriate for gentlemen like you, who have gone forth out of faith from the lay life to homelessness, to sit together for a Dhamma talk. When you’re sitting together you should do one of two things: discuss the teachings or keep noble silence.

Nandaka, a mendicant is faithful but not ethical. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking, ‘How can I become faithful and ethical?’ When a mendicant is faithful and ethical, they’re complete in that respect.

A mendicant is faithful and ethical, but does not get internal serenity of heart. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking, ‘How can I become faithful and ethical and get internal serenity of heart?’ When a mendicant is faithful and ethical and gets internal serenity of heart, they’re complete in that respect.

A mendicant is faithful, ethical, and gets internal serenity of heart, but they don’t get the higher wisdom of discernment of principles. So they’re incomplete in that respect. Suppose, Nandaka, there was a four-footed animal that was lame and disabled. It would be incomplete in that respect. In the same way, a mendicant is faithful, ethical, and gets internal serenity of heart, but they don’t get the higher wisdom of discernment of principles. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking, ‘How can I become faithful and ethical and get internal serenity of heart and get the higher wisdom of discernment of principles?’

When a mendicant is faithful and ethical and gets internal serenity of heart and gets the higher wisdom of discernment of principles, they’re complete in that respect.”

That is what the Buddha said. When he had spoken, the Holy One rose from his seat and entered his dwelling.

Then, not long after the Buddha left, Venerable Nandaka said to the mendicants, “Just now, reverends, the Buddha revealed a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure in four statements, before getting up from his seat and entering his dwelling:

‘Nandaka, a mendicant is faithful but not ethical. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking, “How can I become faithful and ethical?” When a mendicant is faithful and ethical, they’re complete in that respect.

A mendicant is faithful and ethical, but does not get internal serenity of heart. …

They get internal serenity of heart, but they don’t get the higher wisdom of discernment of principles. So they’re incomplete in that respect. Suppose, Nandaka, there was a four-footed animal that was lame and disabled. It would be incomplete in that respect. In the same way, a mendicant is faithful, ethical, and gets internal serenity of heart, but they don’t get the higher wisdom of discernment of principles. So they’re incomplete in that respect, and should fulfill it, thinking: “How can I become faithful and ethical and get internal serenity of heart and get the higher wisdom of discernment of principles?” When a mendicant is faithful and ethical and gets internal serenity of heart and gets the higher wisdom of discernment of principles, they’re complete in that respect.’

Reverends, there are these five benefits of listening to the teachings at the right time and discussing the teachings at the right time. What five?

Firstly, a mendicant teaches Dhamma to the mendicants that’s good in the beginning, good in the middle, and good in the end, meaningful and well-phrased. And they reveal a spiritual practice that’s entirely full and pure. Whenever they do this, they become liked and approved by the Teacher, respected and admired. This is the first benefit …

Furthermore, a mendicant teaches the mendicants the Dhamma … Whenever they do this, they feel inspired by the meaning and the teaching in that Dhamma. This is the second benefit …

Furthermore, a mendicant teaches the mendicants the Dhamma … Whenever they do this, they see the meaning of a deep saying in that Dhamma with penetrating wisdom. This is the third benefit …

Furthermore, a mendicant teaches the mendicants the Dhamma … Whenever they do this, their spiritual companions esteem them more highly, thinking, ‘For sure this venerable has attained or will attain.’ This is the fourth benefit …

Furthermore, a mendicant teaches the mendicants the Dhamma … Whenever they do this, there may be trainee mendicants present, who haven’t achieved their heart’s desire, but live aspiring to the supreme sanctuary from the yoke. Hearing that teaching, they rouse energy for attaining the unattained, achieving the unachieved, and realizing the unrealized. There may be perfected mendicants present, who have ended the defilements, completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and are rightly freed through enlightenment. Hearing that teaching, they simply live happily in this life. This is the fifth benefit …

These are the five benefits of listening to the teachings at the right time and discussing the teachings at the right time.”

AN 9.5 Powers Balasutta

“Mendicants, there are these four powers. What four? The powers of wisdom, energy, blamelessness, and inclusiveness.

And what is the power of wisdom? One has clearly seen and clearly contemplated with wisdom those qualities that are skillful and considered to be skillful; those that are unskillful … blameworthy … blameless … dark … bright … to be cultivated … not to be cultivated … not worthy of the noble ones … worthy of the noble ones and considered to be worthy of the noble ones. This is called the power of wisdom.

And what is the power of energy? One generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives to give up those qualities that are unskillful and considered to be unskillful; those that are blameworthy … dark … not to be cultivated … not worthy of the noble ones and considered to be not worthy of the noble ones. One generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives to gain those qualities that are skillful and considered to be skillful; those that are blameless … bright … to be cultivated … worthy of the noble ones and considered to be worthy of the noble ones. This is called the power of energy.

And what is the power of blamelessness? It’s when a noble disciple has blameless conduct by way of body, speech, and mind. This is called the power of blamelessness.

And what is the power of inclusiveness? There are these four ways of being inclusive. Giving, kindly words, taking care, and equality. The best of gifts is the gift of the teaching. The best sort of kindly speech is to teach the Dhamma again and again to someone who is engaged and who actively listens. The best way of taking care is to encourage, settle, and ground the unfaithful in faith, the unethical in ethics, the stingy in generosity, and the ignorant in wisdom. The best kind of equality is the equality of a stream-enterer with another stream-enterer, a once-returner with another once-returner, a non-returner with another non-returner, and a perfected one with another perfected one. This is called the power of inclusiveness. These are the four powers.

A noble disciple who has these four powers has got past five fears. What five? Fear regarding livelihood, disrepute, feeling insecure in an assembly, death, and bad rebirth.

Then that noble disciple reflects: ‘I have no fear regarding livelihood. Why would I be afraid of that? I have these four powers: the powers of wisdom, energy, blamelessness, and inclusiveness. A witless person might fear for their livelihood. A lazy person might fear for their livelihood. Someone who does blameworthy things by way of body, speech, and mind might fear for their livelihood. Someone who does not include others might fear for their livelihood. I have no fear of disrepute … I have no fear about feeling insecure in an assembly … I have no fear of death … I have no fear of a bad rebirth. Why would I be afraid of that? I have these four powers: the powers of wisdom, energy, blamelessness, and inclusiveness. A witless person might be afraid of a bad rebirth. A lazy person might be afraid of a bad rebirth. Someone who does blameworthy things by way of body, speech, and mind might be afraid of a bad rebirth. Someone who does not include others might be afraid of a bad rebirth.’

A noble disciple who has these four powers has got past these five fears.”

AN 9.6 Association Sevanāsutta

There Sāriputta addressed the mendicants:

“Reverends, you should distinguish two two kinds of individual: those you should associate with, and those you shouldn’t associate with. You should distinguish two kinds of robes: those you should wear, and those you shouldn’t wear. You should distinguish two kinds of almsfood: that which you should eat, and that which you shouldn’t eat. You should distinguish two kinds of lodging: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent. You should distinguish two kinds of village or town: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent. You should distinguish two kinds of country: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.

‘You should distinguish two two kinds of individual: those you should associate with, and those you shouldn’t associate with.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of an individual: ‘When I associate with this individual, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline. And the necessities of life that a renunciate requires—robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick—are hard to come by. And the goal of the ascetic life for which I went forth from the lay life to homelessness is not being fully developed.’ In this case you should leave that individual at that very time of the day or night, without asking. You shouldn’t follow them.

Whereas, should you know of an individual: ‘When I associate with this individual, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline. But the necessities of life that a renunciate requires—robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick—are easy to come by. However, the goal of the ascetic life for which I went forth from the lay life to homelessness is not being fully developed.’ In this case you should leave that individual after reflecting, without asking. You shouldn’t follow them.

Well, should you know of an individual: ‘When I associate with this individual, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow. And the necessities of life that a renunciate requires—robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick—are hard to come by. But the goal of the ascetic life for which I went forth from the lay life to homelessness is being fully developed.’ In this case you should follow that individual after appraisal. You shouldn’t leave them.

Whereas, should you know of an individual: ‘When I associate with this individual, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow. And the necessities of life that a renunciate requires—robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick—are easy to come by. And the goal of the ascetic life for which I went forth from the lay life to homelessness is being fully developed.’ In this case you should follow that individual. You shouldn’t leave them, even if they send you away. ‘You should distinguish two kinds of individual: those you should associate with, and those you shouldn’t associate with.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘You should distinguish two kinds of robes: those you should wear, and those you shouldn’t wear.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of a robe: ‘When I wear this robe, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not wear that kind of robe. Whereas, should you know of a robe: ‘When I wear this robe, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should wear that kind of robe. ‘You should distinguish two kinds of robes: those you should wear, and those you shouldn’t wear.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘You should distinguish two kinds of almsfood: that which you should eat, and that which you shouldn’t eat.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of almsfood: ‘When I eat this almsfood, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not eat that kind of almsfood. Whereas, should you know of almsfood: ‘When I eat this almsfood, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should eat that kind of almsfood. ‘You should distinguish two kinds of almsfood: that which you should eat, and that which you shouldn’t eat.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘You should distinguish two kinds of lodging: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of a lodging: ‘When I frequent this lodging, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not frequent that kind of lodging. Whereas, should you know of a lodging: ‘When I frequent this lodging, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should frequent that kind of lodging. ‘You should distinguish two kinds of lodging: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘You should distinguish two kinds of village or town: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of a village or town: ‘When I frequent this village or town, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not frequent that kind of village or town. Whereas, should you know of a village or town: ‘When I frequent this village or town, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should frequent that kind of village or town. ‘You should distinguish two kinds of village or town: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.

‘You should distinguish two kinds of country: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, but why did I say it? Well, should you know of a country: ‘When I frequent this country, unskillful qualities grow, and skillful qualities decline.’ You should not frequent that kind of country. Whereas, should you know of a country: ‘When I frequent this country, unskillful qualities decline, and skillful qualities grow.’ You should frequent that kind of country. ‘You should distinguish two kinds of country: those you should frequent, and those you shouldn’t frequent.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

AN 9.7 With Sutavā the Wanderer Sutavāsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain. Then the wanderer Sutavā went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Sir, this one time the Buddha was staying right here in Rājagaha, the Mountainfold. There I heard and learned this in the presence of the Buddha: ‘A mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—can’t transgress in five respects. A mendicant with defilements ended can’t deliberately take the life of a living creature, take something with the intention to steal, have sex, tell a deliberate lie, or store up goods for their own enjoyment like they used to as a lay person.’ I trust I properly heard, learned, applied the mind, and remembered that from the Buddha?”

“Indeed, Sutavā, you properly heard, learned, applied the mind, and remembered that. In the past, as today, I say this: ‘A mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—can’t transgress in nine respects. A mendicant with defilements ended can’t deliberately take the life of a living creature, take something with the intention to steal, have sex, tell a deliberate lie, or store up goods for their own enjoyment like they used to as a lay person. And they can’t make decisions prejudiced by favoritism, hostility, stupidity, or cowardice.’ In the past, as today, I say this: ‘A mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—can’t transgress in these nine respects.’”

AN 9.8 With the Wanderer Sajjha Sajjhasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha, on the Vulture’s Peak Mountain. Then the wanderer Sajjha went up to the Buddha, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to the Buddha:

“Sir, this one time the Buddha was staying right here in Rājagaha, the Mountainfold. There I heard and learned this in the presence of the Buddha: ‘A mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—can’t transgress in five respects. A mendicant with defilements ended can’t deliberately take the life of a living creature, take something with the intention to steal, have sex, tell a deliberate lie, or store up goods for their own enjoyment like they used to as a lay person.’ I trust I properly heard, learned, applied the mind, and remembered that from the Buddha?”

“Indeed, Sajjha, you properly heard, learned, applied the mind, and remembered that. In the past, as today, I say this: ‘A mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—can’t transgress in nine respects. A mendicant with defilements ended can’t deliberately take the life of a living creature, take something with the intention to steal, have sex, tell a deliberate lie, or store up goods for their own enjoyment like they used to as a lay person. And they can’t abandon the Buddha, the teaching, the Saṅgha, or the training.’ In the past, as today, I say this: ‘A mendicant who is perfected—with defilements ended, who has completed the spiritual journey, done what had to be done, laid down the burden, achieved their heart’s goal, utterly ended the fetter of continued existence, and is rightly freed through enlightenment—can’t transgress in these nine respects.’”

AN 9.9 Individuals Puggalasutta

“Mendicants, these nine individuals are found in the world. What nine? The perfected one and the one practicing for perfection. The non-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of non-return. The once-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of once-return. The stream-enterer and the one practicing to realize the fruit of stream-entry. And the ordinary person. These are the nine individuals found in the world.”

AN 9.10 Worthy of Offerings Dedicated to the Gods Āhuneyyasutta

“Mendicants, these nine individuals are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world. What nine? The perfected one and the one practicing for perfection. The non-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of non-return. The once-returner and the one practicing to realize the fruit of once-return. The stream-enterer and the one practicing to realize the fruit of stream-entry. And a lamb of the flock. These are the nine individuals who are worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and are the supreme field of merit for the world.”

Abbreviated Texts Beginning With Greed

AN 9.93 Untitled Discourse on Greed (1st) ~

“For insight into greed, nine things should be developed. What nine? The perceptions of ugliness, death, repulsiveness of food, dissatisfaction with the whole world, impermanence, suffering in impermanence, not-self in suffering, giving up, and fading away. For insight into greed, these nine things should be developed.”

AN 9.94 Untitled Discourse on Greed (2nd) ~

“For insight into greed, nine things should be developed. What nine? The first absorption, the second absorption, the third absorption, the fourth absorption, the dimension of infinite space, the dimension of infinite consciousness, the dimension of nothingness, the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, and the cessation of perception and feeling. For insight into greed, these nine things should be developed.”

AN 9.95–112 Untitled Discourses on Greed ~

“For the complete understanding of greed … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … cessation … giving away … letting go of greed … these nine things should be developed.”

AN 9.113–432 Untitled Discourses on Hate, Etc. ~

“For insight into hate … delusion … anger … acrimony … disdain … contempt … jealousy … stinginess … deceitfulness … deviousness … obstinacy … aggression … conceit … arrogance … vanity …

For insight into negligence … complete understanding … complete ending … giving up … ending … vanishing … fading away … ceasing … giving away … For the letting go of negligence … these nine things should be developed.”

The Book of the Nines is finished.

The Chapter on Similarity

AN 9.42 Cramped Sambādhasutta

At one time Venerable Ānanda was staying near Kosambī in Ghosita’s monastery. Then Venerable Udāyī went up to Venerable Ānanda and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Ānanda, “Reverend, this was said by the godling Pañcālacaṇḍa:

‘The opening amid confinement
was discovered by the Buddha of vast intelligence,
who awakened to absorption,
the sage, the solitary boss bull.’

But what is confinement, and what is the opening amid confinement that the Buddha spoke of?”

“Reverend, these five kinds of sensual stimulation are called ‘confinement’ by the Buddha. What five? Sights known by the eye that are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds known by the ear … Smells known by the nose … Tastes known by the tongue … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These are the five kinds of sensual stimulation that are called ‘confinement’ by the Buddha.

Now, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. To this extent the Buddha spoke of an opening amid confinement in a qualified sense. But it is still confined. Confined by what? Whatever placing of the mind and keeping it connected has not ceased is the confinement there.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled … enters and remains in the second absorption. To this extent the Buddha spoke of an opening amid confinement in a qualified sense. But it is still confined. Confined by what? Whatever rapture has not ceased is the confinement there.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, with the fading away of rapture … enters and remains in the third absorption. To this extent the Buddha spoke of creating an opening amid confinement in a qualified sense. But it is still confined. Confined by what? Whatever bliss with equanimity has not ceased is the confinement there.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, giving up pleasure and pain … enters and remains in the fourth absorption. To this extent the Buddha spoke of an opening amid confinement in a qualified sense. But it is still confined. Confined by what? Whatever perception of form has not ceased is the confinement there.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. To this extent the Buddha spoke of an opening amid confinement in a qualified sense. But it is still confined. Confined by what? Whatever perception of the dimension of infinite space has not ceased is the confinement there.

Furthermore, a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite space, aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness. To this extent the Buddha spoke of an opening amid confinement in a qualified sense. But it is still confined. Confined by what? Whatever perception of the dimension of infinite consciousness has not ceased is the confinement there.

Furthermore, a mendicant, going totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness, aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, enters and remains in the dimension of nothingness. To this extent the Buddha spoke of an opening amid confinement in a qualified sense. But it is still confined. Confined by what? Whatever perception of the dimension of nothingness has not ceased is the confinement there.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of nothingness, enters and remains in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. To this extent the Buddha spoke of an opening amid confinement in a qualified sense. But it is still confined. Confined by what? Whatever perception of neither perception nor non-perception has not ceased is the confinement there.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. To this extent the Buddha spoke of an opening amid confinement in a definitive sense.”

AN 9.43 A Direct Witness Kāyasakkhīsutta

“Reverend, they speak of the ‘direct witness’. What is the direct witness that the Buddha spoke of?”

“First, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. They meditate directly experiencing that dimension in every way. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the direct witness in a qualified sense.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, as the placing of the mind and keeping it connected are stilled, enters and remains in the second absorption … third absorption … fourth absorption. They meditate directly experiencing that dimension in every way. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the direct witness in a qualified sense.

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond perceptions of form, with the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, enters and remains in the dimension of infinite space. They meditate directly experiencing that dimension in every way. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the direct witness in a qualified sense. Furthermore, take a mendicant who enters and remains in the dimension of infinite consciousness … the dimension of nothingness … the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception …

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. They meditate directly experiencing that dimension in every way. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the direct witness in a definitive sense.”

AN 9.44 Freed by Wisdom Paññāvimuttasutta

“Reverend, they speak of one ‘freed by wisdom’. What is the one freed by wisdom that the Buddha spoke of?”

“First, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. And they understand that with wisdom. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the one freed by wisdom in a qualified sense. …

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. And they understand that with wisdom. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the one freed by wisdom in a definitive sense.”

AN 9.45 Freed Both Ways Ubhatobhāgavimuttasutta

“Reverend, they speak of one ‘freed both ways’. What is the one freed both ways that the Buddha spoke of?”

“First, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. They meditate directly experiencing that dimension in every way. And they understand that with wisdom. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the one freed both ways in a qualified sense. …

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. They meditate directly experiencing that dimension in every way. And they understand that with wisdom. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the one freed both ways in a definitive sense.”

AN 9.46 In the Present Life Sandiṭṭhikadhammasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘a teaching apparent in the present life’. In what way did the Buddha speak of a teaching apparent in the present life?”

“First, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the teaching apparent in the present life in a qualified sense. …

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. To this extent the Buddha spoke of the teaching apparent in the present life in a definitive sense.”

AN 9.47 Extinguishment is Apparent in the Present Life Sandiṭṭhikanibbānasutta

“Reverend, they say that ‘extinguishment is apparent in the present life’. In what way did the Buddha say extinguishment is apparent in the present life?”

“First, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. To this extent the Buddha said that extinguishment is apparent in the present life in a qualified sense. …

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. To this extent the Buddha said that extinguishment is apparent in the present life in a definitive sense.”

AN 9.48 Extinguishment Nibbānasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘extinguishment’. …”

AN 9.49 Full Extinguishment Parinibbānasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘full extinguishment’. …”

AN 9.50 Extinguishment in a Certain Respect Tadaṅganibbānasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘extinguishment in a certain respect’. …”

AN 9.51 Extinguishment in This Life Diṭṭhadhammanibbānasutta

“Reverend, they speak of ‘extinguishment in this life’. In what way did the Buddha speak of extinguishment in this life?”

“First, take a mendicant who, quite secluded from sensual pleasures … enters and remains in the first absorption. To this extent the Buddha spoke of extinguishment in this life in a qualified sense. …

Furthermore, take a mendicant who, going totally beyond the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, enters and remains in the cessation of perception and feeling. And, having seen with wisdom, their defilements come to an end. To this extent the Buddha spoke of extinguishment in this life in a definitive sense.”

The Chapter on Right Efforts

AN 9.73 Weaknesses in Training and Effort Sikkhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five weaknesses when you’re training. What five? Killing living creatures, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, and intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. These are the five weaknesses when you’re training.

To give up these five weaknesses in your training you should develop the four right efforts. What four? It’s when a mendicant generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that bad, unskillful qualities that have arisen are given up. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities arise. They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed. To give up these five weaknesses in your training you should develop these four right efforts.”

AN 9.74–81 Hindrances, Etc. Nīvaraṇasuttādi

(Tell in full as in the chapter on mindfulness meditation.)

AN 9.82 Shackles of the Heart Cetasovinibandhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five shackles of the heart. What five? Firstly, a mendicant isn’t free of greed, desire, fondness, thirst, passion, and craving for sensual pleasures. … These are the five shackles of the heart.

To give up these five shackles of the heart you should develop the four right efforts. What four? It’s when a mendicant generates enthusiasm, tries, makes an effort, exerts the mind, and strives so that bad, unskillful qualities don’t arise. … so that unskillful qualities are given up … so that skillful qualities arise … They generate enthusiasm, try, make an effort, exert the mind, and strive so that skillful qualities that have arisen remain, are not lost, but increase, mature, and are fully developed. To give up these five shackles of the hearts you should develop these four right efforts.”

The Chapter on Mindfulness Meditation

AN 9.63 Weaknesses in Training and Mindfulness Meditation Sikkhādubbalyasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five weaknesses when you’re training. What five? Killing living creatures, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, and intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor. These are the five weaknesses when you’re training.

To give up these five weaknesses in your training you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … They meditate observing an aspect of the mind … They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. To give up those five weaknesses in your training you should develop these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

AN 9.64 Hindrances Nīvaraṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five hindrances. What five? Sensual desire, ill will, dullness and drowsiness, restlessness and remorse, and doubt. These are the five hindrances.

To give up these five hindrances you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … They meditate observing an aspect of the mind … They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. To give up those five hindrances you should develop these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

AN 9.65 Kinds of Sensual Stimulation Kāmaguṇasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five kinds of sensual stimulation. What five? Sights known by the eye, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. Sounds known by the ear … Smells known by the nose … Tastes known by the tongue … Touches known by the body, which are likable, desirable, agreeable, pleasant, sensual, and arousing. These are the five kinds of sensual stimulation.

To give up these five kinds of sensual stimulation you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. …”

AN 9.66 Grasping Aggregates Upādānakkhandhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five grasping aggregates. What five? The grasping aggregates of form, feeling, perception, choices, and consciousness. These are the five grasping aggregates.

To give up these five grasping aggregates you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. …”

AN 9.67 Lower Fetters Orambhāgiyasutta

“Mendicants, there are five lower fetters. What five? Substantialist view, doubt, misapprehension of precepts and observances, sensual desire, and ill will. These are the five lower fetters.

To give up these five lower fetters you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. …”

AN 9.68 Places of Rebirth Gatisutta

“Mendicants, there are five destinations. What five? Hell, the animal realm, the ghost realm, humanity, and the gods. These are the five destinations.

To give up these five destinations you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. …”

AN 9.69 Stinginess Macchariyasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five kinds of stinginess. What five? Stinginess with dwellings, families, material things, praise, and the teaching. These are the five kinds of stinginess.

To give up these five kinds of stinginess you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. …”

AN 9.70 Higher Fetters Uddhambhāgiyasutta

“Mendicants, there are five higher fetters. What five? Desire for rebirth in the realm of luminous form, desire for rebirth in the formless realm, conceit, restlessness, and ignorance. These are the five higher fetters.

To give up these five higher fetters you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. …”

AN 9.71 Hard-heartedness Cetokhilasutta

“Mendicants, there are five kinds of hard-heartedness. What five? Firstly, a mendicant has doubts about the Teacher. They’re uncertain, undecided, and lacking confidence. This being so, their mind doesn’t incline toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the first kind of hard-heartedness.

Furthermore, a mendicant has doubts about the teaching … the Saṅgha … the training … A mendicant is angry and upset with their spiritual companions, resentful and closed off. This being so, their mind doesn’t incline toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the fifth kind of hard-heartedness.

To give up these five kinds of hard-heartedness you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. …”

AN 9.72 Shackles of the Heart Cetasovinibandhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these five shackles of the heart. What five? Firstly, a mendicant isn’t free of greed, desire, fondness, thirst, passion, and craving for sensual pleasures. This being so, their mind doesn’t incline toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the first shackle of the heart.

Furthermore, a mendicant isn’t free of greed for the body … They’re not free of greed for form … They eat as much as they like until their belly is full, then indulge in the pleasures of sleeping, lying down, and drowsing … They lead the spiritual life wishing to be reborn in one of the orders of gods: ‘By this precept or observance or fervent austerity or spiritual practice, may I become one of the gods!’ This being so, their mind doesn’t incline toward keenness, commitment, persistence, and striving. This is the fifth shackle of the heart. These are the five shackles of the heart.

To give up these five shackles of the heart you should develop the four kinds of mindfulness meditation. What four? It’s when a mendicant meditates by observing an aspect of the body—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. They meditate observing an aspect of feelings … They meditate observing an aspect of the mind … They meditate observing an aspect of principles—keen, aware, and mindful, rid of covetousness and displeasure for the world. To give up these five shackles of the heart you should develop these four kinds of mindfulness meditation.”

The Chapter on Abodes of Sentient Beings

AN 9.21 In Three Particulars Tiṭhānasutta

“The humans of the land north of Kuru surpass the gods of the thirty-three and the humans of the Black Plum Tree Land in three particulars. What three? They’re selfless and not possessive. They have a fixed lifespan. They have a distinctive nature. The humans of the land north of Kuru surpass the gods of the thirty-three and the humans of the Black Plum Tree Land in these three particulars.

The gods of the thirty-three surpass the humans of the land north of Kuru and the Black Plum Tree Land in three particulars. What three? Heavenly lifespan, beauty, and happiness. The gods of the thirty-three surpass the humans of the land north of Kuru and the Black Plum Tree Land in these three particulars.

The humans of the Black Plum Tree Land surpass the humans of the land north of Kuru and the gods of the thirty-three in three particulars. What three? Bravery, mindfulness, and the spiritual life is lived here. The humans of the Black Plum Tree Land surpass the humans of the land north of Kuru and the gods of the thirty-three in these three particulars.”

AN 9.22 A Wild Colt Assakhaḷuṅkasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you about three wild colts and three wild people; three excellent horses and three excellent people; and three fine thoroughbred horses and three fine thoroughbred people. Listen and apply your mind well, I will speak.

And what are the three wild colts? One wild colt is fast, but not beautiful or well proportioned. Another wild colt is fast and beautiful, but not well proportioned. While another wild colt is fast, beautiful, and well proportioned. These are the three wild colts.

And what are the three wild people? One wild person is fast, but not beautiful or well proportioned. Another wild person is fast and beautiful, but not well proportioned. While another wild person is fast, beautiful, and well proportioned.

And how is a wild person fast, but not beautiful or well proportioned? It’s when a mendicant truly understands: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. This is how they’re fast, I say. But when asked a question about the teaching or training, they falter without answering. This is how they’re not beautiful, I say. And they don’t receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. This is how they’re not well proportioned, I say. This is how a wild person is fast, but not beautiful or well proportioned.

And how is a wild person fast and beautiful, but not well proportioned? They truly understand: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. This is how they’re fast, I say. When asked a question about the teaching or training, they answer without faltering. This is how they’re beautiful, I say. But they don’t receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. This is how they’re not well proportioned, I say. This is how a wild person is fast and beautiful, but not well proportioned.

And how is a wild person fast, beautiful, and well proportioned? They truly understand: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering’. This is how they’re fast, I say. When asked a question about the teaching or training, they answer without faltering. This is how they’re beautiful, I say. They receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. This is how they’re well proportioned, I say. This is how a wild person is fast, beautiful, and well proportioned. These are the three wild people.

And what are the three excellent horses? One excellent horse … is fast, beautiful, and well proportioned. These are the three excellent horses.

What are the three excellent people? One excellent person … is fast, beautiful, and well proportioned.

And how is an excellent person … fast, beautiful, and well proportioned? It’s when a mendicant, with the ending of the five lower fetters, is reborn spontaneously. They’re extinguished there, and are not liable to return from that world. This is how they’re fast, I say. When asked a question about the teaching or training, they answer without faltering. This is how they’re beautiful, I say. They receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. This is how they’re well proportioned, I say. This is how an excellent person is fast, beautiful, and well proportioned. These are the three excellent people.

And what are the three fine thoroughbred horses? One fine thoroughbred horse … is fast, beautiful, and well proportioned. These are the three fine thoroughbred horses.

And what are the three fine thoroughbred people? One fine thoroughbred person … is fast, beautiful, and well proportioned.

And how is a fine thoroughbred person … fast, beautiful, and well proportioned? It’s a mendicant who realizes the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom. And they live having realized it with their own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements. This is how they’re fast, I say. When asked a question about the teaching or training, they answer without faltering. This is how they’re beautiful, I say. They receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick. This is how they’re well proportioned, I say. This is how a fine thoroughbred person is fast, beautiful, and well proportioned. These are the three fine thoroughbred people.”

AN 9.23 Rooted in Craving Taṇhāmūlakasutta

“Mendicants, I will teach you about nine things rooted in craving. And what are the nine things rooted in craving? Craving gives rise to searching. Searching gives rise to gaining material things. Gaining material things gives rise to evaluation. Evaluation gives rise to desire and lust. Desire and lust gives rise to attachment. Attachment gives rise to ownership. Ownership gives rise to stinginess. Stinginess gives rise to safeguarding. Owing to safeguarding, many bad, unskillful things come to be: taking up the rod and the sword, quarrels, arguments, and disputes, accusations, backbiting, and lies. These are the nine things rooted in craving.”

AN 9.24 Abodes of Sentient Beings Sattāvāsasutta

“Mendicants, there are nine abodes of sentient beings. What nine?

There are sentient beings that are diverse in body and diverse in perception, such as human beings, some gods, and some beings in the underworld. This is the first abode of sentient beings.

There are sentient beings that are diverse in body and unified in perception, such as the gods reborn in the Divinity’s host through the first absorption. This is the second abode of sentient beings.

There are sentient beings that are unified in body and diverse in perception, such as the gods of sublime luminosity. This is the third abode of sentient beings.

There are sentient beings that are unified in body and unified in perception, such as the gods of universal beauty. This is the fourth abode of sentient beings.

There are sentient beings that are non-percipient and do not experience anything, such as the gods who are non-percipient beings. This is the fifth abode of sentient beings.

There are sentient beings that have gone totally beyond perceptions of form. With the disappearance of perceptions of impingement, not focusing on perceptions of diversity, aware that ‘space is infinite’, they have been reborn in the dimension of infinite space. This is the sixth abode of sentient beings.

There are sentient beings that have gone totally beyond the dimension of infinite space. Aware that ‘consciousness is infinite’, they have been reborn in the dimension of infinite consciousness. This is the seventh abode of sentient beings.

There are sentient beings that have gone totally beyond the dimension of infinite consciousness. Aware that ‘there is nothing at all’, they have been reborn in the dimension of nothingness. This is the eighth abode of sentient beings.

There are sentient beings that have gone totally beyond the dimension of nothingness. They have been reborn in the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception. This is the ninth abode of sentient beings.

These are the nine abodes of sentient beings.”

AN 9.25 Consolidated by Wisdom Paññāsutta

“Mendicants, when a mendicant’s mind has been well consolidated with wisdom it’s appropriate for them to say: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’

And how is a mendicant’s mind well consolidated with wisdom? The mind is well consolidated with wisdom when they know: ‘My mind is without greed.’ … ‘My mind is without hate.’ … ‘My mind is without delusion.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to become greedy.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to become hateful.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to become deluded.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to return to rebirth in the sensual realm.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to return to rebirth in the realm of luminous form.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to return to rebirth in the formless realm.’ When a mendicant’s mind has been well consolidated with wisdom it’s appropriate for them to say: ‘I understand: “Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.”’”

AN 9.26 The Simile of the Stone Post Silāyūpasutta

So I have heard. At one time the Buddha was staying near Rājagaha in the Bamboo Grove, the squirrels’ feeding ground.

There Venerable Candikāputta addressed the mendicants, “Reverends, Devadatta teaches the mendicants like this: ‘When a mendicant’s mind is solidified by heart, it’s appropriate for them to say: “I understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”’”

When he said this, Venerable Sāriputta said to him, “Reverend Candikāputta, Devadatta does not teach the mendicants like that. He teaches like this: ‘When a mendicant’s mind is well consolidated by heart, it’s appropriate for them to say: “I understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”’”

For a second time …

And for a third time Venerable Candikāputta addressed the mendicants …

And for a third time, Sāriputta said to him, “Reverend Candikāputta, Devadatta does not teach the mendicants like that. He teaches like this: ‘When a mendicant’s mind is well consolidated by heart, it’s appropriate for them to say: “I understand: ‘Rebirth is ended, the spiritual journey has been completed, what had to be done has been done, there is nothing further for this place.’”’

And how is a mendicant’s mind well consolidated by heart? The mind is well consolidated by heart when they know: ‘My mind is without greed.’ … ‘My mind is without hate.’ … ‘My mind is without delusion.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to become greedy.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to become hateful.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to become deluded.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to return to rebirth in the sensual realm.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to return to rebirth in the realm of luminous form.’ … ‘My mind is not liable to return to rebirth in the formless realm.’

When a mendicant’s mind is rightly freed like this, even if compelling sights come into the range of vision they don’t occupy their mind. Their mind is quite untainted. It is steady, imperturbable, observing disappearance.

Suppose there was a stone post, sixteen feet long. Eight feet were buried underground, and eight above ground. And violent storms were to blow up out of the east, the west, the north, and the south. They couldn’t make it tremor and tremble and quake. Why is that? It’s because that stone post is firmly embedded, with deep foundations. In the same way, when a mendicant’s mind is rightly freed like this, even if compelling sights come into the range of vision they don’t occupy their mind. Their mind is quite untainted. It is steady, imperturbable, observing disappearance.

If even compelling sounds … smells … tastes … touches … and ideas come into the range of the mind they don’t occupy the mind. Their mind is quite untainted. It is steady, imperturbable, observing disappearance.”

AN 9.27 Fears and Enmities (1st) Paṭhamaverasutta

Then the householder Anāthapiṇḍika went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Householder, when a noble disciple has quelled five fears and enmities, and possesses the four factors of stream-entry, they may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’

What are the five fears and enmities they have quelled? Anyone who kills living creatures brims with fear and enmity both in this life and in lives to come, and experiences mental pain and sadness. Anyone who refrains from killing living creatures does not brim with fear and enmity either in this life or in lives to come, and doesn’t experience mental pain and sadness. So that fear and enmity is quelled for anyone who refrains from killing living creatures.

Anyone who steals …

Anyone who commits sexual misconduct …

Anyone who lies …

Anyone who consumes beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants brims with fear and enmity both in this life and in lives to come, and experiences mental pain and sadness. Anyone who refrains from beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants does not brim with fear and enmity either in this life or in lives to come, and doesn’t experience mental pain and sadness. So that fear and enmity is quelled for anyone who refrains from beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants.

These are the five fears and enmities they have quelled.

What are the four factors of stream-entry that they possess? It’s when a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha: ‘That Blessed One is perfected, a fully awakened Buddha, accomplished in knowledge and conduct, holy, knower of the world, supreme guide for those fit for training, teacher of gods and humans, awakened, blessed.’

They have experiential confidence in the teaching: ‘The teaching is well explained by the Buddha—apparent in the present life, immediately effective, inviting inspection, relevant, so that sensible people can know it for themselves.’

They have experiential confidence in the Saṅgha: ‘The Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples is practicing the way that’s good, direct, systematic, and proper. It consists of the four pairs, the eight individual persons. This is the Saṅgha of the Buddha’s disciples that is worthy of offerings dedicated to the gods, worthy of hospitality, worthy of a religious donation, worthy of greeting with cupped palms, and is the supreme field of merit for the world.’

And a noble disciple’s ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. These are the four factors of stream-entry that they possess.

When a noble disciple has quelled these five fears and enmities, and possesses these four factors of stream-entry, they may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’”

AN 9.28 Fears and Enmities (2nd) Dutiyaverasutta

“Mendicants, when a noble disciple has quelled five fears and enmities, and possesses the four factors of stream-entry, they may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’

What are the five fears and enmities they have quelled? Anyone who kills living creatures brims with fear and enmity both in this life and in lives to come, and experiences mental pain and sadness. Anyone who refrains from killing living creatures does not brim with fear and enmity either in this life or in lives to come, and doesn’t experience mental pain and sadness. So that fear and enmity is quelled for anyone who refrains from killing living creatures.

Anyone who steals … commits sexual misconduct … lies … Anyone who consumes beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants brims with fear and enmity both in this life and in lives to come, and experiences mental pain and sadness. Anyone who refrains from beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants does not brim with fear and enmity either in this life or in lives to come, and doesn’t experience mental pain and sadness. So that fear and enmity is quelled for anyone who refrains from beer, wine, and liquor intoxicants. These are the five fears and enmities they have quelled.

What are the four factors of stream-entry that they possess? When a noble disciple has experiential confidence in the Buddha … the teaching … the Saṅgha … And a noble disciple’s ethical conduct is loved by the noble ones, unbroken, impeccable, spotless, and unmarred, liberating, praised by sensible people, not mistaken, and leading to immersion. These are the four factors of stream-entry that they possess.

When a noble disciple has quelled these five fears and enmities, and possesses these four factors of stream-entry, they may, if they wish, declare of themselves: ‘I’ve finished with rebirth in hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. I’ve finished with all places of loss, bad places, the underworld. I am a stream-enterer! I’m not liable to be reborn in the underworld, and am assured, destined for awakening.’”

AN 9.29 Grounds for Resentment Āghātavatthusutta

“Mendicants, there are nine grounds for resentment. What nine? Thinking: ‘They did wrong to me,’ you harbor resentment. Thinking: ‘They are doing wrong to me’ … ‘They will do wrong to me’ … ‘They did wrong to someone I love’ … ‘They are doing wrong to someone I love’ … ‘They will do wrong to someone I love’ … ‘They helped someone I dislike’ … ‘They are helping someone I dislike’ … Thinking: ‘They will help someone I dislike,’ you harbor resentment. These are the nine grounds for resentment.”

AN 9.30 Getting Rid of Resentment Āghātapaṭivinayasutta

“Mendicants, there are these nine ways to get rid of resentment. What nine? Thinking: ‘They harmed me, but what can I possibly do?’ you get rid of resentment. Thinking: ‘They are harming me …’ … ‘They will harm me …’ … ‘They harmed someone I love …’ … ‘They are harming someone I love …’ … ‘They will harm someone I love …’ … ‘They helped someone I dislike …’ … ‘They are helping someone I dislike …’ … Thinking: ‘They will help someone I dislike, but what can I possibly do?’ you get rid of resentment. These are the nine ways to get rid of resentment.”

AN 9.31 Progressive Cessations Anupubbanirodhasutta

“Mendicants, there are these nine progressive cessations. What nine?

For someone who has attained the first absorption, sensual perceptions have ceased.

For someone who has attained the second absorption, the placing of the mind and keeping it connected have ceased.

For someone who has attained the third absorption, rapture has ceased.

For someone who has attained the fourth absorption, breathing has ceased.

For someone who has attained the dimension of infinite space, the perception of form has ceased.

For someone who has attained the dimension of infinite consciousness, the perception of the dimension of infinite space has ceased.

For someone who has attained the dimension of nothingness, the perception of the dimension of infinite consciousness has ceased.

For someone who has attained the dimension of neither perception nor non-perception, the perception of the dimension of nothingness has ceased.

For someone who has attained the cessation of perception and feeling, perception and feeling have ceased.

These are the nine progressive cessations.”

The Chapter on the Lion’s Roar

AN 9.11 Sāriputta’s Lion’s Roar Sīhanādasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Then Venerable Sāriputta went up to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him, “Sir, I have completed the rainy season residence at Sāvatthī. I wish to leave to wander the countryside.”

“Please, Sāriputta, go at your convenience.” Then Sāriputta rose from his seat, bowed, and respectfully circled the Buddha, keeping him on his right, before leaving.

And then, not long after Sāriputta had left, a certain monk said to the Buddha, “Sir, Venerable Sāriputta attacked me and left without saying sorry.”

So the Buddha addressed one of the monks, “Please, monk, in my name tell Sāriputta that the Teacher summons him.”

“Yes, sir,” that monk replied. He went to Sāriputta and said to him, “Reverend Sāriputta, the Teacher summons you.”

“Yes, reverend,” Sāriputta replied.

Now at that time the venerables Mahāmoggallāna and Ānanda, taking a latchkey, went from dwelling to dwelling, saying: “Come forth, venerables! Come forth, venerables! Now Venerable Sāriputta will roar his lion’s roar in the presence of the Buddha!”

Then Venerable Sāriputta went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him:

“Sāriputta, one of your spiritual companions has made this complaint: ‘Venerable Sāriputta attacked me and left without saying sorry.’”

“Sir, someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.

Suppose they were to toss both clean and unclean things on the earth, like feces, urine, spit, pus, and blood. The earth isn’t horrified, repelled, and disgusted because of this. In the same way, I live with a heart like the earth, abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.

Suppose they were to wash both clean and unclean things in water, like feces, urine, spit, pus, and blood. The water isn’t horrified, repelled, and disgusted because of this. In the same way, I live with a heart like water, abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.

Suppose a fire were to burn both clean and unclean things, like feces, urine, spit, pus, and blood. The fire isn’t horrified, repelled, and disgusted because of this. In the same way, I live with a heart like fire, abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.

Suppose the wind was to blow on both clean and unclean things, like feces, urine, spit, pus, and blood. The wind isn’t horrified, repelled, and disgusted because of this. In the same way, I live with a heart like the wind, abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.

Suppose a rag was to wipe up both clean and unclean things, like feces, urine, spit, pus, and blood. The rag isn’t horrified, repelled, and disgusted because of this. In the same way, I live with a heart like a rag, abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.

Suppose a boy or girl of a corpse-worker tribe, holding a pot and clad in rags, were to enter a town or village. They’d enter with a humble mind. In the same way, I live with a heart like a boy or girl of a corpse-worker tribe, abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.

Suppose there was a bull with his horns cut, gentle, well tamed and well trained. He’d wander from street to street and square to square without hurting anyone with his feet or horns. In the same way, I live with a heart like a bull with horns cut, abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. Someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.

Suppose there was a woman or man who was young, youthful, and fond of adornments, and had bathed their head. If the carcass of a snake or a dog or a human were hung around their neck, they’d be horrified, repelled, and disgusted. In the same way, I’m horrified, repelled, and disgusted by this rotting body. Someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.

Suppose someone was to carry around a bowl of fat that was leaking and oozing from holes and cracks. In the same way, I carry around this body that’s leaking and oozing from holes and cracks. Someone who had not established mindfulness of the body might well attack one of their spiritual companions and leave without saying sorry.”

Then that monk rose from his seat, placed his robe over one shoulder, bowed with his head to the Buddha’s feet, and said, “I made a mistake, sir. It was foolish, stupid, and unskillful of me to speak ill of Venerable Sāriputta with an incorrect, hollow, false, untruthful claim. Please, sir, accept my mistake for what it is, so I will restrain myself in future.”

“Indeed, monk, you made a mistake. It was foolish, stupid, and unskillful of you to act in that way. But since you have recognized your mistake for what it is, and have dealt with it properly, I accept it. For it is growth in the training of the Noble One to recognize a mistake for what it is, deal with it properly, and commit to restraint in the future.”

Then the Buddha said to Venerable Sāriputta, “Sāriputta, forgive that futile man before his head explodes into seven pieces right here.”

“I will pardon that venerable if he asks me: ‘May the venerable please pardon me too.’”

AN 9.12 With Residue Saupādisesasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery.

Then Venerable Sāriputta robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, entered Sāvatthī for alms. Then it occurred to him, “It’s too early to wander for alms in Sāvatthī. Why don’t I visit the monastery for the wanderers of other religions?” Then he went to the monastery for the wanderers of other religions and exchanged greetings with the wanderers there. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side.

Now at that time while those wanderers of other religions were sitting together this discussion came up among them:

“Reverends, no one who dies with residue is exempt from hell, the animal realm, or the ghost realm. They’re not exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.”

Sāriputta neither approved nor rejected that statement of the wanderers of other religions. He rose from his seat, thinking, “I will learn the meaning of this statement from the Buddha himself.”

Then Sāriputta wandered for alms in Sāvatthī. After the meal, on his return from almsround, he went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“Sāriputta, these foolish, incompetent wanderers following other religions: who are they to know whether someone has residue or not?

There are these nine individuals who, dying with residue, are exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld. What nine?

There’s an individual who has fulfilled ethics and immersion, but has limited wisdom. With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished between one life and the next. This is the first individual …

Furthermore, there’s an individual who has fulfilled ethics and immersion, but has limited wisdom. With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished upon landing. This is the second individual …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished without extra effort. This is the third individual …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they’re extinguished with extra effort. This is the fourth individual …

With the ending of the five lower fetters they head upstream, going to the Akaniṭṭha realm. This is the fifth individual …

Furthermore, there’s an individual who has fulfilled ethics, but has limited immersion and wisdom. With the ending of three fetters, and the weakening of greed, hate, and delusion, they’re a once-returner. They come back to this world once only, then make an end of suffering. This is the sixth individual …

Furthermore, there’s an individual who has fulfilled ethics, but has limited immersion and wisdom. With the ending of three fetters, they’re a one-seeder. They will be reborn just one time in a human existence, then make an end of suffering. This is the seventh individual …

Furthermore, there’s an individual who has fulfilled ethics, but has limited immersion and wisdom. With the ending of three fetters, they go from family to family. They will transmigrate between two or three families and then make an end of suffering. This is the eighth individual …

Furthermore, there’s an individual who has fulfilled ethics, but has limited immersion and wisdom. With the ending of three fetters, they have at most seven rebirths. They will transmigrate at most seven times among gods and humans and then make an end of suffering. This is the ninth individual …

These foolish, incompetent wanderers following other religions: who are they to know whether someone has residue or not? These are the nine individuals who, dying with residue, are exempt from hell, the animal realm, and the ghost realm. They’re exempt from places of loss, bad places, the underworld.

Up until now, Sāriputta, I have not felt the need to give this exposition of the teaching to the monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen. Why is that? For I didn’t want those who heard it to introduce negligence. However, I have spoken it in order to answer your question.”

AN 9.13 With Koṭṭhita Koṭṭhikasutta

Then Venerable Mahākoṭṭhita went up to Venerable Sāriputta, and exchanged greetings with him. When the greetings and polite conversation were over, he sat down to one side and said to Sāriputta:

“Reverend Sāriputta, is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds to be experienced in this life be experienced by me in lives to come’?”

“Certainly not, reverend.”

“Then is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds to be experienced in lives to come be experienced by me in this life’?”

“Certainly not.”

“Is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds to be experienced as pleasant be experienced by me as painful’?”

“Certainly not.”

“Then is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds to be experienced as painful be experienced by me as pleasant’?”

“Certainly not.”

“Is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds to be experienced when ripe be experienced by me when unripe’?”

“Certainly not.”

“Then is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds to be experienced when unripe be experienced by me when ripe’?”

“Certainly not.”

“Is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds to be experienced a lot be experienced by me a little’?”

“Certainly not.”

“Then is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds to be experienced a little be experienced by me a lot’?”

“Certainly not.”

“Is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds to be experienced by me be not experienced’?”

“Certainly not.”

“Then is the spiritual life led under the Buddha for this goal: ‘May deeds not to be experienced be experienced’?”

“Certainly not.”

“Reverend Sāriputta, when you were asked whether the spiritual life was lived under the Buddha so that deeds to be experienced in this life are experienced in lives to come, you said, ‘Certainly not’.

When you were asked whether the spiritual life was lived under the Buddha so that deeds to be experienced in lives to come are experienced in this life …

deeds to be experienced as pleasant are experienced as painful …

deeds to be experienced as painful are experienced as pleasant …

deeds to be experienced when ripe are experienced when unripe …

deeds to be experienced when unripe are experienced when ripe …

deeds to be experienced a lot are experienced a little …

deeds to be experienced a little are experienced a lot …

deeds to be experienced are not experienced …

When you were asked whether the spiritual life was lived under the Buddha so that deeds not to be experienced are experienced, you said, ‘Certainly not.’ Then what exactly is the goal of leading the spiritual life under the Buddha?”

“Reverend, the spiritual life is lived under the Buddha to know, see, attain, realize, and comprehend that which is unknown, unseen, unattained, unrealized, and uncomprehended.”

“But what is the unknown, unseen, unattained, unrealized, and uncomprehended?”

“‘This is suffering.’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering.’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering.’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering.’ … This is the unknown, unseen, unattained, unrealized, and uncomprehended. The spiritual life is lived under the Buddha to know, see, attain, realize, and comprehend this.”

AN 9.14 With Samiddhi Samiddhisutta

Then Venerable Samiddhi went up to Venerable Sāriputta, bowed, and sat to one side. Venerable Sāriputta said to him:

“Samiddhi, based on what do thoughts arise in a person?”

“Based on name and form, sir.”

“Where do they become diversified?”

“In the elements.”

“What is their origin?”

“Contact is their origin.”

“What is their meeting place?”

“Feeling is their meeting place.”

“What is their chief?”

“Immersion is their chief.”

“What is their ruler?”

“Mindfulness is their ruler.”

“What is their overseer?”

“Wisdom is their overseer.”

“What is their core?”

“Freedom is their core.”

“What is their objective?”

“Their objective is freedom from death.”

“Samiddhi, when you were asked what is the basis on which thoughts arise in a person, you answered ‘name and form’. When you were asked … what is their objective, you answered ‘freedom from death’. Good, good, Samiddhi! It’s good that you answered each question. But don’t get conceited because of that.”

AN 9.15 The Simile of the Boil Gaṇḍasutta

“Mendicants, suppose there was a boil that was many years old. And that boil had nine orifices that were continually open wounds. Whatever oozed out of them would be filthy, stinking, and disgusting. Whatever exuded from them would be filthy, stinking, and disgusting.

‘Boil’ is a term for this body made up of the four principal states, produced by mother and father, built up from rice and porridge, liable to impermanence, to wearing away and erosion, to breaking up and destruction. And that boil has nine orifices that are continually open wounds. Whatever oozes out of them is filthy, stinking, and disgusting. Whatever exudes from them is filthy, stinking, and disgusting. So, mendicants, have no illusion about this body.”

AN 9.16 Perceptions Saññāsutta

“Mendicants, these nine perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. Their objective and culmination is freedom from death. What nine? The perceptions of ugliness, death, repulsiveness of food, dissatisfaction with the whole world, impermanence, suffering in impermanence, not-self in suffering, giving up, and fading away. These nine perceptions, when developed and cultivated, are very fruitful and beneficial. Their objective and culmination is freedom from death.”

AN 9.17 Families Kulasutta

“Mendicants, visiting a family with nine factors is not worthwhile, or if you’ve already arrived, sitting down is not worthwhile. What nine? They don’t politely rise, bow, or offer a seat. They hide what they have. Even when they have much they give little. Even when they have fine things they give coarse things. They give carelessly, not carefully. They don’t sit nearby to listen to the teachings. When you’re speaking, they don’t listen well. Visiting a family with these nine factors is not worthwhile, or if you’ve already arrived, sitting down is not worthwhile.

Visiting a family with nine factors is worthwhile, or if you’ve already arrived, sitting down is worthwhile. What nine? They politely rise, bow, and offer a seat. They don’t hide what they have. When they have much they give much. When they have refined things they give refined things. They give carefully, not carelessly. They sit nearby to listen to the teachings. When you’re speaking, they listen well. Visiting a family with these nine factors is worthwhile, or if you’ve already arrived, sitting down is worthwhile.”

AN 9.18 The Sabbath with Nine Factors Navaṅguposathasutta

“Mendicants, the observance of the sabbath with its nine factors is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful. And how should it be observed?

It’s when a noble disciple reflects: ‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. They are scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I, too, for this day and night will give up killing living creatures, renouncing the rod and the sword. I’ll be scrupulous and kind, and live full of sympathy for all living beings. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its first factor. …

‘As long as they live, the perfected ones give up high and luxurious beds. They sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I, too, for this day and night will give up high and luxurious beds. I’ll sleep in a low place, either a cot or a grass mat. I will observe the sabbath by doing as the perfected ones do in this respect.’ This is its eighth factor.

They meditate spreading a heart full of love to one direction, and to the second, and to the third, and to the fourth. In the same way above, below, across, everywhere, all around, they spread a heart full of love to the whole world—abundant, expansive, limitless, free of enmity and ill will. This is its ninth factor.

The observance of the sabbath with its nine factors in this way is very fruitful and beneficial and brilliant and bountiful.”

AN 9.19 A Deity Devatāsutta

“Mendicants, tonight, several glorious deities, lighting up the entire Jeta’s Grove, came to me, bowed, stood to one side, and said to me: ‘Sir, formerly when we were human beings, renunciates came to our homes. We politely rose for them, but we didn’t bow. And so, having not fulfilled our duty, full of remorse and regret, we were reborn in a lesser realm.’

Then several other deities came to me and said: ‘Sir, formerly when we were human beings, renunciates came to our homes. We politely rose for them and bowed, but we didn’t offer a seat. And so, having not fulfilled our duty, full of remorse and regret, we were reborn in a lesser realm.’

Then several other deities came to me and said: ‘Sir, formerly when we were human beings, renunciates came to our homes. We politely rose for them, bowed, and offered a seat, but we didn’t share as best we could. …’

‘… we didn’t sit nearby to listen to the teachings. …’

‘… we didn’t actively listen to the teachings. …’

‘… we didn’t memorize the teachings. …’

‘… we didn’t examine the meaning of teachings we’d memorized. …’

‘… not having understood the meaning and the teaching, we didn’t practice in line with the teaching. And so, having not fulfilled our duty, full of remorse and regret, we were reborn in a lesser realm.’

Then several other deities came to me and said: ‘Sir, formerly when we were human beings, renunciates came to our homes. We politely rose, bowed, and offered them a seat. We shared as best we could. We sat nearby to listen to the teachings, lent an ear, memorized them, and examined their meaning. Understanding the teaching and the meaning we practiced in line with the teaching. And so, having fulfilled our duty, free of remorse and regret, we were reborn in a superior realm.’

Here, mendicants, are these roots of trees, and here are these empty huts. Practice absorption, mendicants! Don’t be negligent! Don’t regret it later, like those former deities.”

AN 9.20 About Velāma Velāmasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Then the householder Anāthapiṇḍika went up to the Buddha, bowed, and sat down to one side. The Buddha said to him, “Householder, I wonder whether your family gives gifts?”

“It does, sir. But only coarse sour gruel with false black pepper.”

“Householder, someone might give a gift that’s either coarse or fine. But they give it carelessly, thoughtlessly, not with their own hand. They give the dregs, and they give without consideration for consequences. Then wherever the result of any such gift manifests, their mind doesn’t incline toward enjoyment of nice food, clothes, vehicles, or the five refined kinds of sensual stimulation. And their children, wives, bondservants, servants, and workers don’t want to listen to them. They don’t actively listen or try to understand. Why is that? Because that is the result of deeds done carelessly.

Someone might give a gift that’s either coarse or fine. And they give it carefully, thoughtfully, with their own hand. They don’t give the dregs, and they give with consideration for consequences. Then wherever the result of any such gift manifests, their mind inclines toward enjoyment of nice food, clothes, vehicles, or the five refined kinds of sensual stimulation. And their children, wives, bondservants, servants, and workers want to listen. They actively listen and try to understand. Why is that? Because that is the result of deeds done carefully.

Once upon a time, householder, there was a brahmin named Velāma. He gave the following gift, a great offering. 84,000 gold cups filled with silver. 84,000 silver cups filled with gold. 84,000 bronze cups filled with gold coins. 84,000 elephants with gold adornments and banners, covered with snow gold netting. 84,000 chariots upholstered with the hide of lions, tigers, and leopards, and cream rugs, with gold adornments and banners, covered with snow gold netting. 84,000 milk cows with muslin halter and bronze pails. 84,000 maidens bedecked with jeweled earrings. 84,000 couches spread with woolen covers—shag-piled, pure white, or embroidered with flowers—and spread with a fine deer hide, with canopies above and red pillows at both ends. 8,400,000,000 cloths of delicate linen, cotton, silk, and wool. And who can say how much food, drink, snacks, meals, refreshments, and beverages? It seemed like an overflowing river.

Householder, you might think: ‘Surely the brahmin Velāma must have been someone else at that time?’ But you should not see it like this. I myself was the brahmin Velāma at that time. I gave that gift, a great offering. But at that event there was no one worthy of a religious donation, and no one to purify the religious donation.

It would be more fruitful to feed one individual accomplished in view than that great offering of Velāma.

It would be more fruitful to feed one once-returner than a hundred of those accomplished in view.

It would be more fruitful to feed one non-returner than a hundred once-returners.

It would be more fruitful to feed one perfected one than a hundred non-returners.

It would be more fruitful to feed one independent Buddha than a hundred perfected ones.

It would be more fruitful to feed one Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha than a hundred independent Buddhas.

It would be more fruitful to feed the mendicant Saṅgha headed by the Buddha than to feed one Realized One, a perfected one, a fully awakened Buddha.

It would be more fruitful to build a dwelling especially for the Saṅgha of the four quarters than to feed the mendicant Saṅgha headed by the Buddha.

It would be more fruitful to go for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha with a confident heart than to build a dwelling for the Saṅgha of the four quarters.

It would be more fruitful to undertake the training rules—not to kill living creatures, steal, commit sexual misconduct, lie, or consume intoxicants of beer, wine, and liquor—than to go for refuge to the Buddha, the teaching, and the Saṅgha with a confident heart.

It would be more fruitful to develop a heart of love—even just as long as it takes to pull a cow’s udder—than to undertake the training rules.

It would be more fruitful to develop the perception of impermanence—even as long as a finger-snap—than to do all of these things, including developing a heart of love for as long as it takes to pull a cow’s udder.”

The Chapter on If You Want

AN 10.71 One Might Wish Ākaṅkhasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. There the Buddha addressed the mendicants, “Mendicants!”

“Venerable sir,” they replied. The Buddha said this:

“Mendicants, live by the ethical precepts and the monastic code. Live restrained in the monastic code, conducting yourselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, keep the rules you’ve undertaken.

A mendicant might wish: ‘May I be liked and approved by my spiritual companions, respected and admired.’ So let them fulfill their precepts, be committed to inner serenity of the heart, not neglect absorption, be endowed with discernment, and frequent empty huts.

A mendicant might wish: ‘May I receive robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick.’ So let them fulfill their precepts, be committed to inner serenity of the heart, not neglect absorption, be endowed with discernment, and frequent empty huts.

A mendicant might wish: ‘May the services of those whose robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick I enjoy be very fruitful and beneficial for them.’ So let them fulfill their precepts …

A mendicant might wish: ‘When deceased family and relatives who have passed away recollect me with a confident mind, may this be very fruitful and beneficial for them.’ So let them fulfill their precepts …

A mendicant might wish: ‘May I be content with any kind of robes, almsfood, lodgings, and medicines and supplies for the sick.’ So let them fulfill their precepts …

A mendicant might wish: ‘May I endure cold, heat, hunger, and thirst. May I endure the touch of flies, mosquitoes, wind, sun, and reptiles. May I endure rude and unwelcome criticism. And may I put up with physical pain—sharp, severe, acute, unpleasant, disagreeable, and life-threatening.’ So let them fulfill their precepts …

A mendicant might wish: ‘May I prevail over desire and discontent, and may desire and discontent not prevail over me. May I live having mastered desire and discontent whenever they have arisen.’ So let them fulfill their precepts …

A mendicant might wish: ‘May I prevail over fear and dread, and may fear and dread not prevail over me. May I live having mastered fear and dread whenever they arise.’ So let them fulfill their precepts …

A mendicant might wish: ‘May I get the four absorptions—blissful meditations in this life that belong to the higher mind—when I want, without trouble or difficulty.’ So let them fulfill their precepts …

A mendicant might wish: ‘May I realize the undefiled freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom, and live having realized it with my own insight in this very life due to the ending of defilements.’ So let them fulfill their precepts, be committed to inner serenity of the heart, not neglect absorption, be endowed with discernment, and frequent empty huts.

‘Live by the ethical precepts and the monastic code. Live restrained in the monastic code, conducting yourselves well and resorting for alms in suitable places. Seeing danger in the slightest fault, keep the rules you’ve undertaken.’ That’s what I said, and this is why I said it.”

AN 10.72 Thorns Kaṇṭakasutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Vesālī, at the Great Wood, in the hall with the peaked roof, together with several well-known senior disciples. They included the venerables Cāla, Upacāla, Kakkaṭa, Kaṭimbha, Kaṭa, Kaṭissaṅga, and other well-known senior disciples.

Now at that time several well-known Licchavis plunged deep into the Great Wood to see the Buddha. Driving a succession of fine carriages, they made a colossal racket. Then those venerables thought:

“These several well-known Licchavis have plunged deep into the Great Wood to see the Buddha. Driving a succession of fine carriages, they’re making a colossal racket. But the Buddha has said that sound is a thorn to absorption. Let’s go to the Gosiṅga Sal Wood. There we can meditate comfortably, free of noise and crowds.” Then those venerables went to the Gosiṅga Sal Wood, where they meditated comfortably, free of noise and crowds.

Then the Buddha said to the mendicants:

“Mendicants, where are Cāla, Upacāla, Kakkaṭa, Kaṭimbha, Kaṭa, and Kaṭissaṅga? Where have these senior disciples gone?”

And the mendicants told him what had happened.

“Good, good, mendicants! It’s just as those great disciples have so rightly explained. I have said that sound is a thorn to absorption.

Mendicants, there are these ten thorns. What ten? Relishing company is a thorn for someone who loves seclusion. Focusing on the feature of beauty is a thorn for someone pursuing the meditation on the feature of ugliness. Seeing shows is a thorn to someone restraining the senses. Lingering in the neighborhood of females is a thorn to chastity. Sound is a thorn to the first absorption. Placing the mind and keeping it connected are a thorn to the second absorption. Rapture is a thorn to the third absorption. Breathing is a thorn to the fourth absorption. Perception and feeling are a thorn to the attainment of the cessation of perception and feeling. Greed, hate, and delusion are thorns.

Mendicants, live free of thorns! Live rid of thorns! Mendicants, live free of thorns and rid of thorns! The perfected ones live free of thorns, rid of thorns, free and rid of thorns.”

AN 10.73 Likable Iṭṭhadhammasutta

“Mendicants, these ten likable, desirable, and agreeable things are rare in the world. What ten? Wealth, beauty, health, ethical conduct, the spiritual life, friends, learning, wisdom, good qualities, and heaven are likable, desirable, and agreeable things that are rare in the world.

Ten things are roadblocks for these ten likable, desirable, and agreeable things that are rare in the world. Sloth and lack of initiative are a roadblock for wealth. Lack of adornment and decoration are a roadblock for beauty. Unsuitable activity is a roadblock for health. Bad friendship is a roadblock for ethical conduct. Lack of sense restraint is a roadblock for the spiritual life. Dishonesty is a roadblock for friends. Not rehearsing is a roadblock for learning. Not wanting to listen and ask questions are roadblocks for wisdom. Lack of commitment and reviewing are roadblocks for good qualities. Wrong practice hinders heaven. These ten things are roadblocks for these ten likable, desirable, and agreeable things that are rare in the world.

Ten things nourish these ten likable, desirable, and agreeable things that are rare in the world. Application and initiative nourish wealth. Adornment and decoration nourish beauty. Suitable activity nourishes health. Good friendship nourishes ethical conduct. Sense restraint nourishes the spiritual life. Honesty nourishes friends. Rehearsing nourishes learning. Eagerness to listen and ask questions nourishes wisdom. Commitment and reviewing nourish good qualities. Right practice nourishes heaven. These ten things nourish these ten likable, desirable, and agreeable things that are rare in the world.”

AN 10.74 Growth Vaḍḍhisutta

“Mendicants, a noble disciple who grows in ten ways grows nobly, taking on what is essential and excellent in this life. What ten? He grows in fields and lands, money and grain, wives and children, in bondservants, workers, and staff, and in livestock. And he grows in faith, ethics, learning, generosity, and wisdom. A noble disciple who grows in ten ways grows nobly, taking on what is essential and excellent in this life.

Someone who grows in money and grain,
in wives, children, and livestock,
is wealthy, famous, and respected
by relatives and friends, and even by royals.

When someone grows in faith and ethics,
wisdom, and both generosity and learning—
a good man such as he sees clearly,
and in this very life he grows in both ways.”

AN 10.75 With Migasālā Migasālāsutta

At one time the Buddha was staying near Sāvatthī in Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍika’s monastery. Then Venerable Ānanda robed up in the morning and, taking his bowl and robe, went to the home of the laywoman Migasālā, where he sat down on the seat spread out. Then the laywoman Migasālā went up to Ānanda, bowed, sat down to one side, and said to him:

“Honorable Ānanda, how on earth are we supposed to understand the teaching taught by the Buddha, when the chaste and the unchaste are both reborn in exactly the same place in the next life? My father Purāṇa was chaste, set apart, refraining from the vulgar act of sex. When he passed away the Buddha declared that, since he was a once-returner, he was reborn in the host of joyful gods. But my uncle Isidatta was not chaste; he lived content with his wife. When he passed away the Buddha declared that, since he too was a once-returner, he was reborn in the host of joyful gods.

How on earth are we supposed to understand the teaching taught by the Buddha, when the chaste and the unchaste are both reborn in exactly the same place in the next life?”

“You’re right, sister, but that’s how the Buddha declared it.”

Then Ānanda, after receiving almsfood at Migasālā’s home, rose from his seat and left. Then after the meal, on his return from almsround, Ānanda went to the Buddha, bowed, sat down to one side, and told him what had happened.

“Ānanda, who is this laywoman Migasālā, a foolish incompetent aunty, with an aunty’s wit? And who is it that knows how to assess individual persons?

These ten individuals are found in the world. What ten? Take a certain individual who is unethical. And they don’t truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that unethical conduct ceases without remainder. And they’ve not listened or learned or penetrated theoretically or found even temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a lower place, not a higher. They’re going to a lower place, not a higher.

Take a certain individual who is unethical. But they truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that unethical conduct ceases without remainder. And they’ve listened and learned and penetrated theoretically and found at least temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a higher place, not a lower. They’re going to a higher place, not a lower.

Judgmental people compare them, saying: ‘This one has just the same qualities as the other, so why is one worse and one better?’ This will be for their lasting harm and suffering.

In this case, the individual who is unethical, but truly understands the freedom of heart … and has listened and learned and penetrated theoretically and found at least temporary freedom is better and finer than the other individual. Why is that? Because the stream of the teaching carries them along. But who knows the difference between them except a Realized One? So, Ānanda, don’t be judgmental about individuals. Don’t pass judgment on individuals. Those who pass judgment on individuals harm themselves. I, or someone like me, may pass judgment on people.

Take a certain individual who is ethical. But they don’t truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that ethical conduct ceases without remainder. And they’ve not listened or learned or penetrated theoretically or found even temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a lower place, not a higher. They’re going to a lower place, not a higher.

Take a certain individual who is ethical. And they truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that ethical conduct ceases without remainder. And they’ve listened and learned and penetrated theoretically and found at least temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a higher place, not a lower. They’re going to a higher place, not a lower.

Judgmental people compare them … I, or someone like me, may pass judgment on individuals.

Take a certain individual who is very lustful. And they don’t truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that lust ceases without remainder. And they’ve not listened or learned or penetrated theoretically or found even temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a lower place, not a higher. They’re going to a lower place, not a higher.

Take a certain individual who is very lustful. But they truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that lust ceases without remainder. And they’ve listened and learned and penetrated theoretically and found at least temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a higher place, not a lower. They’re going to a higher place, not a lower.

Judgmental people compare them … I, or someone like me, may pass judgment on individuals.

Take a certain individual who is irritable. And they don’t truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that anger ceases without remainder. And they’ve not listened or learned or penetrated theoretically or found even temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a lower place, not a higher. They’re going to a lower place, not a higher.

Take a certain individual who is irritable. But they truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that anger ceases without remainder. And they’ve listened and learned and penetrated theoretically and found at least temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a higher place, not a lower. They’re going to a higher place, not a lower.

Judgmental people compare them … I, or someone like me, may pass judgment on individuals.

Take a certain individual who is restless. And they don’t truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that restlessness ceases without remainder. And they’ve not listened or learned or penetrated theoretically or found even temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a lower place, not a higher. They’re going to a lower place, not a higher.

Take a certain individual who is restless. But they truly understand the freedom of heart and freedom by wisdom where that restlessness ceases without remainder. And they’ve listened and learned and penetrated theoretically and found at least temporary freedom. When their body breaks up, after death, they depart for a higher place, not a lower. They’re going to a higher place, not a lower.

Judgmental people compare them, saying: ‘This one has just the same qualities as the other, so why is one worse and one better?’ This will be for their lasting harm and suffering.

In this case, the individual who is restless, but truly understands the freedom of heart … and has listened and learned and penetrated theoretically and found at least temporary freedom is better and finer than the other individual. Why is that? Because the stream of the teaching carries them along. But who knows the difference between them except a Realized One? So, Ānanda, don’t be judgmental about individuals. Don’t pass judgment on individuals. Those who pass judgment on individuals harm themselves. I, or someone like me, may pass judgment on individuals.

Who is this laywoman Migasālā, a foolish incompetent aunty, with an aunty’s wit? And who is it that knows how to assess individual persons? These ten individuals are found in the world.

If Isidatta had achieved Purāṇa’s level of ethical conduct, Purāṇa could not have even known Isidatta’s destination. And if Purāṇa had achieved Isidatta’s level of wisdom, Isidatta could not have even known Purāṇa’s destination. So both individuals were lacking in one respect.”

AN 10.76 Three Things Tayodhammasutta

“Mendicants, if three things were not found, the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha would not arise in the world, and the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One would not shine in the world. What three? Rebirth, old age, and death. If these three things were not found, the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha would not arise in the world, and the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One would not shine in the world. But since these three things are found, the Realized One, the perfected one, the fully awakened Buddha arises in the world, and the teaching and training proclaimed by the Realized One shines in the world.

Without giving up three things you can’t give up rebirth, old age, and death. What three? Greed, hate, and delusion. Without giving up these three things you can’t give up rebirth, old age, and death.

Without giving up three things you can’t give up greed, hate, and delusion. What three? Substantialist view, doubt, and misapprehension of precepts and observances. Without giving up these three things you can’t give up greed, hate, and delusion.

Without giving up three things you can’t give up substantialist view, doubt, and misapprehension of precepts and observances. What three? Irrational application of mind, following a wrong path, and mental sluggishness. Without giving up these three things you can’t give up substantialist view, doubt, and misapprehension of precepts and observances.

Without giving up three things you can’t give up irrational application of mind, following a wrong path, and mental sluggishness. What three? Unmindfulness, lack of situational awareness, and scattered mind. Without giving up these three things you can’t give up irrational application of mind, following a wrong path, and mental sluggishness.

Without giving up three things you can’t give up unmindfulness, lack of situational awareness, and scattered mind. What three? Not wanting to see the noble ones, not wanting to hear the teaching of the noble ones, and a fault-finding mind. Without giving up these three things you can’t give up unmindfulness, lack of situational awareness, and scattered mind.

Without giving up three things you can’t give up not wanting to see the noble ones, not wanting to hear the teaching of the noble ones, and a fault-finding mind. What three? Restlessness, lack of restraint, and unethical conduct. Without giving up these three things you can’t give up not wanting to see the noble ones, not wanting to hear the teaching of the noble ones, and a fault-finding mind.

Without giving up three things you can’t give up restlessness, lack of restraint, and unethical conduct. What three? Faithlessness, uncharitableness, and laziness. Without giving up these three things you can’t give up restlessness, lack of restraint, and unethical conduct.

Without giving up three things you can’t give up faithlessness, uncharitableness, and laziness. What three? Disregard, being hard to admonish, and having bad friends. Without giving up these three things you can’t give up faithlessness, uncharitableness, and laziness.

Without giving up three things you can’t give up disregard, being hard to admonish, and having bad friends. What three? Lack of conscience, imprudence, and negligence. Without giving up these three things you can’t give up disregard, being hard to admonish, and having bad friends.

Mendicants, someone who lacks conscience and prudence is negligent. When you’re negligent you can’t give up disregard, being hard to admonish, and having bad friends. When you’ve got bad friends you can’t give up faithlessness, uncharitableness, and laziness. When you’re lazy you can’t give up restlessness, lack of restraint, and unethical conduct. When you’re unethical you can’t give up not wanting to see the noble ones, not wanting to hear the teaching of the noble ones, and a fault-finding mind. When you’ve got a fault-finding mind you can’t give up unmindfulness, lack of situational awareness, and a scattered mind. When your mind is scattered you can’t give up irrational application of mind, following a wrong path, and mental sluggishness. When your mind is sluggish you can’t give up substantialist view, doubt, and misapprehension of precepts and observances. When you have doubts you can’t give up greed, hate, and delusion. Without giving up greed, hate, and delusion you can’t give up rebirth, old age, and death.

After giving up three things you can give up rebirth, old age, and death. What three? Greed, hate, and delusion. After giving up these three things you can give up rebirth, old age, and death.

After giving up three things you can give up greed, hate, and delusion. What three? Substantialist view, doubt, and misapprehension of precepts and observances. After giving up these three things you can give up greed, hate, and delusion.

After giving up three things you can give up substantialist view, doubt, and misapprehension of precepts and observances. What three? Irrational application of mind, following a wrong path, and mental sluggishness. After giving up these three things you can give up substantialist view, doubt, and misapprehension of precepts and observances.

After giving up three things you can give up irrational application of mind, following a wrong path, and mental sluggishness. What three? Unmindfulness, lack of situational awareness, and a scattered mind. After giving up these three things you can give up irrational application of mind, following a wrong path, and mental sluggishness.

After giving up three things you can give up unmindfulness, lack of situational awareness, and scattered mind. What three? Not wanting to see the noble ones, not wanting to hear the teaching of the noble ones, and a fault-finding mind. After giving up these three things you can give up unmindfulness, lack of situational awareness, and scattered mind.

After giving up three things you can give up not wanting to see the noble ones, not wanting to hear the teaching of the noble ones, and a fault-finding mind. What three? Restlessness, lack of restraint, and unethical conduct. After giving up these three things you can give up not wanting to see the noble ones, not wanting to hear the teaching of the noble ones, and a fault-finding mind.

After giving up three things you can give up restlessness, lack of restraint, and unethical conduct. What three? Faithlessness, uncharitableness, and laziness. After giving up these three things you can give up restlessness, lack of restraint, and unethical conduct.

After giving up three things you can give up faithlessness, uncharitableness, and laziness. What three? Disregard, being hard to admonish, and having bad friends. After giving up these three things you can give up faithlessness, uncharitableness, and laziness.

After giving up three things you can give up disregard, being hard to admonish, and having bad friends. What three? Lack of conscience, imprudence, and negligence. After giving up these three things you can give up disregard, being hard to admonish, and having bad friends.

Mendicants, someone who has conscience and prudence is diligent. When you’re diligent you can give up disregard, being hard to admonish, and having bad friends. When you’ve got good friends you can give up faithlessness, uncharitableness, and laziness. When you’re energetic you can give up restlessness, lack of restraint, and unethical conduct. When you’re ethical you can give up not wanting to see the noble ones, not wanting to hear the teaching of the noble ones, and a fault-finding mind. When you don’t have a fault-finding mind you can give up unmindfulness, lack of situational awareness, and a scattered mind. When your mind isn’t scattered you can give up irrational application of mind, following a wrong path, and mental sluggishness. When your mind isn’t sluggish you can give up substantialist view, doubt, and misapprehension of precepts and observances. When you have no doubts you can give up greed, hate, and delusion. After giving up greed, hate, and delusion you can give up rebirth, old age, and death.”

AN 10.77 A Crow Kākasutta

“Mendicants, a crow possesses ten bad qualities. What ten? They’re rude and impudent, gluttonous and voracious, cruel and pitiless, weak and raucous, unmindful and acquisitive. A crow possesses these ten bad qualities. In the same way, a bad mendicant possesses these ten bad qualities. What ten? They’re rude and impudent, gluttonous and voracious, cruel and pitiless, weak and raucous, unmindful and acquisitive. A bad mendicant possesses these ten bad qualities.”

AN 10.78 Jains Nigaṇṭhasutta

“Mendicants, Jain ascetics possess ten bad qualities. What ten? They’re faithless and unethical, without conscience or prudence, and devoted to untrue persons. They glorify themselves and put others down. They’re attached to their own views, holding them tight, and refusing to let go. They’re deceptive, with corrupt wishes and bad friends. Jain ascetics possess these ten bad qualities.”

AN 10.79 Grounds for Resentment Āghātavatthusutta

“Mendicants, there are ten grounds for resentment. What ten? Thinking: ‘They did wrong to me,’ you harbor resentment. Thinking: ‘They are doing wrong to me’ … ‘They will do wrong to me’ … ‘They did wrong by someone I love’ … ‘They are doing wrong by someone I love’ … ‘They will do wrong by someone I love’ … ‘They helped someone I dislike’ … ‘They are helping someone I dislike’ … Thinking: ‘They will help someone I dislike,’ you harbor resentment. You get angry for no reason. These are the ten grounds for resentment.”

AN 10.80 Getting Rid of Resentment Āghātapaṭivinayasutta

“Mendicants, there are these ten ways to get rid of resentment. What ten? Thinking: ‘They harmed me, but what can I possibly do?’ you get rid of resentment. Thinking: ‘They are harming me …’ … ‘They will harm me …’ … ‘They harmed someone I love …’ … ‘They are harming someone I love …’ ‘They will harm someone I love …’ … They helped someone I dislike …’ … ‘They are helping someone I dislike …’ … Thinking: ‘They will help someone I dislike, but what can I possibly do?’ you get rid of resentment. And you don’t get angry for no reason. These are the ten ways of getting rid of resentment.”